<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://segonku.unl.edu/teianalytics/TEIAnalytics.rng"
                        type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="bonner.xml">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dialect Tales:   
Electronic Edition.</title>
            <author>McDowell, Katherine Sherwood Bonner, 1849-1883</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
               <name> Don Sechler</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Text encoded by</resp>
               <name>Jamie Vacca and Natalia Smith </name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>First edition, <date>1997.</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>ca. 500K</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
            <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
            <date>1997.</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Call number PS2357 .D5 1883 (Davis Library, UNC-CH)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc default="false">
            <bibl default="false">
               <title>Dialect Tales</title>
               <author>McDowell, Katherine Sherwood Bonner (pseud. Sherwood Bonner)</author>imprint<pubPlace>New York,</pubPlace>
               <publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers, Franklin Square </publisher>
               <date>1883</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc default="false">
            <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
 database <hi rend="italics">“A Digitized Library of  Southern Literature: Beginnings to 1920.”</hi>
            </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl default="false">
            <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
            <p>All quotation marks and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
            <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
            <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
            <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
            <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
            <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell checkers.</p>
            <p>All the illustrations from the original may be accessed at http://sunsite.unc.edu/docsouth/southlit.html.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="cover_image">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>[Cover Image]</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece_image">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>“DE PARSTER OF DE FUST METHODIS' CHURCH, LIMITED.” [Page 32.<lb/>[Frontispiece Image]</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_image">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">DIALECT TALES</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY</byline>
            <docAuthor>SHERWOOD BONNER</docAuthor>
            <docEdition>
               <hi rend="italics">ILLUSTRATED</hi>
            </docEdition>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK</pubPlace>
               <publisher>HARPER &amp; BROTHERS, FRANKLIN SQUARE</publisher>
               <docDate>1883</docDate>
            </docImprint>
            <titlePart type="verso">
               <date>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1883, by</date>
HARPER &amp; BROTHERS
In the Office of the Librarian of Congress, at Washington.
<hi rend="italics">All rights reserved.</hi>
            </titlePart>
         </titlePage>
         <div type="dedication" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <p>
               <hi rend="italics">Dedicated</hi>
TO MY DEAR FRIEND MRS. S. B. S.
WITH LOVE AND GRATITUDE.</p>
            <lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
               <l part="N">
                  <hi>Her angel face,</hi>
               </l>
               <l part="N">
                  <hi>As the great eye of Heaven, shined bright,</hi>
               </l>
               <l part="N">
                  <hi>And made a sunshine in a shady place.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list type="simple">
               <item>THE GENTLEMEN OF SARSAR . . . . <ref target="bonner9">9</ref>
               </item>
               <item>ON THE NINE-MILE . . . . <ref target="bonner38">38</ref>
               </item>
               <item>HIERONYMUS POP AND THE BABY . . . . <ref target="bonner68">68</ref>
               </item>
               <item>SISTER WEEDEN'S PRAYER . . . . <ref target="bonner81">81</ref>
               </item>
               <item>AUNT ANNIKY'S TEETH . . . . <ref target="bonner93">93</ref>
               </item>
               <item>DR. JEX'S PREDICAMENT . . . . <ref target="bonner107">107</ref>
               </item>
               <item>IN AUNT MELY'S CABIN . . . . <ref target="bonner119">119</ref>
               </item>
               <item>THE CASE OF ELIZA BLEYLOCK . . . . <ref target="bonner134">134</ref>
               </item>
               <item>THE BRAN DANCE AT THE APPLE SETTLEMENT . . . . <ref target="bonner151">151</ref>
               </item>
               <item>LAME JERRY . . . . <ref target="bonner162">162</ref>
               </item>
               <item>JACK AND THE MOUNTAIN PINK . . . . <ref target="bonner172">172</ref>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <pb n="7"/>
         <div org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <head>ILLUSTRATIONS.</head>
            <list type="simple">
               <item>“DE PARSTER OF DE FUST METHODIS CHURCH, LIMITED” . . . . 
Frontispiece</item>
               <item>“DIS AIN'T NUTHIN SHORT OF MURDER, IT AIN'T” . . . . <ref target="bonner25">25</ref>
               </item>
               <item>HIERONYMUS 'S CHARGE . . . . <ref target="bonner68">68</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“WHAT 'S DAT?” . . . . <ref target="bonner69">69</ref>
               </item>
               <item>HIERONYMUS SINGS A SOOTHING DITTY . . . . <ref target="bonner71">71</ref>
               </item>
               <item>DISPOSING OF TIDDLEKINS . . . . <ref target="bonner74">74</ref>
               </item>
               <item>IN SUSPENSE . . . . <ref target="bonner75">75</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“DE WELL!” SHRIEKED MOTHER POP . . . . <ref target="bonner77">77</ref>
               </item>
               <item>RESUSCITATING TIDDLEKINS . . . . <ref target="bonner78">78</ref>
               </item>
               <item>HIERONYMUS RETURNS . . . . <ref target="bonner79">79</ref>
               </item>
               <item>TAIL-PIECE . . . . <ref target="bonner80">80</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“MY SOUL AN' BODY IS A-YEARNIN' FUR A HAN'SUM CHANY SET O'
	TEEF” . . . . <ref target="bonner94">94</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“HONEY, YER AIN'T HARF AS SMART AS YER THINKS YER IS!” . . . . <ref target="bonner99">99</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“IT WUZ ANNIKY'S TEEF” . . . . <ref target="bonner101">101</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“BLESS YOU, CHILE, IT WUZ DE TEEF I WANTED, NOT DE MAN!” . . . .<ref target="bonner106">106</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“COULDN'T I SLEEP IN DE KITCHEN?” . . . . <ref target="bonner109">109</ref>
               </item>
               <item>DR. JEX . . . . <ref target="bonner112">112</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“HOLD ME!” CRIED THE DOCTOR . . . . <ref target="bonner116">116</ref>
               </item>
               <pb n="8"/>
               <item>REPAIRING DAMAGES . . . . <ref target="bonner118">118</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“THE PEDDLER COULD HARDLY KEEP BACK A SHOUT” . . . .  <ref target="bonner145">145</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“SHE LEANED HER HEAD AGAINST A TREE” . . . . <ref target="bonner149">149</ref>
               </item>
               <item>GRANDPA APPLE . . . . <ref target="bonner153">153</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“MARAS TOM SAY HE DONE GIN OUT DE NOTION” . . . . <ref target="bonner156">156</ref>
               </item>
               <item>THE BRAN DANCE . . . . <ref target="bonner157">157</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“JACK APPLE STEPPED IN, AN OPEN CLASP-KNIFE IN ONE 
HAND” . . . . <ref target="bonner160">160</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“‘GOOD-DAY,’ HE SAID, TAKING OFF HIS HAT” . . . . <ref target="bonner173">173</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“‘NONE O' YO' SHOOT IN',’ SAID SINCERITY” . . . . 
<ref target="bonner179">179</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“‘NO, YOU DON T, JACK BODDY!’” . . . . <ref target="bonner181">181</ref>
               </item>
               <item>“A MOUNTAIN PINK!” . . . . <ref target="bonner187">187</ref>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb n="9"/>
         <div type="main" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <head type="main">DIALECT TALES.</head>
            <div type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
               <head>THE GENTLEMEN OF SARSAR.</head>
               <div type="subchapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>SARSAR! The very name of the place was sinister! Who
does not remember De Quincey's “Sarsar wind of desolation,”
and the chill shudder that quivered through the soul as
the harsh adjective came blowing like a discord into the music
of that incomparable writing?</p>
                  <p>Not a misgiving, however, crossed my heart when, shortly
before Christmas, my father asked me if I thought myself
possessed of the qualifications necessary for collecting a bad
debt.</p>
                  <p>“The business of collecting, father,” said I, with what
malicious friends called my “prize-poem manner,” “is odious in
some of its features to a man of spirit; but it may bring into
play some of the finest faculties of the human mind.”</p>
                  <p>“And body,” added my father, in a quiet sort of way.</p>
                  <p>“If courage is needed,” said I, laughing, “I am the son of
my State—the State that does not know how to surrender!
<pb n="10"/>
As for tact, civility, address, urbanity, and downright stubbornness,
these desirable qualities are surely mine by right of
inheritance.”</p>
                  <p>“Well, well,” said my father, meditatively, “it is a pretty
rough place, Sarsar is. The debt is one thousand dollars; and
if you get this sum, or any part of it, I don't mind saying it
is yours for a Christmas-box.”</p>
                  <p>For many reasons these were delightful words. First, while
I fully intended that my life should teem with good things, at
present it was as bare and empty as a sun-dried skull. My
father, with the best intentions in the world, was so indifferent
to the doctrines of Malthus as to become the parent of a
perfect brood of young ones, each of whom had to stand on
his own legs as soon as they were strong enough. I was at
the beginning of my career, and made shift to get on; but
such a sugar-plum as a thousand dollars had never dropped
into my mouth. As befitted my slim purse, I was madly,
unutterably in love—in love with Angie Bell, the prettiest girl,
I would swear, among a million picked beauties. With the
thousand dollars fairly mine, I should be able to offer her
those delicate attentions man delights to lavish on the woman
he adores—buggy drives and bonbons, new music, books, and
bouquets. Thus I should weave myself, as it were, into her
life, keep her little heart in a perpetual simmer of kindly
feeling, and dispose her to look tenderly on my encroaching
passion, nor resist when its tide should sweep her from her
moorings into my arms. Unless—reflected I—it might be better
to trust to winning her solely on my merits, and, the
betrothal an accomplished fact, spend all the sum in the
<pb n="11"/>
purchase of a troth gift in some degree worthy of her inspiring
beauty. </p>
                  <p>Absorbed in the pleasing perplexity of such a question, I
was only aroused from my reverie by my father's tones, raised
a good deal above their ordinary level.</p>
                  <p>“Yes, old Ruck is as saucy and rough a tonic as any man
could swallow. You will need all your mother-wit in dealing
with him. The old scamp swears it is not a just debt, and
pay it he will not.”</p>
                  <p>“Sarsar—nothing more than a backwoods settlement,
is it?”</p>
                  <p>“Nothing. And there are people up among those hills
who actually try to vote for General Jackson to-day! A good
many worthless negroes have congregated in the place, who
fight, quarrel, and steal without much interference from anybody.
There are a lot of rough fellows, however, calling themselves
‘the Gentlemen of Sarsar,' who regulate things after
their own fashion. Chief among them is <hi rend="italics">your</hi> man—Andy
Rucker. He has unbounded influence with his <hi rend="italics">clientèle</hi>, and,
they say, understands how to use the shot-gun better than any
man in the county.”</p>
                  <p>“Never think to daunt me, father,” said I, briskly. “I shall
go to Sarsar, and shall fetch back the money.”</p>
                  <p>A few days later I got off at a station ten miles east of
Sarsar, and, hiring a horse, set out for a ride across the country.
The hills were steep, the road rough, the people rougher.
At the cabins where I stopped to ask the way they looked on
me as a stranger from a far-off land.</p>
                  <p>“Do git down and look at your creetur,” was their
<pb n="12"/>
invariable remark, and one that puzzled me exceedingly, until I
found it was an hospitable invitation to dismount for a rest.</p>
                  <p>Reaching Sarsar, I was directed to “the Widow Joplin's”
as a place of entertainment. The widow, a tired-looking
woman, with her lips drawn down at the corners as if they
needed kissing into shape, put me into the hands of a bright
mulatto boy, whom she called Dee Jay. This worthy
conducted me to my chamber, and asked if I would like some
oysters for supper.</p>
                  <p>“Oysters, by all means; a couple of dozen, fancy roast.”</p>
                  <p>“Lor', marster, we ain't got so many in de house; an' <hi rend="italics">ef</hi>
we had, I 'clar to gracious, marster, two dozen two-poun' cans
would kill you, sho'.”</p>
                  <p>“<hi rend="italics">Cans!</hi> Is it canned oysters you offered me?”</p>
                  <p>“Yes, sir —Cove. We had some fresh ones onct—I
disremember what year it wus. But, lor'! we didn't know how ter
open 'em, an' we jest pounded away at 'em wid brickbats till
Mars' Andy come an' showed us how. Ain't it curus how dey
kin live an' breathe de breff o' life shet up in dem tight
shells?”</p>
                  <p>Declining to enter into a discussion on, oysters, I asked if
“Mars' Andy” was Mr. Rucker.</p>
                  <p>“Yes, sir. Captin Rucker we mostly calls him. You
acquainted wid him?”</p>
                  <p>“No; but to make his acquaintance happens to be my
business here.”</p>
                  <p>“Is dat so?” cried Dee Jay, with increased respect in his
tones. “An' I made sho' you wus a-drummin' for seggars.
Mars' Andy ain't very fond o' dem drummin' men,” he went
<pb n="13"/>
on, confidentially; “in fac', dey ain't popular wid none o' dem
lazy, long-legged Rucker boys. Dey kin fairly devil a stranger
out o' toun if dey takes a notion. Hope you ain't gwine ter
tread on de captin's toes, marster. He's a awful man to have
a rassel wid.”</p>
                  <p>“He must -be a terrible fellow,” said I, laughing.</p>
                  <p>“Lor', dey ain't no harm in Mars' Andy. He's de head
man in dis toun. He's as full o' pranks an' capers as a
unbroke colt; but he's got as much sense as a horse.”</p>
                  <p>With that compliment, in every way worthy of a returned
Gulliver, my innocent Yahoo took me to the Widow Joplin's
dining-room.</p>
                  <p>Before I had well finished my supper a tall man strode into
the room, followed by two of the daintiest, prettiest little black-
and-tan thorough-bred pups I had ever seen.</p>
                  <p>“How Angie would dote on them!” thought I.</p>
                  <p>The master of the pups was a noticeable man. Tall and
broad-shouldered, with clean-cut features, and bright black eyes
—so far not differing from any other. But his hair marked
him among men as Samson's among the Philistines. Long
and heavy, and iron-gray in color, it fell in actual ringlets
to his shoulders, and gave almost a look of ferocity to his
countenance.</p>
                  <p>“A character!” said I to myself, and longed to hear him
speak.</p>
                  <p>The wish was not allowed to grow cold, as he came directly
to me with:</p>
                  <p>“I hear, sir, there is a stranger in town who wants to see
Andy Rucker. That's my name. Yours is—”</p>
                  <pb n="14"/>
                  <p>“Ned Merewether, at your service,” said I, rising, with
extended hand. “You have met my father.”</p>
                  <p>“Oh yes; I am well acquainted with Jack Merewether,”
he said, giving me a prolonged look. “Well, Ned, let's take
a drink.”</p>
                  <p>Knowing the offence I should give by a refusal, I assented,
though dreading the villanous compound I should have to
swallow under the name of “old bourbon.”</p>
                  <p>One drink followed another, and my head began to buzz
a little. Several men dropped in, who were introduced by Mr.
Rucker as kinsmen and friends. I proposed a health to “the
Gentlemen of Sarsar,” and the scene grew convivial.</p>
                  <p>“What d'ye think of our country, mister?” said an ill-looking
youth, whom they addressed by the tender title of “Honey
Rucker.”</p>
                  <p>“It's as fine a country as I ever saw,” responded I. “But
you don't have many rich men, I suppose?”</p>
                  <p>“Rich men!” cried Mr. Rucker, in a tone of compassion;
“why, youngster, we are <hi rend="italics">all</hi> rich, only we don't like to show
off. Good families—like the Ruckers—never make a parade.
Now and then such a fellow as Yowell wants to spread himself.
You remember, boys, how he went to old Nathan
Weeks's funeral?”</p>
                  <p>“Rather!” said Honey Rucker, in a gloomy tone.</p>
                  <p>“It was a big funeral, and most of us walked, for carriages
are unhandy on our roads. But Yowell wanted to make a
show, so he and his must ride. He and his wife were in a
four-wheeled gig, and every Jack and Gill of his seven
children was toted by a likely negro boy, who sat astride a two-
<pb n="15"/>
hundred-dollar mule. Now, each one of those Africans would
have sold for fifteen hundred dollars—aggregate, ten thousand
five hundred dollars; the mules summed up to fourteen hundred
dollars—making a clean sum of eleven thousand nine
hundred dollars winding along these hills as unconcerned as
a snake. What do you think of that for style?”</p>
                  <p>“Quite in the style of the Arabian Nights!” said I.</p>
                  <p>“ ‘Better worth seeing than the <hi rend="italics">aurora borealis</hi>,’ ” quoted
Mr. Honey Rucker.</p>
                  <p>“Ah! there are some queer people up here among these
hills,” said Captain Andy, with a shake of the head.</p>
                  <p>“What do you do in the way of sport?” asked I.</p>
                  <p>“Everything—chase foxes, run deer, spear fish. But our
grand sport”—with sudden animation—“our Christmas frolic,
is a nigger hunt.”</p>
                  <p>“A <hi rend="italics">what?</hi>”</p>
                  <p>“A negro chase perhaps you would call it. You see, our
jail is such a ram-shackle affair that it is next to impossible
to keep a prisoner in bonds, if he has any get-up-and-get in his
make-up. The rascals break out and take to the hills. And
when the humor takes us we hunt them down.”</p>
                  <p>There was a laughing devil in Mr. Rucker's eye, and I
knew not what to think. Determined, however, not to seem
unsophisticated, I said, coolly,</p>
                  <p>“I should think such game would give you but a short
run.”</p>
                  <p>“Humph! put twenty hounds on a black rascal's track—
they can scent it after it's a day old—and he will run faster
than a deer, and out-manoeuvre a fox in dodging corners.”</p>
                  <pb n="16"/>
                  <p>“Poor souls!”</p>
                  <p>“They haven't any souls, I fancy,” said Mr. Rucker, easily;
“ ‘poor bodies’ would be more to the point, as they have to
clip it to a galloping tune. Come, sir; no use walking on
stilts away from home. Join us in our next hunt.”</p>
                  <p>The man seemed as sober as a christened saint, but I felt
I was the butt of a joke, and secretly resented it.</p>
                  <p>“Well, sir,” said I, “I did not come here to make acquaintance
with the sports of the gentry.”</p>
                  <p>“And may I presume to ask why you <hi rend="italics">did</hi> come?” inquired Mr.
Rucker, with vast politeness.</p>
                  <p>“You should know best, sir, as I represent the firm of
Avery &amp; Merewether.”</p>
                  <p>“Aha! I remember something was said of certain moneys
that your people fancied I owed them.”</p>
                  <p>“Fancy me no fancies, Mr. Rucker”—certainly the whiskey
had gone into my head—“<hi rend="italics">the money has to be paid.</hi>”</p>
                  <p>“And you are the man that's to get it? Well, well, it
would be a pity you should not have what you have come so
far to gain—all, and more. I insist you should have more. I
myself ought to make you a little gift.”</p>
                  <p>“Very well,” I said, good-humoredly, “I will gladly accept
these little beauties”—and I caught up Mr. Rucker's pups.</p>
                  <p>“For your sweetheart?”</p>
                  <p>“For the prettiest girl in the county!” said I, laughing,
and with a warm glow at my heart at the bare thought of my
lovely little angel, Angie Bell.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="17"/>
               <div type="subchapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Awaking with a clear head the next morning, I hurried
out to seek Mr. Rucker; but, to my annoyance, that eccentric
gentleman was nowhere to be found. Every one of whom I
inquired was too stupid even to guess at his whereabouts.</p>
                  <p>“De captin is jes' like de sun,” said my sympathizing
valet, Dee Jay: “sometimes he will shine out on folks, an'
agin, when de notion takes him, he will go under a cloud, an'
you can't put your finger on de place whar he is hid.”</p>
                  <p>“And how long is it his majesty's pleasure to stay under a
cloud?”</p>
                  <p>“It 'ud take a wizard man to tell dat, marster.”</p>
                  <p>“I went to his house, hoping to see some member of his
family; but no one came to the door, though I rapped and
pounded half an hour.”</p>
                  <p>“He ain't got no family. De Rucker blood is purty nigh
run out in dis county.”</p>
                  <p>“Why, I thought every other man in it was a Rucker.”</p>
                  <p>“Well, dey is mostly cousins, or dey jes' tuk de name fur
glory. Mars' Andy had a lot of brothers onct, an' a par; but
dey wus killed, all along through de war—one a-bushwhackin',
one a-fightin' wid Morgan, one wid de fever, an' so on. Mars'
Andy hisself had a squeak fur his life onct on a time. He
wus lyin' on de field bleedin' from seventeen or eighteen
wounds, when along comes a calvary man a-swingin' of his
saviour—”</p>
                  <p>“Dee Jay! what in the name of Heaven are you saying?”</p>
                  <pb n="18"/>
                  <p>“Along comes a calvary man on a big black horse,
a-swingin' his saviour in de air till it looked as round as a
cart-wheel an' flashed like de moon on fire. Mars' Andy shet
his eyes an' begun ter say his prayers; when pop! bang! off
went a musket from behind a tree, an' down went Mr. Rider
jes' like a grasshopper when a turkey gobbler nips him off a
sweet-pertater vine!</p>
                  <p>“De captin tuk on mightily about our side gittin' beat,”
continued Dee Jay, encouraged by my laughter; “he ain't let
his hair grow sence Vicksburg fell, an' it turned grisly gray
dat same night. It was jes' struck all of a heap. Dat's why
de people here think so much o' Mars' Andy. Dey has sech
respec' fur his strong feelin's.”</p>
                  <p>“I wish his strong feelings would lead him to pay his
debts,” muttered I.</p>
                  <p>Mr. Rucker was not so cruel as to stay under a cloud all
day. In the afternoon he burst into my room, beaming like
the sun to which he had been compared.</p>
                  <p>“It's all settled, my friend,” he cried.</p>
                  <p>“What! the debt?”</p>
                  <p>“Bother the debt! A question of money should not arise
between gentlemen.”</p>
                  <p>“Gentlemen should pay what they owe,” said I, grimly.</p>
                  <p>“Softly, lad, softly. You are almost on the point of being
uncivil, in which case I should have to leave you to yourself.”</p>
                  <p>Dreading another disappearance on Mr. Rucker's part, I
said,</p>
                  <p>“Really, sir, I had no intention of being uncivil. What is
it that is settled?”</p>
                  <pb n="19"/>
                  <p>“The chase—the hunt for the horny-heeled son of Ham.”</p>
                  <p>“That joke again?”</p>
                  <p>“No joke about it. There is an idle fellow here—Bud
Kane by name—who was caught hog-stealing about a month
back. He has been hiding among the hills, and we think it
well to get him off our hands before Christmas.”</p>
                  <p>“You wouldn't kill the man?”</p>
                  <p>“Oh no; only scare him a bit. If he gives us a good run
we will let him off scot-free. And he is the fleetest scamp in
the country. Lucky to be able to offer you such sport.”</p>
                  <p>“My good Mr. Rucker,” said I, attempting to speak with
great moderation, “unequalled as such sport must be, you
must allow me to decline a share in it. You know my object
in coming here—”</p>
                  <p>“My dear fellow,” interrupted Rucker, “that is all right. I
have plenty of money burning for your pocket. But just now
I can't think of anything but the merry hunt! Come! let us
have it over, and then to business. I will promise that you
shall be fully satisfied. Perhaps, however, you are not a
rider?”</p>
                  <p>It was silly of me, but I was really piqued, and thought I
should like to show this rough man of Sarsar whether I could
ride or not. I reflected, too, that it might be well to humor
his wish and join his hunting-party—it would probably turn
out some portentous joke played by the Gentlemen of Sarsar.
After it was “played out,” Mr. Rucker could hardly fail to
meet my demands, hand over the money, and let me get back
to civilization—civilization and Angie Bell.</p>
                  <p>“Well, well,” said I, carelessly, “get me a decent mount,
<pb n="20"/>
and I'll join your party,” whereon Mr. Rucker gave a tremendous
grin and hurried away.</p>
                  <p>At a ridiculously early hour the next morning I was
aroused by a wild “Halloo!” under my window. Looking
out, I saw the Gentlemen of Sarsar in force—some twenty or
more vagabond-looking fellows, mounted on horses too nobly
built for such riders, all laughing, gesticulating, and occasionally
firing at the incautious chickens roosting in the trees
about the house. They were rigged out like a lot of banditti.
Some were armed with rifles, and all seemed to have equipped
themselves with what was left over from their war equipments,
including horse-pistols and bowie-knives, cavalry boots and
devil-may-care hats. I must say I felt uncommonly ticklish—
as much so as if I had been in Arabia with a set of Bedouins
inviting me for “sport” to plunder one of the desert caravans.
However, I gulped down my scruples with the morning cocktail
which we all took at the bar of the Widow Joplin, and
listened patiently while Mr. Rucker gasconaded about the
wonderful shots he had made, the tremendous leaps his horse
had taken over gullies and logs.</p>
                  <p>“Unless you can stand rip-racing through the country as
if you were trying to shake hands with the lightning,” said he,
“you had better not try to keep up with the hunt, but take a
stand on some overlooking hill—”</p>
                  <p>“Mr. Rucker,” cried I, “spare yourself any fears for me!”</p>
                  <p>“All right, then. Let's be off; boys!”</p>
                  <p>They leaped to their saddles with Texan agility; half a
dozen stag-hounds were brought to the front, and with another
“Halloo!” we were off.</p>
                  <pb n="21"/>
                  <p>Never shall I forget that ride. The keen morning air was
a stimulus that thrilled every sense to alertness. Mr. Rucker
carolled, in a robust voice:</p>
                  <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                     <l part="N">“Last night, in my late rambles,</l>
                     <l part="N">All in the isle of Skye,</l>
                     <l part="N">I met a lovely creature,</l>
                     <l part="N">All in the mountains high.”</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>But the only lovely creature we met was the lady-moon
queen of this wild world of wood and mountain and stream,
now almost out of sight, as day was beginning to dawn. The
hills, near and far, rose like waking giants to meet the pale,
blinking stars; lights twinkled from the valley below; little
piping birds mingled their shrill notes with the sound of the
wood-chopper's axe.</p>
                  <p>We rode at a brisk trot, Mr. Rucker and I in the rear.
Suddenly a cry was heard from one of the advance-guard. I
pressed forward, my mind's eye filled with a fine buck who
sniffed the “tainted gale” and sprung with beautiful fear
from his pursuers. Instead of which I saw a figure on<hi rend="italics"> two
legs</hi> —but </p>
                  <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                     <l part="N">“Whether man or woman,</l>
                     <l part="N">Whether ghoul or human,”</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>I could not tell at the distance—spring across the field as if
Satan's fiends were after him.</p>
                  <p>From this time all is confusion in my memory. Wild,
wild riding I recall, and a sense of reckless delight that vented
itself in shrill cries to my horse. The sun was just darting
up in slim scarlet lances. A light wind blew, and the very
drops of blood in my veins seemed to dance like the
<pb n="22"/>
pine-needles in the wind. What we pursued I no longer knew. I
was beside myself with the passion of the chase. Logs, bogs,
nor brooks appalled me. Fences and gullies were as shadows
leaped over in a dream. The infernal baying of the hounds
was music to my ear. Noble sport this, truly! Now and
then there was a glimpse of a flying figure—a male Atalanta
bounding over the ground with splendid speed; and finally
a sudden pull-up—a <hi rend="italics">something</hi> at bay—and a sound of rifles
snapping and hounds yelping.</p>
                  <p>“Fire, lad, fire!” cried Mr. Rucker.</p>
                  <p>“For God's sake tell me—is it a man?”</p>
                  <p>“Fire in the air, if you have any doubt,” he said, with a
great laugh, and firing his own rifle at a tree-top. Wild with
excitement, I essayed to do the same. My horse plunged—my
gun went off—an awful cry followed the report, and a
voice shrieked: “He has killed him! He has shot Bud
Kane!”</p>
                  <p>I leaped from my horse and rushed to the spot. There,
truly, lay a man—a muscular, finely-shaped young negro,
entirely nude but for a fox - skin thrown over his shoulders.
He was panting heavily, and his blood was staining the yellow
sedge-grass.</p>
                  <p>I could not believe my eyes. I was almost distracted.
Had<hi rend="italics"> I</hi> done this horrible deed? Had I slain an inoffensive
fellow-creature, whose hands were certainly clean toward me,
no matter how many Sarsar hogs he had stolen? Innocent
I felt myself, yet guilty with a horrible guiltiness; for there
lay the poor wretch bleeding, like Marco Bozzaris, and not
a man among them all spoke a word of comfort.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="23"/>
               <div org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>A LITTER was made of the boughs of pine-trees and Bud
Kane lifted upon it. Mr. Rucker and I rode in advance of
the bearers, to prepare Bud's mother for the reception of her
son.</p>
                  <p>“Man alive!” cried Andy, impatiently, “why did you not
fire in the air? Did you not see we were all doing so?”</p>
                  <p>“I saw nothing. Why did you lead me into such a devil's
business?”</p>
                  <p>“My dear Merewether,” he said in a cool, dry tone, “like
Shakspeare's Jew, you bettered my instruction.”</p>
                  <p>At the door of a particularly mean-looking cabin Mr.
Rucker called a halt. A veritable hag sat in the door-way—
old, black, lean, and wrinkled, but with a head of crisp wool
as bushy as a box-plant. This person was engaged in the
curious operation of “roping” her hair—that is, dividing it
into small strands, each one of which was wrapped tightly to
its end with a white cotton string.</p>
                  <p>“Hello, Aunt Diana!” said Mr. Rucker.</p>
                  <p>“Why, Mars' Andy! Dat you? What brings you here
dis hour in de mornin'? Want a drink o' buttermilk?”</p>
                  <p>“No; I've some bad news for you. Bud has met with an
accident.”</p>
                  <p>“What's dat you tell me?”</p>
                  <p>She sprung to her feet. Anything more uncanny and
witch-like than her appearance cannot be imagined. On one
side of her head her hair stood out like an electrified mane,
<pb n="24"/>
evidently fresh from a vigorous carding; on the other it lay
flat in little snaky cotton twists. Her eyes rolled till they
seemed all white. One hand was on her hip; the other
stretched toward us with clinched fist.</p>
                  <p>Mr. Rucker ran over the details of the accident without
mentioning my name. But she pinned me on the spot.</p>
                  <p>“I s'pose you did it,” she said, “seein' as you are a
stranger? Der ain't none o' de boys here would a-been so
clumsy.”</p>
                  <p>“Yes, my horse reared, and my gun went off accidentally.
I am very sorry—”</p>
                  <p>“Sorrow don't butter no corn-pone,” she interrupted, in a
high key. “I mistrusted sompen wrong yesterday when Mars'
Andy Rucker wus here persuadin' Bud ter take part in his
onmannerly, onchristian rampage.”</p>
                  <p>“What,” cried I, in a passion in my turn, “it was a sell,
then after all?”</p>
                  <p>Mr. Rucker smiled and shrugged his shoulders.</p>
                  <p>“You would a-thought so,” screamed Mother Kane, “if you
had a-heerd him beggin' Bud an' bribin' him to take de job.
Bud warn's noways anxious to dress hisself up in a fox-skin
an' go tarin' over de country, an' let de hounds be turned loose
on him. But says Mars' Andy, ‘We will post horses in de
thickets, so that you can ride from one point to annudder, an'
save your strength to dash across de open fields an' keep
ahead o' de hunt. An' it will be a big frolic, Bud,’ he says;
‘an' when it's done you shell have a quart o' rum an' five
dollars fur de night's work.’ Five dollars looked big enough
to cover de sun an' moon, it did! So he gin his consent, an'
<pb n="25"/>
                     <figure>
                        <p>“DIS AIN'T NUTHIN' SHORT OF MURDER, IT AIN'T.”</p>
                     </figure>
                     <pb n="27"/>
here's de end of it—Bud killed, an' me left ter scuffle along de
heavenly powers knows how!”</p>
                  <p>She threw her apron over her head and began to weep.</p>
                  <p>“I knowed mischief wus comin',” she sobbed. “Twarn't
on'y las' week dat ole Debby, de witch 'ooman, tole my fortune
on de shoulder-blade of a sheep, an' likewise de bres' bone of
a goose. ‘Troubles dark an' many,’ she says, ‘an' a funeral in
de house, an' a hard row ter hoe!’ An' I jis tell you, young
man”—dropping her apron and shaking her extraordinary old
head at me—“<hi rend="italics">I'll</hi> have de law of you. Dis ain't nuthin' short
of murder, it ain't.”</p>
                  <p>“It was an accident,” I cried; “and whatever I <hi rend="italics">can</hi> do to
make amends you may be sure I <hi rend="italics">will</hi> do.”</p>
                  <p>“Den you kin jist hen' me over some money fur de funeral
expenses an' odder matters.”</p>
                  <p>“How much do you want?”</p>
                  <p>“Jes' put it to yourself, sir. Don't you think if you wus
tore away from your pa, an' his ole age left widout support, he
would ax a purty high figger to cover de loss?”</p>
                  <p>“I think,” said I, with much internal bitterness, “if my
father could see me at this moment he would think twenty-five
dollars a high value for my head.”</p>
                  <p>“Well, gimme dat, marster, an' I'll be satisfied.”</p>
                  <p>I handed her the sum, and we left the house, just as the
men bearing Bud on the litter came in sight and the old
mother began her distracting screams.</p>
                  <p>“Rucker,” said I, as we rode away—“Rucker”—and my
voice trembled with rage—“as I am a living man you shall
give me satisfaction for this.”</p>
                  <pb n="28"/>
                  <p>“Let a harmless jest go by,” he said, coldly, “and consider
your own position. I am bound to tell you that you are in
some danger. The negroes here are a wild lot, and, backed
by certain lawless white men I could mention, would just as
soon lynch you as not.”</p>
                  <p>“That I own would be quite in keeping with what I have
seen of the Gentlemen of Sarsar.”</p>
                  <p>“We will discuss the matter farther when you are rested.
You look fagged out,” said Mr. Rucker, with an air of paternal
interest.</p>
                  <p>At the Widow Joplin's I shut myself into my room, and,
throwing myself on my bed, fell into as profound a sleep as if
to shoot a man before breakfast was nothing more serious
than to bag a lot of birds.</p>
                  <p>Toward noon Mr. Rucker came back. His face was drawn
into solemn lines, his ringlets hung damp and uncurled.</p>
                  <p>“Kane is dead,” he said.</p>
                  <p>“No!”</p>
                  <p>“The wound seemed a trifle at first; but traumatic tetanus
set in, and he went off like a shot.”</p>
                  <p>“I would give my right hand to undo this morning's
work.”</p>
                  <p>“Come, man, don't be cast down. My advice is that you
come with me at once to a magistrate and give yourself up.
I will go bail for your appearance at the April court. I need
not ask if you will be sure to be on hand?”</p>
                  <p>“If I allow you to be my bondsman such a question is an
insult,” said I, haughtily.</p>
                  <p>“Exactly. I will go your bail for—say two thousand dollars.
<pb n="29"/>
And since this sum, like the rod of Aaron, swallows
up the smaller amount you came to collect, we will let <hi rend="italics">that</hi>
matter rest over until you come on to your trial—eh?”</p>
                  <p>“I am in your hands, Mr. Rucker,” said I, fiercely, and
feeling like a rat in a trap, “and have no alternative but to
do as you suggest. But my father will be here as my legal
adviser, and I can tell you this whole thing will be well sifted.”</p>
                  <p>“Your father may count on my aid and friendship,” said
Mr. Rucker, with the air of a generous potentate, “both for
his sake and yours.”</p>
                  <p>As he spoke there was a rap at the door, and a trim
mulatto girl answered to my “Come in.” There was a gypsy
beauty in her bold black eyes, and mischief lurked in the
corners of her mouth; but she made a tolerably modest courtesy,
and said,</p>
                  <p>“If you please, sir, I wus gwine ter be married.”</p>
                  <p>“That is not surprising,” said Mr. Rucker, seeing me at a
loss how to reply to this unexpected confidence. “I should
think all the young bucks in the country would be after you.”</p>
                  <p>“I ain't gwine ter boast o' dat, Mars' Andy, for you knows
I never wus one o' dem flirtin', owdacious gals dat would jest
as soon sleep in de calaboose as anywhar else. But I wus
gwine ter marry decent an' respectable as any white lady, an'
have a gold ring an' piller-shams. An' now he's gone an' got
killed, and I ain't got nobody ter marry; and I jes' wish I was
dead, too.”</p>
                  <p>Here she began to weep, and, with a pang at the heart, I
realized that before me stood another victim of my fatal shot.
It was Bud Kane whom she was to marry!</p>
                  <pb n="30"/>
                  <p>“My poor girl—” said I.</p>
                  <p>“Don't you poor girl me!” she cried, viciously. “I'm jest
as free as anybody, and I don't want no foolin' nor soft talk
from you nor no other white gentleman!”</p>
                  <p>“Well, what <hi rend="italics">do</hi> you want?” said I, roughly.</p>
                  <p>“My circumstances is these,” she said, checking her tears: 
“that I have give up a good place I had at five dollars a
month, an' have spent all my savin's an' givin's a-buyin' weddin'
clothes an' a feather-bed, which I am meanin' to swap off to
the Widder Joplin for the tombstone of her fust husband, an'
set it up over poor Bud; the verses on it bein' ekally upproprite,
as they only says:</p>
                  <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                     <l part="N">‘He wus too bright fur earth,</l>
                     <l part="N">He wus taken from our hearth.</l>
                     <l part="N">Of angels ther wus a dearth,</l>
                     <l part="N">So they welcomed him with mirth.’ ”</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>“That is a fine idea of yours,” said Mr. Rucker; “but you
wander from the point.”</p>
                  <p>“No, sir, I'm jest a-comin' to it. Seein' as I am all throwed
out an' disadvantaged, I thought if I had ten or twelve dollars
I could go to town, an' git a place an' earn my livin'; an' it
looked like de gentleman dat shot Bud ought tu holp me
along a little to kerry out my projecs an' git de better o' my
afflictions.”</p>
                  <p>My hand was in my pocket. I pulled it out holding a bill,
and bade good-bye to Bud Kane's interesting sweetheart.</p>
                  <p>“You did well,” said Mr. Rucker; “a policy of conciliation
now, by all means.”</p>
                  <pb n="31"/>
                  <p>Our business at the magistrate's was soon transacted; but
after leaving his office we found it a matter of difficulty to get
past the crowd. A mob of negroes had collected, and muttered
threats made my blood run cold. Plainly Sarsar was no
longer a safe place for me.</p>
                  <p>On reaching the inn I found myself awaited at the door of
my room by an imposing-looking old darkey, with white hair
and a stout cane.</p>
                  <p>“Good-day, sir,” said he. “If your name is young Mr.
Merewether I would like a few words wid you.”</p>
                  <p>“All right, uncle; come in.” And I threw open the door
and flung myself into a chair.</p>
                  <p>“Give me de satisfacshun to intreduce myse'f,” said the old
man, with dignity, “as de parster of de Fust Methodis' Church,
limited.”</p>
                  <p>“Limited to what?” said I, profanely.</p>
                  <p>“To de godly an' to de seekers; an' to dis latter class our
departed brudder, Bud Kane, belonged. He wus a seekin'
sperrit.”</p>
                  <p>“Bud Kane again!”</p>
                  <p>“Dat pore wild lad lost his life as so many of our color
loses der manly sperrit—by submittin' to de white folks as if
dey wus monkeys instid o' men. But, in despite of Bud bein'
in some sort a son of Belial, he <hi rend="italics">wanted</hi> ter do what wus right;
an' he hed agreed ter give us a small sum toward erectin' a
edifice fur prayer an' praise, de present meetin'-house bein'
subject to rats, an' bats, an' rain, an' de bad boys of Sarsar.”</p>
                  <p>“I really don't see how this matter concerns <hi rend="italics">me!</hi>” cried I,
though, alas! I <hi rend="italics">did</hi> see with fatal clearness what he was after.</p>
                  <pb n="32"/>
                  <p>“I wus thinkin', marster,” he said, severely, “dat it mought be
a sort o' balm o' Gilead to your conscience to supply dat sum.”</p>
                  <p>“Better give him a trifle,” whispered Mr. Rucker; “he has
great influence among the blacks.”</p>
                  <p>There was no help for it. A five-dollar bill passed from
my keeping into that of the “parster of the Fust Methodis'
Church, limited.”</p>
                  <p>I began to pack my portmanteau.</p>
                  <p>“What are you about?” said Mr. Rucker.</p>
                  <p>“About to leave your town. I can catch the night train
at L --- by making good speed.”</p>
                  <p>“So you can; but take my advice again and leave that
luggage.”</p>
                  <p>“Leave my portmanteau? But why?”</p>
                  <p>“You won't be allowed to get away. The people are
keeping watch. I can manage it, however. Start out with
me as if for a friendly ride, and we can get on to L --- with
nobody the wiser; but if you start out with that carpet-sack I
won't answer for the consequences. I can send it after you in
a day or so.”</p>
                  <p>Again I had to submit—anything to get out of the
accursed place.</p>
                  <p>We mounted our horses, Mr. Rucker ostentatiously
remarking that we were going out for a little ride.</p>
                  <p>“You won't let him get away, Mars' Andy?” cried a voice.</p>
                  <p>“Have no fear, boys—he is in Andy Rucker's charge!”
exclaimed another.</p>
                  <p>Once away from them, I thought my trials at an end. But
there were yet other ordeals in store. From a cabin a shade
<pb n="33"/>
more dingy than Mother Kane's there rushed out a fat black
female, with three or four children hanging to her skirts.</p>
                  <p>“Stop, stop, gentlemen!” she cried, and we reined in
accordingly. She laid her hand on the bridle of my horse.</p>
                  <p>“Ain't you de gentleman dat killed Bud Kane?” she asked.</p>
                  <p>Bud Kane's name was fast becoming the red rag to the bull.</p>
                  <p>“What's that to you?” roared I.</p>
                  <p>“Jest this, sir—these is Bud's chillern.”</p>
                  <p>“I wonder if there is anything or anybody in this town
that Bud Kane is not in some way connected with?” said I,
violently. “I suppose <hi rend="italics">you</hi> want a little money to buy a black
frock?”</p>
                  <p>“I ain't pertickeler es ter the frock, but I need the money
powerful bad to help raise the chillern, fur Bud always wus
mighty fond of 'em”—and she too began to weep. “He
always said he meant ter have Julius Caesar educated. He
wus de favorite, because he wus de oldest, an' de fust chile
Bud ebber had. Den he made a gret pet o' Leonidas,
because he wus de youngest an' prized accordin'; an' de gal
—Mary Margeret—”</p>
                  <p>“Why, look here,” said I, “I have just seen a girl who told
me she was going to marry Bud.”</p>
                  <p>“Yes, sir, he tole me he wus gwine ter marry. He wanted
me to have him, but lor! I wouldn't marry Bud, <hi rend="italics">because he
didn't belong to de church!</hi>”</p>
                  <p>I looked at Mr. Rucker. A grin convulsed his features.
There was nothing to be said. I gave some money to the
worthy matron, and we rode on.</p>
                  <p>At last we were well out of Sarsar, and my spirits began to
<pb n="34"/>
rise. Suddenly we heard the clatter of a horse's hoofs coming
after us at a rapid gallop.</p>
                  <p>“We are pursued!” said Mr. Rucker.</p>
                  <p>“Let me give him a run for it,” I cried.</p>
                  <p>“No, no; wait here; guilt flies; you risk nothing in facing
whomsoever it may be.”</p>
                  <p>The pursuer turned out to be a lean little man, who
introduced himself as Dr. Mellar.</p>
                  <p>“I heard you were about leaving town, Mr. Merryfield,” he
said, briskly—“Merewether?—excuse me—and I wanted to
mention to you a little bill for attendance on the negro, Bud
Kane—his mother being unable to pay—and hearing you had
a fine feeling of honor—”</p>
                  <p>I got down from my horse, squared my elbows, doubled my
fists. “Come on!” said I.</p>
                  <p>“Are you mad?” cried the little doctor; and wheeling his
horse sharply round, he fled back to Sarsar.</p>
                  <p>Before I mounted again I deliberately loaded my pistol.</p>
                  <p>“This is a seven-shooter,” said I to Mr. Rucker. “One
ball is for the undertaker, one for the grave-digger, the odd
ones for any of the mourners who may wish to be paid for
weeping at Bud Kane's funeral.”</p>
                  <p>“I think,” cried Mr. Rucker, reeling slightly in his saddle,
as if convulsed by some internal emotion—“I really think we
have seen the last of them. You may shake the dust from
your feet, Mr. Merewether—you are out of Sarsar.”</p>
                  <p>It was shortly before Christmas that this adventure befell
me. Christmas-day dawned brightly, as it seemed, to all the
<pb n="35"/>
world but me. I had no heart to go to church, feeling in no
mood for the jubilant services. I was alone in the house,
and when there came a ring at the bell I answered the
door. There stood a remarkably tall, lithe negro man, with
my portmanteau in one hand, and in the other a little
covered basket.</p>
                  <p>“Christmas-gift, marster!” he cried.</p>
                  <p>“Merry Christmas to you. You can get a glass of eggnog
in the kitchen. I see you are from Sarsar. You have
brought back my portmanteau.”</p>
                  <p>“Yes, sir. Looks like you ought to know me by name,
young marster. You nearly shot my head off onct. Don't
you remember Bud Kane?”</p>
                  <p>“<hi rend="italics">Bud Kane!</hi>”</p>
                  <p>“Yes, sir; dat's me. Mars' Andy tole you I wus dead; but
dat wus jest a joke o' his. Somebody axed him what made
him act so hateful to you, an' he said onct afar wus two men
standin' on de Court-house steps, an' one of 'em ups and knocks
de odder off de steps; an' dey had him up fur 'salt an' battery.
An' de judge says, ‘What made you knock dat man offen de
steps? He wus a stranger ter you, an' not a-coin' no harm.’
An' de man says, ‘I knows it, judge; I didn't have nothin' agin
de fellow; but de truth is, <hi rend="italics">he stood so fair I couldn't help it.</hi>’ ”</p>
                  <p>And Bud Kane chuckled as if I would be at no loss to
apply his choice anecdote.</p>
                  <p>“Here's a note Mars' Andy sont you,” he added.</p>
                  <p>I took the note, and read as follows:</p>
                  <div type="letter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                     <p>“DEAR MEREWETHER,—I hope you don't bear malice. I know you will
be glad that Bud Kane is <hi rend="italics">not</hi> dead, and send this note by him to convince
<pb n="36"/>
you of the fact. Of course tile bail business was a farce; and I return the
money you so handsomely shelled out to the various claimants. And I must
do myself the justice to say that I had nothing to do with Mother Kane's
onslaught; that was unpremeditated and original.</p>
                     <p>“It is the season of forgiveness, so don't be backward about it. And,
in token of amity, accept the pups you admired—we call them Prince and
Pauper—and give them to your sweetheart. Come again to Sarsar on a
different errand, and I promise you a better welcome from rough old</p>
                     <closer>“<name>ANDY RUCKER.</name>”</closer>
                  </div>
                  <div org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                     <p>“You take those pups back,” said I, “and tell Mr. Rucker
that I will accept nothing at his hands.”</p>
                     <p>“Yes, sir,” said Bud, with a look of drollery; “but can't I
have my eggnog befo' I start back? Christmas-time, you know,
marster.”</p>
                     <p>“Oh yes, have all the eggnog you want; and when you are
ready to go come to me for a note I shall send to Mr.
Rucker.”</p>
                     <p>Bud Kane disappeared in the direction of the kitchen; and,
angry, mortified, humbled in my own esteem, I set myself to
the realization of how I had been duped. All the details of
the fine joke—just where truth ended and imposture began—
I should probably not know until I met Mr. Rucker. Then I
promised myself an explanation and an ugly quarrel.</p>
                     <p>While I brooded over the matter the pups got out of the
basket and began to frisk about the room. Then who should
come in but Angie, rosy and beautiful, on her way home from
church. Down she went on her knees before the little beauties
in black-and-tan; and then she went into such raptures over
them, and kissed them so many times, that I couldn't stand it,
but offered her them and myself on the spot! She accepted
<pb n="37"/>
the three of us; and the next thing I knew I had Angie,
Prince, and Pauper in my arms, and was pressing a first kiss
on her smiling lips. Pauper happened to be somewhere
between her heart and mine, and in consequence was so cruelly
squeezed as to give a piercing howl; but it was a rapturous
moment. I loved all the world; I blessed Andy Rucker; and
I forgave the Gentlemen of Sarsar!</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <pb n="38"/>
            <div type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
               <head>ON THE NINE-MILE.</head>
               <div type="subchapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <head>I.—JANEY.</head>
                  <p>WHAT I said when I first come as a boarder ter Mr. Jed
Burridge's house on the Nine-mile Perarer wuz that his
daughter Janey would be snapped up before she wuz twenty,
an' Mr. B. would hev ter look out fur another wife. But his
sister, Mis' Stackley—commonly called Little Mary Jane, owin'
to her short height, an' to her havin' been left a widder at the
age of eighteen—she says ter me, “I tell you, brother Jed
don't want no more wives.”</p>
                  <p>“Land!” says I, “how many has he had?”</p>
                  <p>“One,” says she, very severe, “an' that one a handful. Sister
Lucilly wuz a good woman, but ther' wuzn't such a driver
on the perarer, an' she kep' Jed on the jump. If he come in
to set down a minnit, it 'ud be ‘Jed, you peel them pertaters,’
or, ‘Jed, tear me off some carpet rags—change o' work will
rest ye.’ An' somehow, sence Lucilly wuz called, I've seen a
kind of expression of peace steal inter Jed's face that wuzn't
there o' former years.”</p>
                  <p>Amos Burridge's wife spoke up, an' says she, with a laugh,</p>
                  <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                     <l part="N">“ ‘Beneath this stone my wife cloth lie:</l>
                     <l part="N">She is at rest, and so am I.’ ”</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>“Ther' ain't nothin' o' that sort on Lucilly's tombstone,”
<pb n="39"/>
says another sister o' Jed's—sister Charity Hackleton, who
wuz a tall lady, shaped like a camel, an' powerful religious—
“but a nice, hullsome epitaff settin' forth the virtues of the
deceased, an' a text of Scripture appropriate.”</p>
                  <p>“That's neither here nor there,” says Nancy Jones as wuz,
who married the youngest o' the Burridge boys; “but as
to Janey Burridge bein' married afore she's twenty, I don't
believe she will be married at all. What with her mother
a-dyin' an' leavin' so much orthority in Janey's hands, the girl
is plum spoiled. Ther' ain't a Sunday but the house is filled
with beaux, an' she won't say yes, an' she won't say no. I
don't believe in no such doin's. It's flyin' in the face o' Providence.
When a girl has a good offer, she had ought ter take it.”</p>
                  <p>“No doubt o' that bein' your opinion, Nancy,” said Mis'
Amos, a-smilin' quite amiable; but, fur all that, Nancy colored
up like a turkey-cock, fur folks do say that she snapped at her
good offer afore ever it wuz made. But la! this is a slanderous
world.</p>
                  <p>“Eben will scatter the boys when he gits home,” says
Little Mary Jane; “he ain't a-goin' ter stand the entertainin'
of such a crowd.”</p>
                  <p>“Janey feeds her beaux high,” says I, parenthetical.</p>
                  <p>“Maybe that's the attraction,” sniffs Nancy Jones as wuz.</p>
                  <p>“Don't you believe it,” cries Amos B.'s wife, very prompt. 
“It's Janey herself they are after. An' no wonder. She's as
smart as a steel-trap, an' as pretty as a young pullet. She can
pick an'  choose.”</p>
                  <p>“Some folks' incinerations,” says Nancy, very furious, “is
about as nasty as this here wool we are a-pickin' out.”</p>
                  <pb n="40"/>
                  <p>It wuz at a wool-pickin' we wuz conversin', an' about this
time I had to leave, though very reluctant, as I did enjoy
a reg'lar set-to between Janey Burridge's aunts. Git 'em 
together, an' they use' ter make me think of a line of poetry
in my readin'-book at school:</p>
                  <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                     <l part="N">“An Austrian army awfully arrayed!”</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>They were free an' loud of voice as a pack of hounds, an'
when they didn't agree the din wuz tremenjus. Ther' wuz
four of 'em, two bein' Burridges by birth, an' two havin' married
inter the family. Certainly ther' wuz no porcity of aunts
to look after Janey, but as if enough wuzn't as good as a feast,
she always called me aunt too. I wuz no blood-kin to the
child, but my husband wuz connected in a roundabout way
with some o' the Burridges, so I wuz Aunt Fonie to most o'
the young folks, an' I wuz that fussless in my natur' that I
got on peaceable with the hull lot, though the aunts wuz as
tryin' as seven years' aguy, an' Janey would make a sassy
speech occasional. Fur instance, the day o' the wool-pickin',
when I got home she wuz leanin' on the gate a-chattin' ter
Roland Selph, who had been cock o' the walk on the perarer
sence he got religion in the spring. Janey's sleeves wuz rolled
up ter the shoulders, an' her arms wuz all dough, a- showin' she
had jest left her bread in the pan to rise or fall as the Lord
willed. “Bread an' beaux,” says I to her, speakin' mild but
impressive, “has both to be treated with attention; but the
Queen of England,” says I—“no, nor the Sar of Russia—
couldn't 'tend to the two simultaneous.”</p>
                  <p>“Well, Aunt Fonie,” cries Janey, “if a person can't do two
<pb n="41"/>
things at onct, what makes you think you can manage your
business an' mine too?”</p>
                  <p>I won't deny that my feelin's wuz hurt. People ought ter
be mighty careful what they say ter an isolate female whose
partner is a-restin' with the worms.</p>
                  <p>But somehow I never could stay mad with Janey. She
wuz such a cheerful person to have around: somethin' eternally
goin' on wher' she wuz. She wuz as good as a breeze
among leaves to set things a-goin'; an' she could turn out
more work in a day than most of us in a week. She wuz
powerful good-lookin' too, Janey wuz, with crisp black hair,
cheeks like apples, an' a big, laughin' mouth full o' white teeth,
that she akchilly thought as much of as if they wuz diamonds.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subchapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <head>II.—EBEN BURRIDGE COMES HOME.</head>
                  <p>Nobody don't consider a boy of much account. And I
don't say but that little Elick Farley had a hard time of it
at the farm. He wuz a child that Mr. Burridge had took out
of charity—a son of a distant niece of his, who had married a
young man by the name of Alexander Farley, from St. Louis.</p>
                  <p>It wuz the sort of marriage that the song of “Dixie” tells
about:</p>
                  <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                     <l part="N">“Ole mis' she acted a foolish part —</l>
                     <l part="N">She married a man dat broke her heart.”</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Not that Lex Farley meant ter be a bad man. He wuz kind,
and could make money hand over hand in the photographin'
line when he wanted to. But drink seemed ter have a lien on
him, an' he would spree in the awfullest way, always insistin',
when the fit wuz on him, that he should be called General
<pb n="42"/>
Harrison. What the p'int of this idea was nobody ever could
exactly see, except that it seemed a sort o' pride o' natur'
comin' out even when he wuz at the lowest pitch. But he
carrid on so ridickerlous in his spells that his wife's spirits
seemed to wear out. She wuz always weakly, an' she up an'
died. The only spark o' fun that wuz ever in the poor girl
showed itself on her dyin' bed.</p>
                  <p>“I think,” says she, smilin' very pitiful—“I do think I
might git up agen, if it wuzn't fur—“Then she stopped a
long while.</p>
                  <p>“If it wuzn't for what, Effie?” asks a neighbor.</p>
                  <p>“Fur General Harrison,” she whispers, very gentle.</p>
                  <p>After her death, Jed Burridge took her boy to bring him
up on the farm, out o' the reach o' temptation. Elick wuz a
wild flitter-gibbet, always a-needin' to be kept down, but a real
worker fur his age.</p>
                  <p>One of his chores wuz to go to the post-office. Most o'
the folks on the perarer wuz mighty neglectful as to mail
matter, trustin' usually to the chance of some neighbor
inquirin' fur 'em, or lettin' it run on indefinite; but Jed Burridge
always would keep up with things, bein' a man very
advanced in his notions. Once every week reg'lar, rain or
shine, Elick was sent in to the office; most ginerally Saturday
evenin's, so as Jed could git his paper, the Toledo Blade, fur
Sunday readin'. He didn't git to church frequent, but set up
an' chuckled an' swore alternate over that paper; fur it wuz
as hot as ginger, an' Jed, though a powerful peaceful man,
agreed with it all, an' rolled out politics like smoke if a
Democrat dropped in fur an argeyment.</p>
                  <pb n="43"/>
                  <p>On a special Saturday Elick fetched home a letter from
Eben Burridge to his pa, sayin' we might expect him by the
15th which wuz the following Sunday. Eben had been out in
Kansas fur a couple o' years, seekin' a place to locate. It
seemed he hadn't found one, however, fur the next day he
arrove at home, like Duffey after the third round, confident an'
smilin', as pompous an' self-satisfied a little man as ever I see.
After dinner the boys came a-droppin' in as usual, an' what
does he do but take the'r visits to hisself! When Janey come
to the sittin'-room door to bid 'em to supper, ther' wuz as
many as a dozen, lookin' at each other like gawks, but all very
perlite to Eben, wantin' to curry favor with Janey.</p>
                  <p>“Now, I take this as kind, boys,” says Eben, quite affable,
as we set round the table, “that you should all come so soon
to see me. It takes the old perarer fur good fellows. I tell
you, out yonder in Kansas it's scramble, scramble, an' everybody
a-suspicionin' of everybody. If ther' wuz a conflaggeration
of a neighbor's house, every man would be a-crowdin' in
ter see what he could git fur hisself in the way o' pelf, instead
o' helpin' to save a sufferin' fellow-creetur's goods.”</p>
                  <p>“Sho,” says Amos Burridge, “we ain't that bad, though
neither air we what we use' ter be. Fifty years ago, when I
settled here, you might talk. There wuzn't a merkenary man
among us. No pullin' an' haulin' an' cat-scratchin' ter git
ahead. Pervide enough ter eat fur yourself an' your stock,
an' you could ride aroun' the balance o' the time.”</p>
                  <p>“I'm sure ther's a-plenty of visitin' nowadays,” says I, likin'
always to hear my bob in conversation.</p>
                  <p>“ 'Tain't the same kind. Folks drop in, ter be sure; but
<pb n="44"/>
then they went fur a stayin' spell. The doors wuz made of
split boards two or three inches too short, an' when you left
home all you hed to do wuz ter throw a quilt over the top, an'
then folks would know you wuz out, an' wouldn't holler.”</p>
                  <p>“Mighty funny way ter make a door!” says Elick Farley.</p>
                  <p>“Ther' wuz no winders, don't you see. Not a pane o'
glass on the Nine-mile. I remember the first man that hed
any made half his front door of glass; an' it wuz a sort o'
guide: so many miles east or west o' the cabin with the glass
door, folks would say.</p>
                  <p>“Wonder what they say about our house?” says Elick,
stuffin' a laugh inter his throat with a piece of bread.
“Reckon they talk about t'other side o' wher' Janey Black-Eyes
lives.”</p>
                  <p>“Hold your jaw!” says Eben, fetchin' Elick a awful tweak
o' the ear.</p>
                  <p>Elick squeals out: “Ho! you stuck-up Kansas grasshopper!
Think the fellows come ter see you, do you? Ain't
got sense enough to know they're after Janey! They didn't
know you wuz looked fur. They comes every Sunday o' the
world. Ho! ho! and you thought you wuz so pretty that you
drawed the whole squad! Ef that ain't a joke I never!”</p>
                  <p>Them young men turned every color, from a pea-green to
a grizzly gray. An' Eben looked red and furious from one
ter another.</p>
                  <p>“Is this so?” says he, glarin' round. “Is it Janey you've
come ter set up with?”</p>
                  <p>As luck would have it, he looked straight at Roland Selph,
an' Roland sence he got religion had swore off from tellin'
<pb n="45"/>
lies, though the boys wuz always tryin' to git him in a tight
place where he couldn't speak the truth without a-hurtin'
somebody's feelin's.</p>
                  <p>Howsomever, Roland laughed, good-humored, an' says he,
“Wher' ther's honey you must look for flies, Eben.”</p>
                  <p>“Yes,” says Eben, very significant, an' lookin' as if he
would like to bite somethin', “and wher' ther's flies you can
look out fur fly-pizen. What have you to say fur yourself,
Charley Winn?”</p>
                  <p>“I have ter say that I come a-courtin' Janey,” says Mr.
Winn, as bold as brass; “an' she can take me or leave me
any day she says the word.”</p>
                  <p>“Brother Eben,” cries Janey, her face afire, “I wish you
wuz back in Kansas, that I do.”</p>
                  <p>“Very well,” says Eben, quite majestic, “I relieve you of
my company fur the present. “An' out he stalks, puffin' like
a mad gobbler.</p>
                  <p>“Boys, we'd better git our hats,” says Albert Thing.</p>
                  <p>They got up, and every last one of 'em slips away like a
whip-tailed hound.</p>
                  <p>Janey burst out a-cryin', without waitin' to wash up the
supper things.</p>
                  <p>“Of all the mean sneaks that ever wuz born, Ebenezer
Burridge, you are the worst,” she said.</p>
                  <p>“Do you want your par eat out of house an' home?”</p>
                  <p>“Well, on my word! to count company's eatin'!”</p>
                  <p>“I should say so! A supper spread out fit fur a preacher!
Two dishes of fresh, an' apple butter, an' a stack o' pies, an'
dear knows what! I'll stand nothin' of the sort in my house.”</p>
                  <pb n="46"/>
                  <p>“Easy, my boy, easy,” says his par. “This property belongs
to old Jed Burridge yet a while.”</p>
                  <p>“Well, it's a-goin' to be mine by the law of primogenicy,”
says Eben, very grand; “an' all I have to say is, that if Jane
wants ter marry, she's got to pick one outen the crowd, an'
turn the rest off. My foot is down.”</p>
                  <p>“La, Eben!” says I, “it's so hard for Janey to choose.
She's the most popperler girl on the perarer.”</p>
                  <p>“Popperler!” yells Eben. “An' what business has a decent
woman to be popperler? Let her be popperler with her husband,
an' that's enough. I've saw your popperler women—I
haven't travelled with my eyes shut—an' I tell you they've got
no more character than stale eggs.”</p>
                  <p>The words wuzn't well spoke afore up jumped Janey an'
give him such a slap as might have been heard to the wheat
field. Then she tore off like a cyclone to her room.</p>
                  <p>Eben wuz in a blazin' rage; but his par he on'y laughed
a little, and “Ain't she got sperrit?” says he. “Ain't she,
though?” Then a sort of shade came over his face, and “She
do put me so much in mind of her mother,” he said, a-knockin'
the ashes out of his pipe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subchapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <head>III.—JANEY MAKES A CHOICE.</head>
                  <p>It didn't surprise any of us, a few weeks later, when Janey
told her par that she meant to marry Charley Winn; fur he
had been comin' alone quite frequent, an' he an' Janey had set
up in the parlor, not findin' much ter say.</p>
                  <p>“I ain't no objection to Charley,” says Jed, “an' I shall give
Janey fifty geese an' ten sheep an' a cow.”</p>
                  <pb n="47"/>
                  <p>“Charley's goin' ter build, par,” says Janey—“three rooms
an' a ell. It will be real nice beginnin' all fresh.”</p>
                  <p>Everybody seemed to think Janey had done well, and most
had a warm word fur her. The aunts would try to fault
Charley occasional, but they couldn't git the best o' Janey;
an' neither could Eben when he fussed with her about wantin'
to take so much o' the furniture out o' the house.</p>
                  <p>“It wuz my mother's furniture,” says she, “an' I mean ter
have it.”</p>
                  <p>“Well, wozn't she my mother too?” snarls Eben. “D'ye
think you have got a patent on her? Ther' won't be a thing
left in the house for me and my girl to set up with.”</p>
                  <p>Neither one of 'em appeared to consider the old father as
they wrangled over his things. I made up my mind, if Janey
did make a clean sweep, I should unpack some of my own
goods that I had stored in Peppertown, an' bring 'em over;
for though a boarder I wuz human, an' my feelin's went out to
Jed settin' there so peaceful, with his pipe an' his white head.</p>
                  <p>Charley Winn lost no time in gettin' his house put up, an'
a good job it wuz—neat an' nice as a palace, with a bay-window
an' plenty o' closets. Every evenin' Janey would go over
to see how it wuz gittin' along, an' Charley would walk home
with her, both of 'em lookin' as proud an' as pleased as if the
whole o' the comin' wheat crop belonged to 'em. The weddin'
wuz to be just after harvestin', that bein' a time when everybody
took a restin' spell. Janey's weddin' frock wuz bein'
made in Peppertown, an' Jed had made her a present of a
whole bolt of domestic that we wuz makin' up as fast as
possible. He wuz a mighty liberal man, Jed wuz, an' Janey's
<pb n="48"/>
aunts said that her outfittin' would be the ruin of every girl
on the perarer.</p>
                  <p>The wheat crop this year wuz a very stavin' one, and the
farmers had considerable difficulty in gittin' help.</p>
                  <p>“I reckon you'll have to ride the reaper to-morrow, Janey,”
says Eben, one night at supper, “if you can spare the time.”</p>
                  <p>“All right,” she said. “My work can wait, an' the wheat
can't. It's already overripe.”</p>
                  <p>“I don't see how you can be so venturesome as to ride on
the reaper,” says I.</p>
                  <p>“Janey is an old hand at helpin' in the crop,” says her pa.
“When she wuzn't more'n half the size o' Elick here she rid
the leadin' horse when we wuz a-thrashin' out the wheat.”</p>
                  <p>“Why, uncle, didn't you have a thrashin'-machine?” cries
Elick, stickin' his knife between his teeth, an' proddin' a piece
o' pork with his fork, simultaneous with stretchin' out his
other hand for a biscuit.</p>
                  <p>“Machines wuz locked up then in some man's brain,” says
Jed; “an' sometimes I wish they had never got out, fur it
gives a poor man's pocket-book the swinney to buy one. The
way we thrashed wuz to set the bundles in a ring about forty
feet in diameter, I cal'late, an' ride around it, the horses' feet
a-trampin' out the grain. An' when it wuz pretty well out
we would sweep it up in a cloth.”</p>
                  <p>“I should think it would 'a been awful unclean.”</p>
                  <p>“Well, our biscuits wuz gritty sometimes,” says Jed, with a
smile.</p>
                  <p>Long before sun-up the next mornin' Ebenezer gave us a
call, for at harvest-time the sooner you could git things to
<pb n="49"/>
goin' the better. In fact, durin' a very dry season, when the
sun shone down hot an' fierce, an' the wheat wuz as brittle as
broom straws, an' it wuz a sheer impossibility to bundle it without
breakin', then the men would often have to work all night,
so's ter take advantage o' the dew. 'Twan't no great hardship,
however, with the big yellow harvest-moon a-shinin' in the
sky, an' the air so cool an' pleasant. But it wuz powerful apt
to bring on the chills.</p>
                  <p>When Janey jumped out o' bed at Eben's call she said she
had a pain in her left eye, and wuz afeared she wuz goin' ter
have a sty, to which she wuz subject occasional. We had a
piece o' broken lookin'-glass in our room, an' takin' it in her
hand, Janey went to the winder to examine her eye where she
could ketch the first beam o' light. While she stood there, as
evil doom would have it, Elick Farley passed by on his way
ter feed the turkeys.</p>
                  <p>“Hi, Janey!” he calls, “you'd better come down-stairs an'
git the breakfast, instid of a-primpin' an' a-fixin' an' a-lookin' in
the glass as if you wuz goin' to a party.”</p>
                  <p>“You go about your business an' let me alone,” says Janey
firin' up a little.</p>
                  <p>Then what does he do but commence a-dancin' up an'
down, an' a-singin':</p>
                  <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                     <l part="N">“Janey's mad, an' I am glad,</l>
                     <l part="N">An' I know what'll please her —</l>
                     <l part="N">A bottle o' wine ter make her shine,</l>
                     <l part="N">An' Charley Winn to squeeze her.”</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>At this Janey turned real ugly. “See if I can't make
you change your tune,” she cries. And without a moment's
<pb n="50"/>
thought, I am sure, she flung the piece o' lookin'-glass square
at Elick's head. It struck him on the forehead, an' he began
to bleed and howl simultaneous. We ran down, considerably
skeered; but the cut didn't turn out to be much, an' wuz soon
salved and bound up. Elick's feelin's, however, wuz all agog.
Many a black look he cast at Janey.</p>
                  <p>“I'll be even with you yet,” says he, “an' you mark my
words.” But Janey on'y humped up her shoulders at him, an'
went along to the wheat field.</p>
                  <p>Reapin' is hungry work, an' our harvesters could put away
four meals a day quite comfortable. So along about eleven
o'clock I fixed up a lunch of cold biscuit an' pork an' hoecake,
an' a jug of cool buttermilk, an' went ter the field with it.
Fur though I wuz a boarder, I wuz never above doin' any
little chores to help the work along.</p>
                  <p>I got to the field just as the reaper wuz comin' up. Janey
wuz sittin' up high under the awnin' drivin', an' Charley Winn
stood beside her, a-tyin' up the bundles very swift. Eben wuz
stackin' up in a distant part o' the field, an' his par had stopped
to rest under a big walnut-tree which wuz a sort o' landmark
to people in those parts, it bein' the tallest tree on the
Nine-mile, an' wuz ginerally known as “Burridge's walnut.”
Here they gethered ter eat their lunch.</p>
                  <p>“Phew! but it's a hot day!” says Jed, takin' a long pull at
the buttermilk, an' passin' the jug to Charley Winn.</p>
                  <p>“The wheat field is a mighty purty sight,” says I; for it
wuz, with the yellow sun shinin' on the yellow waves o' grain,
an' the path that the reaper had made lookin' as smooth an'
clean an' hare as the dry line through the Red Sea.</p>
                  <pb n="51"/>
                  <p>“I don't know about purty,” says Jed, “but it's as fine a
stand of wheat as I ever had. Not a spear of cheat in it. An'
this one good year the Hessian fly an' the chinch-bug has let
us alone.”</p>
                  <p>“Ther' ain't a farmer in the country as can compare with
you, Mr. Burridge,” says Charley Winn. “I only hope to
have half as good-luck when I am tryin' it single-hand.”</p>
                  <p>“Sho! you'll have Janey ter help you. She's as good a
farmer as I am. I allays said Janey ought ter 'a bin the boy
an' Eben the girl in our family. Eben has a picayunish,
meachin' sort o' way with him as is nateral to women. His
mother hed it,” went on the old man, quite thoughtful, an'
chewin' a wheat straw. “But Janey is another sort, active an'
strong, an' muscles like steel.”</p>
                  <p>“Oh, I love ter work out-doors,” cries Janey. “I can do
a'most anything that a man can. I don't know what I should
do if I had to stay shut up in the house.”</p>
                  <p>“I believe you could throw me in a rassel,” says Charley.
“What a muscle, ter be sure!” an' he give her arm a squeeze.</p>
                  <p>Janey tossed her head, an' colored up, an' laughed—a big,
saucy laugh. Gracious! if any one had told me that I would
never again hear that laugh, never see her standin', strong an'
vigorous as a young oak, an' red as a poppy bloom, in the
golden grain, with her sweetheart by her side! Well, well!
a body may jest as well give up soon as late a-tryin' ter
understand the ways of Providence!</p>
                  <p>They set off again, Janey still a-drivin', an' I started fur
home. As I reached the bars I turned an' looked back. The
reaper wuz cuttin' against the wind. Janey's bonnet wuz off,
<pb n="52"/>
an' her black hair wuz blowin' over her face. Suddenly I saw
a little sunbeam dancin' about the head of old Pete, the right-hand
horse. He shook his head, annoyed like; but the little
patch of light went bobbin', bobbin', here an' there, glancin' in
eyes, ears, an' nose, quick as a hummin'-bird, an' finally flashin'
full in the eyes of Nelly Grey, the little mare, that wuz
a-drivin' with old Pete. The skittish thing give an awful
jump. The next minnit both frightened animals had started
off on a run, <hi rend="italics">an' Janey, poor Janey, wuz thrown forward in
front of the sickle bar!</hi> Great Heaven! what a time it seemed
before the horses could be overtook an' halted! How I got to
the spot I never could tell. When I did, ther' wuz Ebenezer
holdin' to the pantin', tremblin' horses, that wuz rollin' the'r
eyes as if in a mortal fright. An' Charley an' Jed wuz tryin'
to lift somethin' from the knives, red with blood, an' the pointed
guards clogged with mangled flesh. They got her
out, and laid her down on the ground. Charley went over to
the house, an' came back with a door that he had wrenched
off, an' we managed to git her on this, knowin' only by a faint
moanin' that the breath wuz still in the poor torn body.</p>
                  <p>Eben an' Jed crept across the field with the'r burden, while
Charley jumped on Nelly Grey an' rid like mad fur the
doctor.</p>
                  <p>I walked a little behind, feelin' stunned an' dazed; an' as
I passed under “Burridge's walnut” I heard a voice callin',
“Aunt Fonie!”</p>
                  <p>I looked up. A pair of wild eyes peered at me through
the branches.</p>
                  <p>“Aunt Fonie,” called Elick, “is she dead?”</p>
                  <pb n="53"/>
                  <p>“Come down outen that tree, Elick Farley!” says I, very
solemn.</p>
                  <p>Down he slid, the most miserable, God-forsakened little
wretch. He had cried white streaks down his cheeks, an' he
wuz a-shakin' all over. <hi rend="italics">In his hand be held a bit of broken looking-glass.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>“What does this mean?” says I.</p>
                  <p>“I did it,” he says, very pitiful. “I wanted to tease her
because I wuz mad, an' wanted to pay her off a little. I knew
she never could guess that I wuz hid up in the tree catchin'
the sunbeam with the same piece of glass that she struck me
with. But I didn't mean to hurt her. I never dreamed o' her
bein' thrown on them—them knives.”</p>
                  <p>“Elick Farley,” says I, takin' him hard by the hand, “come
here;” and I followed the men that wuz a-carryin' poor Janey.</p>
                  <p>“Look!” says I—“look!” and along the path wuz a line o'
drippin' blood.</p>
                  <p>“Pray,” says I, burstin' inter tears—“pray to the good God
that that stain shell not rest forever on your soul.”</p>
                  <p>The child give a wild cry that seemed as if it had fairly
burst from his heart; then tearin' away from me, he ran like a
dart across the perarer, in the direction of Peppertown.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subchapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <head>IV.—JANEY'S COMFORTERS.</head>
                  <p>Fur many a draggin' week poor Janey lay betwixt life an'
death. The child wuz cut an' bruised over every part of her
body. Two of her ribs wuz broke, an' one limb had been
impaled on the guards of the sickle, an' wuz nearly sawed in
two. That she should so much as survive the shock an'
<pb n="54"/>
horrid wounds seemed a miracle; but the doctor brought her
round at last, though he told her quite frank she would never
be able ter walk again.</p>
                  <p>“Never ter walk again!” said Janey, flingin' her arms over
her head, with a long, long groan—“never ter walk again!
Oh, Lord! oh, Lord!”</p>
                  <p>The aunts wuz all a-settin' round very solemn, an' they
sithed an' rocked themselves back an' forth like trees in a
wind.</p>
                  <p>“It's the Lords will,” says sister Charity Hackleton; “an'
mebbe it's sent es a punishment fur your sins.”</p>
                  <p>“That's all nonsense,” says Janey, very dogged like. “What
sins have I committed, I want ter know? I've worked hard,
an' done my best; an' beyond a sharp word now an' then, I've
nothin' on my conscience. I don't deserve this.”</p>
                  <p>“We all deserve damnation,” says Charity, severe as a
Hard-shell preacher. “Let this turn your soul to God, an' it
will prove a blessin' in disguise.”</p>
                  <p>“Sho!” says Mis' Amos Burridge; “ther' ain't no use tryin'
ter bolster the poor child up with such talk es that. It's a
terrible misfortin—terrible. It's jest es if she had jumped from
twenty years to eighty—from bein' a strong young girl to a
helpless old woman, needin' es much care es a baby, an'
sufferin' perhaps fur a drink o' water even; because a family
do git so wore out waitin' on a invaleed.”</p>
                  <p>“In <hi rend="italics">my</hi> family,” says I, “ther' would a' bin no thought o'
trouble. We wuzn't the kind ter count our steps fur the
afflicted. Consequently, when my husband's mother wuz down
with the rheumatism fur years an' years, her room wuz about
<pb n="55"/>
the cheerfulest in the house—fur everybody wuz a-runnin' to
her with some lovin' service—an' the Visitation o' the Sick
read quite frequent to enliven us.”</p>
                  <p>“Never mind all that,” says Little Mary Jane, with a wave
of her little fat hand. “Let us be practical. The thing is ter
find somethin' fur Janey ter do. I cal'late she don't mean ter
lie round all her days a burden on folks, so I've bin a-studyin'
an' a-studyin' what she could do. Now, I take it she couldn't
do nothin' better than ter buy a knittin'-machine. She could
pervide mittens an' socks fur the whole country, fur everybody
would buy of her on account of her affliction; an' thusly she
could have ockerapation an' a stiddy income.”</p>
                  <p>“Knittin'-machines cost a sight o' money,” says Amos
Burridge's wife, very dry. “Who's goin' ter pay fur it?”</p>
                  <p>“She might sell her geese fur a start.”</p>
                  <p>“An' her relations might all throw in an' help,” says I.</p>
                  <p>At this there wuz a sort o' silence. Never a Burridge by
name or by birth wuz ever willin' to put his hand in his
pocket.</p>
                  <p>“Well,” says Nancy Jones as wuz, “some has to <hi rend="italics">be</hi> burdens,
an' some to <hi rend="italics">bear</hi> 'em. I'm one o' the last, an' I don't know but
what I'm the worse off o' the two of us. Twins the first year
o' my marriage, an' a baby ten months after! I am fairly dragged
out with nursin', an' I suppose I shell have a baby in
my arms es long es I am able to move.”</p>
                  <p>“That's somethin' Janey will never be troubled with,
anyhow,” says Mis' Amos, with a laugh, as if she wuz sayin'
somethin' of a soothin' an' agreeable natur'. So far from that bein'
the case, however, it seemed as if that speech wuz the last
<pb n="56"/>
straw. I had noticed fur some time a sort of convulsive movement
under the bedclothes, as if Janey's breast wuz a-heavin'
with silent sobs, an' now ther' came a storm o' tears an' cries,
as if natur' had bore an' bore until a flood came fur relief.</p>
                  <p>I jest riz up then, an' says I: “Clear out from here, you
onfeelin' set o' human critters! If I didn't have no more
decency than you've got, I'd go an' hold my head under Big
Muddy Creek.”</p>
                  <p>They wuz skeered at the state they see they'd throwed
Janey inter, so they filed out pretty meek. I took the poor
child, an' worked with her, an' made her drink some hot tea
an' take a good strengthenin' dose of quineen; an' after a
while she grew quiet, an' the big moans stopped comin' from
the poor breast where a child's head would never rest, an' she
fell inter a sweet sleep.</p>
                  <p>Afore I thought her nap wuz over Eben's head wuz poked
in the door. Says he, “Charley Winn's here, an' would like
ter see Janey.”</p>
                  <p>“Well, he can't,” says I, very short, “fur she is asleep.”</p>
                  <p>“I am awake now, Aunt Fonie,” says a voice from the bed.
“An' Charley may come in as soon as you've tidied me up a
bit.”</p>
                  <p>Pretty soon we heard his step on the stair. Janey wuz
tremblin', but she shook hands with him quite calm when he
came in, an' she says, “You go out, Aunt Fonie; I want to
talk to Charley by himself.”</p>
                  <p>But, dear sakes! I had no notion of effacin' myself, so I
stepped outside o' the door, leavin' it ajee, an' a-settin' myself
where I could look an' listen quite comfortable.</p>
                  <pb n="57"/>
                  <p>Janey day there, her big eyes fixed on Charley's face. He
stood up, twirlin' his hat, first on one foot, then on the other,
an' lookin' powerful meachin', fur a fact.</p>
                  <p>“Charley,” begun poor Janey, “it's hard to come to this.”</p>
                  <p>“I'd like to kill that little devil!” cried Charley.</p>
                  <p>“Oh no, don't say that. Poor child! you know he ran
away to his pa: you remember Lex Farley? Lex wrote a
letter ter my father, expressin' a great deal o' concern. He
said it seemed as if Elick's heart wuz fairly broke. Maybe
he'll make a good man yet.”</p>
                  <p>“If he gits ter be the President, I don't see how that's ter
make up ter me fur losin' you.”</p>
                  <p>“A-losin' me?” repeats Janey, very slow. “But I ain't dead,
Charley, nor like ter die, the doctor says.”</p>
                  <p>That hat went round in Charley's fingers as if it wuz
possessed. “But you know, Janey,” he stammered—“you know,
a man hes to marry a woman ter do her shear o' the work.
And you can't do anything.”</p>
                  <p>“True,” says Janey, speakin' very loud an' harsh, “I'm laid
on the shelf. An' of course a man marries a woman ter have
his meals cooked reg'lar, an' the harvestin' 'tended to, an' the
lard tried out, an' the apple-butter made, an' the geese plucked,
an' the house cleaned, an' the washin' done on Monday, an' the
mendin' Saturday, an' the odd jobs on Sunday.”</p>
                  <p>“Exactly,” says he, noddin' his head, an' never mistrustin'
—the gawk!—that any woman with feelin's above a dumb
beast's would 'a liked fur her beau to add a little tenderness
to that bill of pertikelers.</p>
                  <p>Janey swallered a few times, an' then said, quite nateral,
<pb n="58"/>
“Of course, Charley, you will be marryin' some one else before
a great while?”</p>
                  <p>“Oh yes,” he says. “My house is built, you know, an' I've
already got my seed in that fifty-acre lot. I shell have to git
me a wife by next harvest-time, you know.”</p>
                  <p>“An' have you made up your mind,” says Janey, very
polite, “where you'll go a-courtin' next time?”</p>
                  <p>Don't talk to me about a man havin' any gumption!
Charley Winn seemed quite pleased that Janey wuz takin'
intrust in his marryin', an' says he, in a sociable kind o' way,
as if he had been talkin' to his grandmother, “I have been
thinkin' of Mahaly Thing.”</p>
                  <p>“She's powerful untidy,” says Janey. “They say she washes
her hands an' makes up her bread in the same bowl. An' I
know her kitchen is the sloppiest on the Nine-mile.”</p>
                  <p>“What do you think of Hatty Holman?”</p>
                  <p>“Oh, she would do,” says Janey, speakin' quite dry, “if you
could keep two hired girls—one to do the work, an' one to
wait on her. She's as lazy as a snail.”</p>
                  <p>“Well, ther's Evy Wait; she appears to be of a brisk,
active natur'.”</p>
                  <p>“So much so that they say she can drink more hard cider
than any girl on the perarer.”</p>
                  <p>Charley knit up his brows, ant looked as if the subject wuz
gittin' very knotty.</p>
                  <p>“Suppose I wuz to ask one o' the Whiteside girls?” he
suggested; “they are purty, and smart too.”</p>
                  <p>“Oh yes; and they'll give a kiss for the askin' to you or
the next one that comes along.”</p>
                  <pb n="59"/>
                  <p>“I don't like that,” says Charley, very stern. “None o'
your fast flirts fur me! That's what I use' ter like about you,
Janey. Every fellow hed to keep his distance. Now, the
Biscoe girls are of a very proper kind. Wonder how it would
do fur me to apply there?”</p>
                  <p>“Jenny is engaged to Roland Selph; an' as fur Leila, she
wouldn't wipe her shoes on a Western wheat farmer.</p>
                  <p>“An' es to Polly Ann Carpenter?”</p>
                  <p>“She is a waster. She can throw out with a teaspoon
faster than a man can bring in with a shovel.”</p>
                  <p>“I declare, Janey,” said Charley, seemin' quite injured, “it
looks es if you don't want me ter git a wife. You try to set
me agen every girl on the perarer. 'Pears like you can't bear
to give me up to anybody else.”</p>
                  <p>“You are quite mistaken, Mr. Winn,” cries poor Janey, her
voice risin' higher with every word—“<hi rend="italics">quite</hi> mistaken, I do
assure you. I've no objection to your havin' forty wives.
You might go to Utah an' join the Mormons; then you could
try all kinds, you know—ha! ha! ha! ha!”</p>
                  <p>When I heard this wild laughin' I knew it wuz time to
walk in with the camphor bottle in hand.</p>
                  <p>“I think you hed better make yourself scarce,” says I to
Charley Winn, with a very viperish look. Pickin' up his hat,
he sneaked out o' the room, an' out o' Janey Burridge's life.
An' I may jest as well mention that it wuzn't six months afore
he wuz married to Mahaly Thing.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="60"/>
               <div type="subchapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <head>V.—UNEXPECTED THINGS HAPPEN TO JANEY.</head>
                  <p>Janey didn't seem ter git any better as the days passed on.
She took no intrust in anything in the heavens above nor in
the earth beneath. The doctor said he couldn't do no more
fur her, en' except to make her pretty deef, all the quineen she
took didn't have a mite of effect. Seein' her so dwindlin' an'
pinin', I set my wits ter work. The child ought ter have
somethin' to engage her time an' her mind. An' Little Mary
Jane's idea as to the knittin'-machine wuz fur from bein' a
injudishus one. How to git the purchase-money wuz the
trouble. The thought come to me that Lex Farley might
jest as well as not help in the matter; so I wrote him a letter
on my own hook, as the sayin' is, an' presented the case. By
the next Saturday came an answer sayin' he would be proud
ter git the machine out an' out for Janey, but fur me to say
nothin' about it till it had arrove. In the same mail wuz a
letter ter me from poor little Elick, a-sayin' thusly:</p>
                  <p>“DEAR AUNT FONIE,—Pa has swore off till he gits Janey's
machine. I am a-helpin' him, an' learnin' the photographin'
business very fast. Give my respex ter Janey. I am very
sorry that she got hurt.	Yours truely,	E. FARLEY.”</p>
                  <p>“Seems ter me you're gittin' a lot o' letters,” says Eben
when he handed 'em to me; but I only smiled mysterious, an'
said not a word.</p>
                  <p>I never had seen Janey so low as she wuz the day before
Thanksgivin'. I wuz bustlin' round preparin' fur nex' day's
<pb n="61"/>
dinner, but she barely raised her eyelids from her cheeks.
“What hev I ter be thankful fur?” she would say when I
would try to hearten her up somewhat.</p>
                  <p>Before night, however, Janey took back them words o' hens;
fur old Mr. Thing, passin' by on his way from town, stopped
with a box outen the express office directed to “Miss Janey
Burridge.”</p>
                  <p>“Fur me!” cries Janey, very incredulous, but her eyes
sparklin' as I hadn't seen 'em since her accident.</p>
                  <p>We all assembled while Jed knocked off the wooden slats
an' untied the strings; fur, be the hurry what it may, the man
wuz that careful that cut a string he would not.</p>
                  <p>An' lo an' behold! there wuz the prettiest knittin'-machine
ever made, with a card:</p>
                  <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                     <l part="N">
                        <hi rend="italics">“Compliments and Resects</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l part="N">
                        <hi rend="italics">of</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l part="N">
                        <hi rend="italics">Alexander Farley</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l part="N">
                        <hi rend="italics">to</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l part="N">
                        <hi rend="italics">Miss Janey Burrirdge.”</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Janey wuz pleased enough ter cry, an' I don't believe she
slept a wink that night fur longin' ter try her hand on the
little beauty. The aunts didn't lose no time in comin' over to
the house as soon as they got wind o' Janey's present. An'
sister Charity, who understood how to work machines, offered
to stay a week, if need be, to put Janey in the way o' runnin'
hers; which showed she wuzn't a bad kind o' woman, in spite
o' bein' so aggressive in the way o' religion.</p>
                  <p>From that time Janey's health an' spirits improved
considerable. She turned out mittens an' socks very fast; an' the
<pb n="62"/>
very first pair wuz sent as a present to Lex Farley. As fur
me, seein' how well my idea had worked, an' though not as a
rule approvin' of ridin' a willin' horse to death, still I thought,
while his hand was in, Lex might as well as not lay up more
treasures in heaven. So I up an' wrote another letter, sayin'
that if Janey had a wheel-cheer, it would be the greatest thing
in the world fur her to ease her pain, an' enable her ter git
about. No answer came to this; but I waited patient, thinkin'
somethin' might come of it. An' ther' did.</p>
                  <p>Christmas had come, an' we all had bundled up in the big
wagon, an' gone over ter Amos Burridge's to dinner—except, of
course, poor Janey, who wuz left in the charge of one o' the
neighbors' children, little Sally Wysnicker, with a nice dinner
ready cooked for 'em, and set out in the dresser.</p>
                  <p>The day wore along as them family spreads usually do,
an' about four o'clock we started fur home. Now, it's a very
curious thing, but as we reached the corner o' Mr. Burridge's
wheat field, I had the most flutterin' sensation erbout the
heart, es if somethin' wuz a-goin' ter happen. It wouldn't hev
surprised me a mite ter hev found the house burnt up, fur I
felt the same way twice previous in my life—once precedin' to
our Jersey cow bein' gored, an' agin before my partner wuz
taken with the dropsy that carrid him off. Howsomever, ther'
wuz the house safe an' sound; an' es we neared the gate the
wind bore the sound of laughin' to our ears. Very cur'ous, we
hurried on; but afore we got to the door out broke a boy,
all dressed up, clean as clean, an' a-shoutin' at the top of his
voice, “Howdy, Aunt Fonie! howdy, Uncle Jed! howdy, Eben!
Christmas-gift! Christmas-gift!”</p>
                  <pb n="63"/>
                  <p>Of course it wuz Elick. An' of course the slim, long-bearded
man we see through the winder a-talkin' so kindly ter
Janey wuz Elick's par, Lex Farley. But the wonder of all wuz
ter see Janey. There she wuz, bright an' smilin', <hi rend="italics">an' a-sittin' up</hi>
in the finest kind o' wheeled cheer, es proud es if she wuz on
a throne.</p>
                  <p>Well, we wuz all a-talkin' together fur quite a spell; an' Jed
he welcomed Lex real hearty, an' told him he must make himself
at home fur es long es he would like ter stay. An' you
never see a boy so changed as Elick Farley. From bein' a
wild, cantankerous limb that nobody hardly could abide, he
wuz a quiet, nice little chap, modest an' obligin' in his ways,
an' a-hangin' on every word that Janey spoke.</p>
                  <p>“It wuz all I could do ter git him ter come,” said his par,
when he got a chance fur a word with me. “You see he
thought Janey would be so set agen him that she would want
ter hev him arrested or somethin'; but I told him ter be a
man, an' face the music. When we got inside the hall door
here, an' see Janey lookin' so white an' quiet, as if she might
be dead, the child hung back as if he darsn't go a step farther.
But I pushed him inside the room, an' he begun ter cry.
Janey turned her head quick, an' seen him a-standin' ther'.
Somehow she didn't seem a bit surprised. ‘Elick,’ says she,
very gentle—‘Elick, come here;’ an' when he wuz in reach she
put her arms around him an' kissed him.”</p>
                  <p>“No!” I cried, “Janey Burridge didn't ever do that!”</p>
                  <p>“Yes,” he said, strokin' his beard, kind o' meditative, “she
kissed him. An' I suppose it's the first time anybody hes
kissed him sence his mother died. An' that she should do it
<pb n="64"/>
who lay there a wreck through his mischief! I tell you, Aunt
Fonie, she is a angel.”</p>
                  <p>It hed never occurred ter me ter look on Janey Burridge
in that light, as you ain't apt to think of a angel bein' strong
as a heifer, an' built for labor rusher than a-flyin' roun' an'
singin'; but I wuz glad ter hev Lex Farley appreshiate her,
even though he stretched the blanket a little in doin' so.</p>
                  <p>After supper Mr. Burridge examined the cheer most admirin'.
It wuz made of cherry-wood, an' stuffed with hair, an'
set on springs, an' covered with rep, an' it wuz es fine es a
coffin.</p>
                  <p>“It must 'a cost a sight o' money,” says Jed.</p>
                  <p>“A matter o' fifty dollars,” says Lex Farley; “but you
know, Uncle Jed, I don't ever find it difficult to make money.”</p>
                  <p>“True, Lex,” says the old man, very kind; “you are smart
enough ter do anything when you give the enemy the go-by.”</p>
                  <p>I wuz a little skeert at this plain-speakin', fearin' Lex might
take offence; but he spoke out quite manful: “Uncle Jed, I
haven't teched a drop of anything stronger than tea sence my
boy come in an' told me what hed happened to Janey. I made
up my mind that instant that ef the poor girl wuz gone, I
would pay all the funeral expenses, an' put her up a handsome
monument; an' ef she lived, that I would come to see her, an'
try to make such poor reparation es I could.”</p>
                  <p>“I'm sure,” says Jed, “that Janey will set more value on
your lettin' the drink alone than on either the knittin'-machine
or the wheel-cheer. You see, it runs in our blood ter be
gret on temperance. Forty year ago, when the Burridges first
settled here, one of our first performances wuz ter git up a
<pb n="65"/>
temperance meetin' at Peppertown. The Yahoos came in an' tried
ter put a stop to it.”</p>
                  <p>“The Yahoos? An' who were they?”</p>
                  <p>“That wuz the name we give the early settlers. They wuz
mostly riffraff o' the hardest sort, who hed drifted here from
Tennessee an' Kentucky. They wuz dead-set agin temperance.
They came a-whoopin' an' a-ridin' an' a-yellin' inter
Peppertown on the occasion of our meetin'; an' they hed
caught a wild wolf, which they turned loose among the folks,
an' nearly skeered the women ter death.</p>
                  <p>“In them days even the preachers hated ter give up the'r
whiskey. Well, it wuz a heap purer article than you git now;
you could buy it by the barrel at a bit a gallon. Everybody
drunk it. It wuz handed around ter women an' children. At
the races once old Mrs. Wysnicker had a barrel that she peddled
out by the drink, an' they said she made enough ter buy a
handsome family Bible.”</p>
                  <p>“I wish they would give us a purer article of whiskey in
these days,” said Mr. Farley.</p>
                  <p>“Lex—Lex Farley, don't say that!” cried Janey, leanin'
for'ard, en' speakin' with such entreaty as I never heerd from
mortal lips.</p>
                  <p>“You have gone without it,” she says, “from sorrow an'
pity fur me, an' you can keep on in the good course fur love 
—fur love of God. Listen to me, Lex. You wuz pleased with
my thanks when I told you how the knittin'-machine had
comforted me an' give me a new start in life; an' you smiled an'
almost cried too when I told you ter-day of the rest your
beautiful cheer give to my poor tired body. Think, think what it
<pb n="66"/>
will be when you can bring the gifts of a good an' manly life
ter the Lord, an' receive his thanks, an' know his joy over the
one sinner that repents! Oh, Lex, don't give me more than
you give to your Maker!”</p>
                  <p>It came like a thunder-clap. I never would 'a believed
Janey Burridge could have spoke so beautiful. We wuz all
moved beyond speech. But, after a-little, Lex Farley says:
“I won't forgit your words, Janey. God bless you fur 'em!”</p>
                  <p>Jed passed his hand across his eyes. “My friends,” said
he, “it is Christmas night. Let us unite in prayer.”</p>
                  <p>An' kneelin' round Janey's cheer, we prayed in silence, an'
somethin' seemed ter whisper that a good new year wuz
a-dawnin' fur us all.</p>
                  <p>Well, well, Lex Farley wuz in no hurry to git away. An'
one day he asked our Janey to marry him.</p>
                  <p>“He says, Aunt Fonie,” said Janey to me, “that I can <hi rend="italics">help</hi>
him—I, a poor lame creature, that never expected to be of use
or pleasure ter any livin' soul.”</p>
                  <p>“He loves you, dear,” I said, pattin' her dark head.</p>
                  <p>“I can hardly believe it,” she said, in a falterin' way. “He
says so many strange things, Aunt Fonie: that to be with me
helps an' heartens him; that he wants nothin' better than to
work for me all his days; that he wants me only to give him
my heart—not my labor an' service, but my heart.”</p>
                  <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                     <l part="N">“ ‘Ther's nothin' half so sweet in life</l>
                     <l part="N">As love's young dream,’ ”</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>says I, quotin' out of a poetry book.</p>
                  <pb n="67"/>
                  <p>“Don't you think,” says she, very timid, “that folks will say
he wanted me from pity, an' that I took him from pride?”</p>
                  <p>“Fools may,” says I, very decisive.</p>
                  <p>The end of it all wuz that she put him off six months,
durin' which time he wuz as sober as a horse, an' then she
married him. They went ter St. Louis ter live, an' he got a
run o' fashionable customers, an' soon we heard of 'em as
surprisin' prosperous. A couple o' years later her par an' me
went ter visit 'em; fur I hed got rusher tired o' bein' a
boarder an' hed married Jed Burridge. That wuz a visit!
They hed three rooms leadin' out o' the photograph gallery - 
an apartment, they called it—an' a servant to do the work, an'
a little maid to 'tend the door. Lex Farley was the proudest,
happiest man in the State. For Janey—bless her!—with a
long trailed gown on, her face pale and pretty, her hair curlin'
on her forehead, <hi rend="italics">walked</hi> to meet us, with a snow-white baby
cuddlin' in her arms.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <pb n="68"/>
            <div type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
               <head>HIERONYMUS POP AND THE BABY.</head>
               <p>“NOW, 'Onymus Pop,” said the mother of that gentle boy,
“you jes take keer o' dis chile while I'm gone ter de
hangin'. An' don't you leave dis house on no account, not if
de skies fall an' de earth opens ter swaller yer”</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>HIERONYMUS'S CHARGE.</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Hieronymus grunted gloomily. He thought it a burning
shame that he should not go to the hanging; but never had
his mother been willing that he should have the least pleasure
<pb n="69"/>
in life. It was either to tend the baby, or mix the cow's food,
or to card wool, or cut wood, or to pick a chicken, or wash up
the floor, or to draw water, or to sprinkle down the clothes - 
always something. When everything else failed, she had a
way, that seemed to her son simply demoniac, of setting him
at the alphabet. To be sure, she did not know the letters
herself, but her teaching was none the less vigorous.</p>
               <p>“What's dat, 'Onymus?” she would say, pointing at random
with her snuff-brush to a letter.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>“WHAT'S DAT?”</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>“Q”—with a sniff.</p>
               <p>“Is you <hi rend="italics">sho'?</hi>”—in a hollow voice.</p>
               <p>Woe be unto young Pop if he faltered, and said it <hi rend="italics">might</hi>
be a Z. Mother Pop kept a rod ready, and used it as if she
were born for nothing else. Naturally, he soon learned to stick
<pb n="70"/>
brazenly to his first guess. But, unfortunately, he could not
remember from one day to another what he had said; and his
mother learned, after a time, to distinguish the forms of the
letters, and to know that a curly letter called S on Tuesday
could not possibly. be a square-shaped E on Thursday. Her
faith once shattered, 'Onymus had to suffer in the usual way.</p>
               <p>The lad had been taught at spasmodic intervals by his
sister Savannah—commonly called Sissy—who went to school,
put on airs, and was always clean. Therefore Hieronymus
hated her. Mother Pop herself was a little in awe of her
accomplished daughter, and would ask her no questions, even
when most in doubt as to which was which of the letters G
and C.</p>
               <p>“A pretty thing!” she would mutter to herself, “if I must
be a-learnin' things from my own chile, dat wuz de mos'
colicky baby I ever had, an' cos' me unheard-of miseries in de
time of her teethin'.”</p>
               <p>It seemed to Hieronymus that the climax of his impositions
had come when he was forced to stay at home and mind
the baby, while his mother and the rest of them trotted off,
gay as larks, to see a man hanged.</p>
               <p>It was a hot afternoon, and the unwilling nurse suffered.
The baby wouldn't go to sleep. He put it on the bed - -a
feather- bed—and why it didn't drop off to sleep, as a proper
baby should, was more than the tired soul of Hieronymus
could tell. He did everything to soothe Tiddlekins. (The
infant had not been named as yet, and by way of affection
they addressed it as Tiddlekins.) He even went so far as to
wave the flies away from it with a mulberry branch for the
<pb n="71"/>
space of five or ten minutes. But as it still fretted and tossed
he let it severely alone, and the flies settled on the little black
thing as if it had been a licorice stick.</p>
               <p>After a while Tiddlekins grew aggressive, and began to
yell. Hieronymus, who had almost found consolation in studying
a gory picture pasted on the wall, cut from the weekly
paper of a wicked city, was deprived even of this solace. He
picked up “de miserbul little screech-owl,” as he called it in
his wrath. He trotted it. He sung to it the soothing ditty of</p>
               <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <l part="N">“ ‘Tain't never gwine to rain no mo';</l>
                  <l part="N">Sun shines down on rich and po’.”</l>
               </lg>
               <p>But all was vain. Finally, in despair, he undressed Tiddlekins.
He had heard his mother say, “Of'en and of'en when a
<figure>
                     <p>HIERONYMUS SINGS A SOOTHING DITTY.</p>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="72"/>
chile is a-screamin' its breff away 'tain't nothin' ails it 'cep'n
<hi rend="italics">pins.</hi>”</p>
               <p>But there were no pins. Plenty of strings and hard knots,
but not a pin to account for the antics of the unhappy
Tiddlekins.</p>
               <p>How it <hi rend="italics">did</hi> scream! It lay on the stiffly braced knees of
Hieronymus, and puckered up its face so tightly that it looked
as if it had come fresh from a wrinkle mould. There were no
tears, but sharp, regular yells, and rollings of its head, and a
distracting monotony in its performances.</p>
               <p>“Dis here chile looks 's if it's got de measles,” muttered
Hi, gazing on the squirming atom with calm eyes of despair.
Then, running his fingers over the neck and breast of the
small Tiddlekins, he cried, with the air of one who makes a
discovery, “It's got de heat! <hi rend="italics">Dat's</hi> what ails Tiddlekins!”</p>
               <p>There was really a little breaking out on the child's body
that might account for his restlessness and squalls. And it
was <hi rend="italics">such</hi> a hot day! Perspiration streamed down Hi's back,
while his head was dry. There was not a quiver in the
tree leaves, and the silver-poplars showed only their leaden
side. The sunflowers were drooping their big heads; the flies
seemed to stick to the window-panes, and were too languid to
crawl.</p>
               <p>Hieronymus had in him the materials of which philosophers
are made. He said to himself, “ 'Tain't nothin' but heat
dat's de matter wid dis baby; so uf <hi rend="italics">cose</hi> he ought ter be cooled
off.”</p>
               <p>But how to cool him off—that was the great question. Hi
knitted his dark brows and thought intently.</p>
               <pb n="73"/>
               <p>It happened that the chiefest treasure of the Pop estate
was a deep old well that in the hottest days yielded water as
refreshing as iced champagne. The neighbors all made a
convenience of the Pop well. And half-way down its long, cool
hollow hung, pretty much all of the time, milk cans, butter
pats, fresh meats - all things that needed to be kept cool in
summer days.</p>
               <p>He looked at the hot, squirming, wretched black baby on
his lap; then he looked at the well; and, simple, straightforward
lad that he was, he put this and that together.</p>
               <p>“If I wuz ter hang Tiddlekins down de well,” he reflected,
“ 'twouldn't be mo' den three jumps of a flea befo' he's as cool
as Christmas.”</p>
               <p>With this quick-witted youth to think was to act. Before
many minutes he had stuffed poor little Tiddlekins into the
well bucket, though it must be mentioned to his credit that
he tied the baby securely in with his own suspenders.</p>
               <p>Warmed up with his exertions, content in this good
riddance of such bad rubbish as Tiddlekins, Hieronymus reposed
himself on the feather-bed, and dropped off into a sweet slumber.
From this he was aroused by the voice of a small boy.</p>
               <p>“Hello, Hi! I say, Hi Pop! whar is yer?”</p>
               <p>“Here I is!” cried Hi, starting up. “What you want?”</p>
               <p>Little Jim Rogers stood in the door-way.</p>
               <p>“Towzer's dog,” he said, in great excitement, “and daddy's
bull-pup is gwine ter have a fight dis evenin'! Come on quick,
if yer wants ter see de fun.”</p>
               <p>Up jumped Hi, and the two boys were off like a flash.
<hi rend="italics">Not one thought to Tiddlekins in the well bucket!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="74"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>DISPOSING OF TIDDLEEKINS.</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>In due time the Pop family got home, and Mother Pop,
fanning herself, was indulging in the moral reflections suitable
to the occasion, when she checked herself suddenly, exclaiming,
“But, land o' Jerusalem! whar's 'Onymus an' de baby?”</p>
               <p>“I witnessed Hieronymus,” said the elegant Savannah, “as
I wandered from school. He was with a multitude of boys,
who cheered, without a sign of disapperation, two canine beasts
that tore each other in deadly feud.”</p>
               <p>“Yer don't mean ter say, Sissy, dat 'Onymus Pop is gone
ter a dog fight?”</p>
               <p>“Such are my meaning,” said Sissy, with dignity.</p>
               <p>“Den<hi rend="italics"> whar's</hi> de baby?”</p>
               <pb n="75"/>
               <p>For answer, a long, low wail smote upon their ears, as
Savannah would have said.</p>
               <p>“Fan me!” cried Mother Pop. “Dat's Tiddlekins's voice.”</p>
               <p>“Never min' about fannin' mammy,” cried Weekly, Savannah's
twin, a youth of fifteen, who could read, and was much
addicted to tales of thunder and blood; “let's fin' de baby.
P'r'aps he's been murdered by dat ruffian Hi, an' cat's his
<hi rend="italics">ghos'</hi> dat we hears a-callin'.”</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>IN SUSPENSE.</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>A search was instituted—under the bed, in the bed, in the
wash-tub and the soup-kettle; behind the wood-pile, and in the
pea vines; up the chimney, and in the ash-hopper; but all in
vain. No Tiddlekins appeared, though still they heard him
cry.</p>
               <pb n="76"/>
               <p>“Shade of Ole Hickory!” cried the father Pop, “whar,
whar is dat chile?” Then, with a sudden lighting of the eye,
“Unchain de dog,” said he; “he'll smell him out.”</p>
               <p>There was a superannuated blood-hound pertaining to the
Pop <hi rend="italics">ménage</hi> that they kept tied up all day, under a delusion
that he was fierce. They unchained this wild animal, and
with many kicks endeavored to goad his nostrils to their
duty.</p>
               <p>It happened that a piece of fresh pork hung in the well,
and Lord Percy—so was the dog called—was hungry. So he
hurried with vivacity toward the fresh pork.</p>
               <p>“De well!” shrieked Mother Pop, tumbling down all in a
heap, and looking somehow like Turner's “Slave-ship,” as one
stumpy leg protruded from the wreck of red flannel and ruffled
petticoats.</p>
               <p>“What shall we do?” said Sissy, with a helpless squeak.</p>
               <p>“Why, git him out,” said Mr. Pop, who was the practical
one of the family.</p>
               <p>He began to draw up the well bucket, aided by Weekly,
who whispered, darkly, “Dar'll be anudder hangin' in town
befo' long, <hi rend="italics">and Hi won't miss dat hangin'.</hi>”</p>
               <p>Soon appeared a little woolly head, then half a black body,
the rest of him being securely wedged in the well bucket. He
looked like a Jack-in-the-box. But he was cool, Tiddlekins was
—no doubt of that.</p>
               <p>Mother Pop revived at sight of her offspring, still living,
and feebly sucking his thumb.</p>
               <p>“Ef we had a whiskey bath ter put him in!” she cried.</p>
               <p>Into the house flew Father Pop, seized the quart cup, and
<pb n="77"/>
                  <figure>
                     <p>“DE WELL!” SHRIEKED MOTHER POP.</p>
                  </figure>
was over to the white house on the hill in the wink of a cat's
eye.</p>
               <p>“He stammered forth his piteous tale,” said Savannah, telling
the story the next day to her school-mates; “and Judge
Chambers himself filled his cup with the best of Bourbon, and
Miss Clara came over to see us resusirate the infant.”</p>
               <pb n="78"/>
               <p>Mother Pop had Tiddlekins wrapped in hot flannel when
he got back; and with a never-to-be-sufficiently-admired economy
Mr. Pop moistened a rag with “the best of Bourbon,” and
<figure>
                     <p>RESUSCITATING TIDDLEKENS.</p>
                  </figure>
said to his wife, “Jes rub him awhile, Cynthy, an' see if dat
won't bring him roun'.”</p>
               <p>As she rubbed he absent-mindedly raised the quart cup to
his lips, and with three deep and grateful gulps the whiskey
bath went to refresh the inner man of Tiddlekins's papa.</p>
               <p>Then who so valorous and so affectionate as he? Dire
<pb n="79"/>
were his threats against Hieronymus, deep his lamentations
over his child.</p>
               <p>“My po' little lammie!” he sobbed. “Work away, Cynthy.
Dat chile mus' be saved, even if I should have ter go over
ter de judge's fur anudder quart o' whiskey. Nuthin' shall be
spared to save that preciousest kid o' my ole age.”</p>
               <p>Miss Clara did not encourage his self-sacrificing proposal;
but, for all that, it was not long before Tiddlekins grew warm
and lively, and winked at his father—so that good old man
declared - as he lay on his back, placidly sucking a pig's tail.
<figure>
                     <p>HIERONYMUS RETURNS.</p>
                  </figure>
Savannah had roasted it in the ashes, and it had been cut
from the piece of pork that had shared the well with Tiddlekins.
The pork belonged to a neighbor, by-the-way; but at
<pb n="80"/>
such a time the Pop family felt that they might dispense with
the vain and useless ceremony of asking for it.</p>
               <p>The excitement was over, the baby asleep, Miss Clara gone,
and the sun well on its way to China, when a small figure was
seen hovering diffidently about the gate. It had a limp air
of dejection, and seemed to feel some delicacy about coming
farther.</p>
               <p>“The miscreant is got back,” remarked Savannah.</p>
               <p>“Hieronymus,” called Mrs. Pop, “you may thank yo'
heavenly stars dat you ain't a murderer dis summer day—”</p>
               <p>“A-waitin' ter be hung nex' wild-grape-time,” finished
Weekly, pleasantly.</p>
               <p>Mr. Pop said nothing. But he reached down from the
mantel-shelf a long, thin something, shaped like a snake, and
quivered it in the air.</p>
               <p>Then he walked out to Hi, and, taking him by the left ear,
led him to the wood-pile.</p>
               <p>And here— But I draw a veil.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>[Illustration]</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="81"/>
            <div type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
               <head>SISTER WEEDEN'S PRAYER.</head>
               <p>YES we had gethered at the river, as the song says, to see a
sight as might have surprised the angels. Ther' wuz
a crowd, sure. They had come from the four-mile, an' the six-mile,
an' the nine-mile, an' from down in the timber, an' ther'
wuz even a pretty smart sprinklin' o' town folks, kind of apart
from the rest, with a plenty of artificial flowers in the'r hats,
an' an air of gentility that differed 'em from the farmers'
women, with the'r sun-bonnets an' babies. It wuz four o'clock
of a Sunday afternoon, an' they wuz all assembled to see
young Roland Selph baptized by Preacher Powell, who
expounded the Word four times a year at Big Muddy meetin'-
house.</p>
               <p>It wuz a'most like a meracle. Roland wuz a hard case.
My husband—who, bein' one o' the “swearin' Wallers,” as they
wuz called in Grandpar Waller's day, had a sort of ancesterl
talent for usin' strong words—an' better that than for usin'
strong drink, says I, when twitted, for what is words but a
slap-dash thrown together of letters? an' if a man chooses 'em
hard, like goose-quills, instead o' soft, like goose-down, an'
nobody's hurt, then where's the harm?—well, my husband he
allays said that Roland wuz the “darnedest man to cuss
on the prairie.” He never had had no bringin' up wuz the
<pb n="82"/>
trouble. His father, a rele active, nice man, wuz killed in a
mill six months before he wuz born, an' his mother she took
on so that she didn't have no strength to git him even so
far along as teethin'. So his grandmother she raised him
on sheep's milk an' a peach-tree switch. Kicks an' cuffs
wuz sandwiched between the poor child's meals, until the old
woman died an' left him, kithless an' kinless in the land. A
wild-lookin' lad he wuz, with a shock o' black hair that you
couldn't 'a combed with a wool-card, an' big eyes bold as the
hub of a wheel, an' clothed summer an' winter in <hi rend="italics">rags!</hi> He
wuz mightily in demand at harvest-time, for he wuz as strong
as a horse, an' hadn't had a chill since his grandmother broke
'em on him at the age of fourteen with black pepper an'
molasses an' santonine, an' a bag o' camphor at the pit of his
stomach. But people wuz powerful shy of associatin' with
him. He wuz druv to the saloons for company; an' they said
he could drink a quart o' whiskey as if it wuz spring-water.</p>
               <p>How it had come about nobody knew. Brother Powell
never wuz counted to have much influence, an' he looked
powerful little an' meachin'-like beside Roland, tall an'
broad-chested, an' as handsome as anybody in a bran'-new suit o'
brown jeans an' a white shirt clean as clean.</p>
               <p>As he went down into the water the men took off the'r
hats with a soft, loose sweep, an' the women hushed the'r
babies at the'r breasts. The sun shone out broad an' mellow;
everything seemed to listen, somehow, as the words wuz
uttered over that wild, forsakened one that made him a member
o' Christ's great family. Then what a crowdin' roun' an' a
han'-shakin' as he came out drippin', an' castin' a glance round
<pb n="83"/>
half beseechin' an' half a-darin'! It wuz wuth comin' a long
way jest to see that poor sinner a-welcomed inter the fold.</p>
               <p>But I noticed one curious thing. Mrs. Biscoe wuz there,
with her two daughters, Leila an' Jenny—Rose an' Lily we
used to call 'em, seein' as how one wuz a red beauty an' one a
white. Jenny—she wuz the fair one—wuz the most help to
her mother. Leila, for all her rosy cheeks an' black eyes, wuz 
a lazy little flitter-gibbet. Mrs. Biscoe she wuz a widow: a
little, straight, dark woman, with plenty of snap to her, who
took in sewin' for a livin', an' wuz much respected in the
Baptist society. Well, she gave a quick little nod to'ards
Roland jest before he wuz dipped, an' she said, in kind of an
undertone, “They do look nice girls, don't they?” I studied
quite a spell over this speech, but I couldn't exactly make out
what she meant by it.</p>
               <p>Some days after the baptizin', Mrs. Wysnicker of the
four-mile invited all the society to a wool-pickin'. Ther' wuzn't
any declinations, for Mrs. Wysnicker wuz a master-hand for
dinners. Never did she sit you down to her table unless she
had “fresh,” an' maybe a couple o' chickens besides; an' her
pie-crust would break inter honest flakes if you so much as
p'inted a knife at it. Furthermore, we wanted to see if her
wool was so much finer than anybody else's. She had boasted
considerable about it, an' we understood that she sheared fourteen
pounds to a sheep. So it was candle-light breakfast all
over the prairie, an' by seven o'clock we wuz mostly assembled
in Mrs. Wysnicker's sittin'-room, ready for work. The wool
wuz on a sheet in the middle of the floor, an' a powerful big
pile it wuz: seemed as if it reached nearly to the ceilin'. We
<pb n="84"/>
wuz all a-settin' round it, pretty prim, a-waitin' for the stiffness
to wear off.</p>
               <p>Ther' wuz one person I wuz surprised to see in the
company, an' that wuz Florindy Daggett. 'Twan't often anybody
sighted her at wool-pickin's or apple-parin's or rag-tackin's, for
she set up for a genteel, an' always washed dishes with, a mop.
She wuz a powerful dressy woman, too. Husband he allays
said she wuz the kind that 'ud gin a man's pocket the swinney.
But she loved <hi rend="italics">talk</hi> beyond dress. It wuz joked around
that old man Daggett told her once that he'd nuss her cheerful
through a twenty-years' spell, if her disease jest happened
to be paralysis of the tongue. Ther's apt to be mischief, too,
in the tongues of these talkie' females. Thar she set, her
mouth a-puckered up, three sand-colored curls a-hangin' as fur
as her nose on each side, an', as a last dyin' touch, <hi rend="italics">kid gloves.</hi>
We didn't none of us take much notice of her, but we started
out pickin' wool pretty pears. After a little, Florindy she
sithed an' said, “Sister Wysnicker, what's the duty of one
sister in the society when she's discovered another sister in
the act o' backslidin'?”</p>
               <p>“P'raps she might make her a present of Brother
Throckmorton's ‘Serious Review of Infant Sprinklers,’ ” says Sister
Wysnicker, who gits a laugh out of most things goin'.</p>
               <p>“This is no matter for jokin',” says Florindy, solemn as
Moses in the bulrushes.</p>
               <p>Farmer Sweet's wife spoke up very excited: “<hi rend="italics">Sister</hi>
Daggett, you <hi rend="italics">do</hi> surprise me all to pieces! “Hev you <hi rend="italics">reely</hi> caught
a backslider? A <hi rend="italics">man</hi>, of course. <hi rend="italics">Bad</hi> is the <hi rend="italics">best</hi> of 'em. Do
<hi rend="italics">pray</hi> don't wait another <hi rend="italics">minute.</hi> Tell us <hi rend="italics">all</hi> about it.” She
<pb n="85"/>
wuz a little, sharp woman, whose words tumbled out of her
mouth fast as chopped straw out of a thrashin'-machine, an
had jest about as much cash value.</p>
               <p>“No man,” says Florindy: “<hi rend="italics">it wuz a woman.</hi> An' what
she wuz doin' is so ser'ous an' awful that reveal it I won't
unless the sisters here think it is my <hi rend="italics">duty.</hi>”</p>
               <p>Well, now, do you know, not one of us had the Christian
charity to say, “Hold your tongue, Florindy.” Truth is, we
wuz dyin' to hear what it wuz: so we jest edged our cheers a
little closer together, an' sort of slacked in the wool-pickin'.</p>
               <p>“Last Sunday, about noon,” says Florindy, speakin' slow
an' impressive, “as I wuz a-returnin' home after visitin' my
brother's sick child, my throat got so dry that I knew I must
have a drink of water. So I stopped at a certain cottage on
the four-mile, where there is an althea-bush a-growin' in the
yard, an' an oleander in a tub by the steps—”</p>
               <p>“The Biscoes!”</p>
               <p>“I name no names. The front door wuz shut, an' the
blind wuz drawn close, an' I mistrusted they wuz not at
home. So I opened the slats very gently an' looked in—”</p>
               <p>“An' what did ye see? Do, for goodness' sake, stop lookin'
so mysterious.” An' Farmer Sweet's wife tore at a piece
of wool quite reckless.</p>
               <p>“<hi rend="italics">I saw the three of 'em—on the Lord's-day—in a room dark
as iniquity—a-sewin' for dear life!</hi>”</p>
               <p>“Sewin' ” “Sewin'!” “Sewin'!” “Sewin'!” “Sewin'!”</p>
               <p>You reely would have thought it wuz the hissin' of a ring
of geese.</p>
               <p>“I stood there for a minute,” says Florindy, “quite stagnated,
<pb n="86"/>
as you may say, with surprise; an', besides, I wanted to
see what they wuz sewin' on. But I couldn't make out, for the
life o' me, an' I didn't dare to open the slats any wider.”</p>
               <p>“That ain't the pint at all,” says Sister Sweet: “whether
'twas carpet-rags, or seed-bags, or satin robes for the rich, it's
all one. The sin wuz in sewin' at all on the Lord's-day.”</p>
               <p>“Unless it wuz for a corpse,” says Sister Wysnicker, “or
funeral clothes for the family.”</p>
               <p>“Well it ain't no question of a corpse this time. An'
what's to be done about it?”</p>
               <p>“I'm lookin' for Sister Biscoe every minute. She's a
mighty good hand at wool, an' she promised to come. soon as
ever she could git off.”</p>
               <p>“All I have to say,” cries Florindy, “is that when she
steps <hi rend="italics">in</hi> I steps <hi rend="italics">out.</hi> Hold countenance with sinners I won't.
You can't touch pitch an' not be defiled. Ther's doctrine
for it.”</p>
               <p>Mrs. Wysnicker looked powerful bothered, jest as if she
didn't know which way to turn. “We haven't heard from
Sister Weeden yet,” says she: “perhaps she will give us a
word in season.”</p>
               <p>Sister Weeden wuz the impressivest female in the Baptist
society. She wuz tall an' clean-cut, an' not a bend in her from
neck to knee. What she said <hi rend="italics">wuz said.</hi> She had high cheekbones,
an' black eyes, an' a great twist of milk-white hair coiled
on top of her head. “I have listened,” says she, “an' if what
Sister Daggett charges shell be proven true, we must expel
Dorothy Biscoe from the society an' leave her to the mercy
of God.”</p>
               <pb n="87"/>
               <p>Cold shivers ran down our backs: it wuz jest as if she had
said <hi rend="italics">Selah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At this minute I happened to look sideways through a
crack in the door, an' what should I see but Leila Biscoe half
stretched out on a lounge, with a picture-paper crumpled up in
her hand! Her head wuz up, an' she wuz a-listenin' with all
her ears, her face red as fire, an' her eyes sparklin', as lazy
brown eyes will when they git fired up.</p>
               <p>Up she jumped as she caught my eye an' ran out of the
other door. I said nothin' to anybody, but I quietly slipped
after the child, a-leavin' my bonnet behind. I mistrusted she
wuz goin' to meet her mother; an', sure enough, Mrs. Biscoe
an' Jenny wuz footin' it along the road, when Leila flew at 'em,
raisin' the dust with a swirl around her. “Mother,” she cries,
“dons go near 'em. <hi rend="italics">Don't!</hi> the scandalous old cats!”</p>
               <p>“Leily Biscoe! what under the blue sky <hi rend="italics">air</hi> you talkin'
about?” She took the child by the arm an' plumped her down
into a fence-corner. “Now!” says she.</p>
               <p>“Why, mammie, that horrid, sneakin', pryin', white-eyed—”</p>
               <p>“<hi rend="italics">Leila!</hi>”</p>
               <p>“Well, then, the beautiful Mistress Florinda Daggett peeped
into our windows last Sunday—”</p>
               <p>“Oh!”</p>
               <p>“An' saw us sewin'; an' they are havin' no end of a time
about it, an' won't sit in the room with you, an' say you shall
be expelled from the society—”</p>
               <p>“So!”</p>
               <p>I put in a word now, an' tried to smooth down matters;
but, my stars! Sister Biscoe looked as if she could bite steel.</p>
               <pb n="88"/>
               <p>“Let's go home, mammie,” said Jenny, beginnin' to cry.</p>
               <p>“<hi rend="italics">Home!</hi>” says she: “we're goin' to the wool-pickin'.”</p>
               <p>“But I tell you,” cried Leila, “they won't have you; they
will insult you.”</p>
               <p>“You can go home if you want to.”</p>
               <p>Leila felt, maybe, that she hadn't deserved sech a snub, so
she tossed her head an' followed her mar. I could hardly keep
up with 'em. I hadn't felt so warmed up an' excited not sence
I brought Belle Burns through a congestive chill after the
doctor had give her up.</p>
               <p>My soul! them women jumped when they seen the widow
an' her two daughters standin' at the door, as if the sheared
sheep wuz a-chargin' in after the wool they'd been robbed of.</p>
               <p>“I hear,” says Sister Biscoe, “that my friends an' neighbors
have been makin' mighty free with my name.”</p>
               <p>“Lor!” says Sister Wysnicker, in a quaverin' sort o' voice;
“who's been a-bearin' any slanderous tale to you?”</p>
               <p>“Slanderous, is it? Well, my daughter Leila is the bearer.
I sent her on ahead of me this mornin', an' she wuzn't no
farther from your talk than the next room.”</p>
               <p>“Nobody's said nothin' that they ain't willin' to stand by,”
snapped Florindy Daggett. “Women that use God's day for
puttin' money in their pockets must be ready to face the
consequences.”</p>
               <p>Two red spots came out on the widow's cheeks; her eyes
shot sparks like flints struck together. “I've nothin' to say to
<hi rend="italics">you</hi>,” she says, turnin' her back on Florindy, “but the rest of
you shall hear what's behind the story she's told. It looks as
if those that has known me all my life, watched me strugglin'
<pb n="89"/>
with poverty, workin' to keep a roof over these two girls that
wuz left babes on my hands, an' never heard so much as a
breath against me or mine, <hi rend="italics">might 'a waited a little</hi> before
talkin' about expellin' me from the society.”</p>
               <p>Everybody colored up, an' Farmer Sweet's wife she
whimpered a little.</p>
               <p>“I <hi rend="italics">wish</hi> you'd take a cheer, Sister Biscoe,” said Sister
Wysnicker, real entreatin'.</p>
               <p>“I'll sit in no house nor break bread under no roof till my
pardon has been asked by all that thought ill of me.”</p>
               <p>Florindy sniffed, but no one j'ined in.</p>
               <p>“Last Friday night a week ago,” says Sister Biscoe, ”Roland
Selph knocked with his ridin'-whip against my door.
Jenny opened it, a-drawin' back when she saw who it wuz, for
Roland has a kiss an' a joke for every girl who will let him
come near enough. But he walked in very quiet, a-followin'
her into the back room, where I sat sewin'.</p>
               <p>“ ‘Mrs. Biscoe,’ says he, ‘can you make me some decent
clothes agin Sunday?’</p>
               <p>“ ‘Not agin Sunday, Roland,’ says I, ‘for it's Friday night
now.’</p>
               <p>“He set quite a while without sayin' anything, a-hittin' his
boot with his whip, an' finally he said, in a loud, defiant sort
of way, that he <hi rend="italics">hed</hi> thought of bein' baptized Sunday, if he
could git anything to put on his back, for he wuz perfectly
ragged.</p>
               <p>“ ‘You baptized!’ says Leila, pertly. ‘Is the world comin'
to an end?’</p>
               <p>“ ‘Mebbe,’ says he, very sullen, an' got up as if he would
<pb n="90"/>
go. But I found strength to stop him. ‘Good gracious!’ says
I, ‘don't fly off the let's talk it over.’</p>
               <p>“The long and the short of it is that I soon saw Roland
wuz a-tremblin' between two worlds. He wuz that unregenerate
that he wouldn't face the public at Big Muddy without the
befittin' clothes, yet the Spirit wuz so workin' within him that
he had set his heart on sealin' himself to God the comin'
Sunday. I thought of suggestin' to him to wait until Brother
Powell came round again; but, seein' as how he wuz just out
of the devil's clutches by a needle's length, as you may say, I
didn't <hi rend="italics">dare</hi> to say ‘put it off’ to him. Would any sister here
have done it?”</p>
               <p>“NO!” says Sister Weeden, lettin' the word drop very
ponderous.</p>
               <p>“It might be then or never. To be the means of stoppin'
him wuz more of a responsibility than I could shoulder. There
wuz tears on Jenny's cheeks, an' she whispered to me, ‘Say
that you will, mammie.’ An' even Leila nodded when I looked
inquirin' at her. ‘Roland,’ says I, ‘we'll do it. Come for your
clothes Sunday noon. They'll be ready, and without money
an' without price, for it's the Lord's work.’</p>
               <p>“We got 'em cut out that night, an' we worked steady
Saturday, an' Saturday night, an' Sunday mornin'. Yes, we did
work on the Lord's-day, for mortal fingers couldn't 'a finished
the job without.</p>
               <p>“By luck an' plannin' we saved all the hand-sewin' till the
last, so that the noise of a machine runnin' on Sunday shouldn't
bring reproach on my house. For many a thing is all right if
it's kept quiet that fools label wrong if it comes to their ears.</p>
               <pb n="91"/>
               <p>“That's about the whole story. You all saw Roland Selph
baptized that afternoon, an' can bear witness to how modest
an' handsome he looked in his clean new suit, with the light
of the Gospel a-shinin' on his face. I won't speak of myself;
but as for my two girls, who had gone without rest an' food,
an' worked their fingers sore, to put him where he stood, I
only hope that all of you said ‘Amen’ to Brother Powell's
prayer with as clean a conscience as theirs. An' I will say
for myself that, just as sure as my name is Dorothy Biscoe,
I would do it all over again! <hi rend="italics">An' it's a business between me
an' my God.</hi>”</p>
               <p>She had swept us all along; and we wuz throwed into a
confusion when she stopped short an' sudden, as if waitin' for
some one to speak. Nobody knew jest how to lead off, an' it
wuz a relief when Sister Weeden rose up an' says, “Let us pray!”</p>
               <p>Down we all knelt promiscuous, the wool a-scatterin' from
our laps, an' Sister Weeden, without stoppin' a minute to think
up her words—for prayin' comes to her by nature—began:
“O Father, our hearts is vile an' unclean as the wool we've
been pickin' out this day; quick to catch at evil as sheep's
backs to catch at brambles an' briers in pushin' through a
thicket; clogged with meanness an' jealousies an' suspicions,
till they're got no will nor power to beat harmonious with thy
Spirit, which is love. O Lord, we'd give up, despairin', if it
wuzn't that immortal patience can cleanse them of trash that
defiles; if it wuzn't that Immanuel's blood can wash the blackness
of blackness away; if it wuzn't that we knew forgiveness
wuz held out free as long as breath held body an' soul
together Every day Satan dangles some new temptation before
<pb n="92"/>
us, an' we fall inter sin. Most especial to-day hev we failed
in charity toward our sister here, condemnin' her without a
hearin', an' never a-dreamin' that it wuz the Lord's work to
which she give his day, as sinless as the act of Him who
plucked the ears of corn an' wuz reproached by the lip-servin'
Jews. Put it inter her heart, O Father, to pardon us without
much more said about it. All for the dear sake of him who
died for us. Amen.”</p>
               <p>Then we said the Lord's Prayer all together, an' somehow
a good, healthy shame laid hold of us an' made us humble in
our own conceit for once.</p>
               <p>We didn't exactly like to look Sister Biscoe in the eye
when we got up. We didn't know but what she'd hold out
till we had made apologies all 'round; an' how to do it wuz
more than we knew.</p>
               <p>But, dear sakes! Sister Wysnicker—she's such a comfortable
woman—she says, quite natural, “Won't you take off your
things, Sister Biscoe, an' help us out with this wool? It's a
powerful sight worse 'n I looked for it to be.”</p>
               <p>“To be sure,” says Sister Biscoe, a little hystericky, but
very cheerful; “ain't that what I'm here for?”</p>
               <p>So, pretty soon we wuz workin' like bees, an' chattin' by
spells, as neighbors should, about the harvestin', an' the hard
work, an' the aguey, an' the Republican rally, an' the thrivin'
business of them wicked saloons when politics wuz flyin' all
abroad, an' other subjects harmonious to the company.</p>
               <p>Jenny she stood by her mother and helped; but as for Miss
Leila, she tossed her head and walked off home, as unforgivin'
a young one as ever listened to prayer with a stony heart.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="93"/>
            <div org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
               <head type="chapter">AUNT ANNIKY'S TEETH.</head>
               <p>AUNT ANNIKY was an African dame, fifty years old, and
of an imposing presence. As a waffle-maker she possessed
a gift beyond the common, but her unapproachable
talent lay in the province of nursing. She seemed born for
the benefit of sick people. She should have been painted
with the apple of healing in her hand. For the rest, she was
a funny, illiterate old darkey, vain, affable, and neat as a pink.</p>
               <p>On one occasion my mother had a dangerous illness.
Aunt Anniky nursed her through it, giving herself no rest
night nor day until her patient had come “back to de walks
an' ways ob life,” as she expressed the dear mother's recovery.
My father, overjoyed and grateful, felt that we owed this result
quite as much to Aunt Anniky as to our family doctor, so he
announced his intention of making her a handsome present,
and, like King Herod, left her free to choose what it should
be. I shall never forget how Aunt Anniky looked as she
stood there smiling and bowing, and bobbing the funniest
little courtesies all the way down to the ground.</p>
               <p>And you would never guess what it was the old woman
asked for.</p>
               <p>“Well, Mars' Charles,” said she (she had been one of our
old servants, and always called my father Mars' Charles), “to
<pb n="94"/>
tell you de livin' trufe, my soul an' body is a-yearnin' fur a
han'sum chany set o' teef.”</p>
               <p>“A set of teeth!” cried father, surprised enough. “And
have you none left of your own?”</p>
               <p>“I has gummed it fur a good many ye'rs,” said Aunt
Anniky, with a sigh; “but not wishin' ter be ongrateful ter my
<figure>
                     <p>“MY SOUL AN' BODY IS A-YEARNIN' FUR A HAN'SUM CHANY SET O' TEEF.”</p>
                  </figure>
obligations, I owns ter havin' five nateral teef. But dey is po'
sogers: dey shirks battle. One ob dem's got a little somethin'
in it as lively as a speared worm, an' I tell you when anything
teches it, hot or cold, it jest makes me <hi rend="italics">dance!</hi> An' anudder
is in my top jaw, an' ain't got no match fur it in de bottom
one; an' one is broke off nearly to de root; an' de las' two is
<pb n="95"/>
so yeller dat I's ashamed ter show 'em in company, an' so I lif's
my turkey tail ter my mouf every time I laughs or speaks.”</p>
               <p>Father turned to mother with a musing air. “The curious
student of humanity,” he remarked, “traces resemblances where
they are not obviously conspicuous. Now, at the first blush
one would not think of any common ground of meeting for
our Aunt Anniky and the Empress Josephine. Yet that fine
French lady introduced the fashion of handkerchiefs by
continually raising delicate lace <hi rend="italics">mouchoirs</hi> to her lips to hide her
bad teeth. Aunt Anniky lifts her turkey tail! It really seems
that human beings should be classed by <hi rend="italics">strata</hi>, as if they were
metals in the earth. Instead of dividing by nations, let us
class by qualities. So we might find Turk, Jew, Christian,
fashionable lady and washer-woman, master and slave, hanging
together, like cats on a clothes-line, by some connecting cord
of affinity—”</p>
               <p>“In the mean time,” said my mother, mildly, “Aunt Anniky
is waiting to know if she is to have her teeth.”</p>
               <p>“Oh, surely, surely!” cried father, coming out of the clouds,
with a start. “I am going to the village to-morrow, Anniky,
in the spring wagon. I will take you with me, and we will see
what the dentist can do for you.”</p>
               <p>“Bless yo' heart, Mars' Charles!” said the delighted
Anniky; “you're jest as good as yo' blood an' yo' name, an' mo'
I <hi rend="italics">couldn't</hi> say.”</p>
               <p>The morrow came, and with it Aunt Anniky, gorgeously
arrayed in a flaming red calico, a bandanna handkerchief, and
a string of carved yellow beads that glistened on her bosom
like fresh buttercups on a hill-slope.</p>
               <pb n="96"/>
               <p>I had petitioned to go with the party, for, as we lived on
a plantation, a visit to the village was something of an event.</p>
               <p>A brisk drive soon brought us to the centre of “the
Square.” A glittering sign hung brazenly from a high window
on its western side, bearing, in raised black letters, the
name Doctor Alonzo Babb.</p>
               <p>Dr. Babb was the dentist and the odd fish of our village.
He beams in my memory as a big, round man, with hair and
smiles all over his face, who talked incessantly, and said things
to make your blood run cold.</p>
               <p>“Do you see this ring?” he said, as he bustled about,
polishing his instruments, and making his preparations for the
sacrifice of Aunt Anniky. He held up his right hand, on the
forefinger of which glistened a ring the size of a dog-collar.
“Now, what d'ye s'pose that's made of?”</p>
               <p>“Brass,” suggested father, who was funny when not
philosophical.</p>
               <p>“<hi rend="italics">Brass!</hi>” cried Dr. Babb, with a withering look: “it's
virgin gold, that ring is. And where d'ye s'pose I found the
gold?”</p>
               <p>My father ran his hands into his pockets in a retrospective
sort of way.</p>
               <p>“In the mouths of my patients, every grain of it,” said the
dentist, with a perfectly diabolical smack of the lips: “old
fillings—plugs, you know—that I saved, and had made up into
this shape. Good deal of sentiment about such a ring as this.”</p>
               <p>“Sentiment of a mixed nature, I should say,” murmured
my father, with a grimace.</p>
               <p>“Mixed?—rather! A speck here, a speck there. Some
<pb n="97"/>
times an eye, oftener a jaw, occasionally a front. More than a
hundred men, I s'pose, have helped in the cause.”</p>
               <p>“Law, doctor! you beats de birds, you does,” cried Aunt
Anniky, whose head was as flat as the floor where her reverence
bump should have been; “you know how dey snatches
de wool from every bush to make deir nests.”</p>
               <p>“Lots of company for me that ring is,” said the doctor,
ignoring the pertinent, or impertinent, interruption. “Often,
as I sit in the twilight, I twirl it around and around, a-thinking
of the wagon-loads of food it has masticated, the blood
that has flowed over it, the groans that it has cost— Now,
old lady, if you will sit just here—”</p>
               <p>He motioned Aunt Anniky, to the chair, into which she
dropped in a limp sort of way, recovering herself immediately,
however, and sitting bolt-upright in a rigid attitude of defiance.
Some moments of persuasion were necessary before she
could be induced to lean back and allow Dr. Babb's fingers
on her nose while she breathed the laughing-gas; but once
settled, the expression faded from her countenance almost as
quickly as a magic-lantern picture vanishes. I watched her
nervously, my attention divided between her vacant-looking
face and a dreadful picture on the wall. It represented Dr.
Babb himself minus the hair, but with double the number of
smiles, standing by a patient from whose mouth he had
apparently just extracted a huge molar that he held triumphantly
in his forceps. A gray-haired old gentleman regarded the pair
with benevolent interest. The photograph was entitled, “His
First Tooth.”</p>
               <p>“Attracted by that picture?” said Dr. Alonzo, affably, his
<pb n="98"/>
fingers on Aunt Anniky's pulse. “My par had that struck off
the first time I ever got a tooth out. That's par with the gray
hair and the benediction attitude. Tell you, he was proud of
me! I had such an awful tussle with that tooth! Thought
the old fellow's jaw was bound to break! But I got it out,
and after that my par took me with him 'round the country - 
starring the provinces, you know—and I practiced on the
natives.”</p>
               <p>By this time Aunt Anniky was well under the influence
of the gas, and in an incredibly short space of time her five
teeth were out. As she came to herself, I am sorry to say,
she was rather silly, and quite mortified me by winking at Dr.
Babb in the most confidential manner, and repeating over and
over again, “Honey, yer ain't harf as smart as yer thinks yer
is!”</p>
               <p>After a few weeks of sore gums Aunt Anniky appeared
radiant with her new teeth. The effect was certainly funny.
In the first place, blackness itself was not so black as Aunt
Anniky. She looked as if she had been dipped in ink and
polished off with lamp-black. Her very eyes showed but the
faintest rim of white. But those teeth were white enough to
make up for everything. She had selected them herself, and
the little, ridiculous, milk-white things were more fitted for the
mouth of a Titania than for the great cavern in which Aunt
Anniky's tongue moved and had its being. The gums above
them were black, and when she spread her wide mouth in a
laugh it always reminded me of a piano-lid opening suddenly
and showing all the black and white ivories at a glance. Aunt
Anniky laughed a good deal, too, after getting her teeth in,
<pb n="99"/>
                  <figure>
                     <p>“HONEY, YER AIN'T HARF AS SMART AS YER THINKS YER IS!”</p>
                  </figure>
and declared she had never been so happy in her life. It was
observed, to her credit, that she put on no airs of pride, but
was as sociable as ever, and made nothing of taking out her
teeth and handing them around for inspection among her
curious and admiring visitors. On that principle of human
nature which glories in attracting attention to the weakest
part, she delighted in tough meats, stale bread, green fruits,
and all other eatables that test the biting quality of the teeth.
But finally destruction came upon them in a way that no one
could have foreseen.</p>
               <pb n="100"/>
               <p>Uncle Ned was an old colored man, who lived alone in a
cabin not very far from Aunt Anniky's, but very different from
hers in point of cleanliness and order. In fact, Uncle Ned's
wealth, apart from a little corn crop, consisted in a lot of fine
young pigs that ran in and out of the house at all times, and
were treated by their owner as tenderly as if they had been his
children. One fine day the old man fell sick of a fever, and he
sent in haste for Aunt Anniky to come and nurse him. He
agreed to give her a pig in case she brought him through;
should she fail to do so, she was to receive no pay. Well,
Uncle Ned got well, and the next thing we heard was that
he refused to pay the pig. My father was usually called on
to settle all the disputes in the neighborhood; so one morning
Anniky and Ned appeared before him, both looking very
indignant.</p>
               <p>“I'd jes like ter tell yer, Mars' Charles,” began Uncle Ned,
“ov de trick dis miser'ble ole nigger played on me.”</p>
               <p>“Go on, Ned,” said my father, with a resigned air.</p>
               <p>“Well, it war de fift' night o' de fever,” said Uncle Ned,
“an' I wuz a-tossin' an' a-moanin', an' ole Anniky jes lay back
in her cheer an' snored as ef a dozen frogs wuz in her throat.
I wuz a-perishin' an' a-burnin' wid thirst—an' I hollered to
Anniky; but lor! I might as well 'a hollered to a tombstone!
It wuz ice I wanted; an' I knowed dar wuz a glass somewhar
on my table wid cracked ice in it. Lor! lor! how dry I wuz!
I neber longed fur whiskey in my born days ez I panted fur
dat ice. It wuz powerful dark, fur de grease wuz low in de
lamp, an' de wick spluttered wid a dyin' flame. But I felt
aroun', feeble like an' slow, till my fingers touched a glass. I
<pb n="101"/>
pulled it to me, an' I run my hen' in an' grabbed de ice, as I
s'posed, an' flung it in my mouf, an' crunched an' crunched—”</p>
               <p>Here there was an awful pause. Uncle Ned pointed his
thumb at Anniky, looked wildly at my father, and said, in a
hollow voice: “<hi rend="italics">It wuz Anniky's teef.</hi>”</p>
               <p>My father threw back his head and laughed as I had never
heard him laugh. Mother from her sofa joined in. I was
doubled up-like a jackknife in the corner. But as for the
<figure>
                     <p>“IT WUZ ANNIKY'S TEEF.”</p>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="102"/>
principals in the affair, neither of their faces moved a muscle.
They saw no joke. Aunt Anniky, in a dreadful, muffled,
squashy sort of voice, took up the tale:</p>
               <p>“Nexsh ting I knowed, Marsh Sharles, somebody's sheizin'
me by de head, a-jammin' it up 'gin de wall, a-jawin' at me like
de angel Gabriel at de rish ole sinners in de bad plashe—an'
afar wash ole Ned a-spittin' like a black cat, an' a-howlin' so
dreadful dat I tought he wash de debil; an' when I got de
light, afar wash my beautiful chany teef a-flung aroun' like
scattered seed-corn on de flo', an' Ned a-swarin' he'd have de
law o' me.”</p>
               <p>“An' arter all dat,” broke in Uncle Ned, “she purtends to
lay a claim fur my pig. But I says no, sir; I don't pay nobody
nothin' who's played me a trick like dat.”</p>
               <p>“Trick!” said Aunt Anniky, scornfully; “whar's de trick?
Tink I wanted yer ter eat my teef? An' furdermo', Marsh
Sharles, dar's jes dis about it. When dat night set in dar
warn's no mo' hope fur ole Ned den fur a foundered sheep.
Laws-a-mussy! cat's why I went ter sleep. I wanted ter hev
strengt' ter put on his burial clo'es in de mornin'. But don'
yer see, Marsh Sharles, dat when he got so mad it brought
on a sweat dat <hi rend="italics">broke de fever!</hi> It saved him! But fur all dat,
arter munchin' an' manglin' my chany teef, he has de imperdence
of tryin' to 'prive me of de pig dat I honestly 'arned.”</p>
               <p>It was a hard case. Uncle Ned sat there a very image of
injured dignity, while Aunt Anniky bound a red handkerchief
around her mouth and fanned herself with her turkey
tail.</p>
               <p>“I am sure I don't know how to settle the matter,” said
<pb n="103"/>
father, helplessly. “Ned, I don't see but that you'll have to
pay up.”</p>
               <p>“Neber, Mars' Charles—neber!”</p>
               <p>“Well, suppose you get married?” suggested father, brilliantly.
“That will unite your interests, you know.”</p>
               <p>Aunt Anniky tossed her head. Uncle Ned was old,
wizened, wrinkled as a raisin, but he eyed Anniky over with a
supercilious gaze, and said, with dignity, “Ef I wanted ter
marry, I could git a likely young gal.”</p>
               <p>All the four points of Anniky's turban shook with
indignation. “Pay me fur dem chany teef!” she hissed.</p>
               <p>Some visitors interrupted the dispute at this time, and the
two old darkies went away.</p>
               <p>A week later Uncle Ned appeared, with rather a sheepish
look.</p>
               <p>“Well, Mars' Charles,” he said, “I's 'bout concluded dat I'll
marry Anniky.”</p>
               <p>“Ah! is that so?”</p>
               <p>“ 'Pears like it's de onliest way I kin save my pigs,” said
Uncle Ned, with a sigh. “When she's married she's boun' ter
<hi>'bey</hi> me. Women, <hi rend="italics">'bey</hi> your husban's; cat's what de good Book
says.”</p>
               <p>“Yes, she will <hi rend="italics">bay</hi> you, I don't doubt,” said my father,
making a pun that Uncle Ned could not appreciate.</p>
               <p>“An' ef ever she opens her jaw ter me 'bout dem ar teef,'
he went on, “I'll <hi rend="italics">mash</hi> her.”</p>
               <p>Uncle Ned tottered on his legs like an unscrewed fruit
stand, and I had my own opinion as to his “mashing” Aunt
Anniky. This opinion was confirmed the next day when my
<pb n="104"/>
father offered her his congratulations. “You are old enough
to know your own mind,” he remarked.</p>
               <p>“I's ole, maybe,” said Anniky, “but so is a oak-tree, an' it's
wigorous, I reckon. I's a purty wigorous sort o' growth myself,
an' I reckon I'll have my own way wid Ned. I'm gwine
ter fatten dem pigs o' his'n, an' you see ef I don't sell 'em nex'
Christmas fur money 'nouf ter git a new string o' chany teef.”</p>
               <p>“Look here, Anniky,” said father, with a burst of generosity,
“you and Ned will quarrel about those teeth till the day
of doom; so I will make you a wedding present of another set,
that you may begin married life in harmony.”</p>
               <p>Aunt Anniky expressed her gratitude. “An' dis time,” she said,
with sudden fury, “I sleeps wid 'em in.”</p>
               <p>The teeth were presented, and the wedding preparations
began. The expectant bride went over to Ned's cabin and
gave it such a clearing up as it had never had. But Ned did
not seem happy. He devoted himself entirely to his pigs, and
wandered about, looking more wizened every day. Finally he
came to our gate and beckoned to me mysteriously.</p>
               <p>“Come over to my house, honey,” he whispered, “an' bring
a pen an' ink an' a piece o' paper wid yer. I wants you ter
write me a letter.”</p>
               <p>I ran into the house for my little writing-desk, and followed
Uncle Ned to his cabin.</p>
               <p>“Now, honey,” he said, after barring the door carefully,
“don't you ax me no questions, but jes put down de words
dat comes out o' my mouf on dat ar paper.”</p>
               <p>“Very well, Uncle Ned; go on.”</p>
               <p>“Anniky Hobbleston,” he began, “dat weddin' ain't a-gwine
<pb n="105"/>
ter come off. You cleans up too much ter suit me. I ain't
used ter so much water splashin' aroun'. Dirt is warmin'.
Spec' I'd freeze dis winter if you wuz here. An' you got too
much tongue. Besides, I's got anudder wife over in Tipper.
An' I ain't a-gwine ter marry. As fur havin' de law, I's a-leavin'
dese parts, an' I takes de pigs wid me. Yer can't fin' <hi rend="italics">dem</hi>, an'
yer can't fin' me. <hi rend="italics">Fur I ain't a-gwine ter marry.</hi> I wuz born
a bachelor, an' a bachelor will I represent myself befo' de
judgment-seat. If you gives yer promise ter say no mo' 'bout dis
marryin' business, p'raps I'll come back some day. So no mo'
at present from your humble worshipper,—NED CUDDY.”</p>
               <p>“Isn't that last part rather inconsistent?” said I, greatly
amused.</p>
               <p>“Yes, honey, if yer says so; an' it's kind o' soothin' to de
feelin's of a woman, yer know.”</p>
               <p>I wrote it all down, and read it aloud to Uncle Ned.</p>
               <p>“Now, my chile,” he said, “I'm a-gwine ter git on my mule
soon as de moon rises, an' drive my pigs ter Col'water Gap,
whar I'll stay an' fish. Soon as I'm well gone you take dis
letter ter Anniky, but <hi rend="italics">min'</hi> don't tell whar I's gone. An' if
she takes it all right, an' promises ter let me alone, you write
me a letter, an' I'll git de fust Methodis' preacher I run across
in de woods ter read it ter me. Den, ef it's all right, I'll come
back an' weed yer flower-gyardin fur yer as purty as preachin'.”</p>
               <p>I agreed to do all Uncle Ned asked, and we parted like
conspirators. The next morning Uncle Ned was missing, and
after waiting a reasonable time I explained the matter to my
parents, and went over with his letter to Aunt Anniky.</p>
               <p>“Powers above!” was her only comment as I got through
<pb n="106"/>
the remarkable epistle. Then, after a pause to collect her
thoughts, she seized me by the shoulder, saying: “Run to yo'
pappy, honey, quick, an' ax him if he's gwine ter stick ter his
bargain 'bout de teef. You know he p'intedly said dey wuz a
<hi rend="italics">weddin'</hi> gif'.”</p>
               <p>Of course my father sent word that she must keep the
teeth, and my mother added a message of sympathy, with a
present of a pocket-handkerchief to dry Aunt Anniky's tears.</p>
               <p>But “It's all right,” said that sensible old soul, opening her
piano-lid with a cheerful laugh. “Bless you, chile, it wuz de
teef I wanted, not de man! An', honey, you jes sen' word to
dat shif'less ole nigger, ef you know whar he's gone, to come
back home an' git his crap in de groun'; an', as fur as I'm
consarned, you jes let him know dat I wouldn't pick him up
wid a ten-foot pole, not ef he wuz ter beg me on his knees till
de millennial day.”</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>“BLESS YOU, CHILE, IT WUZ DE TEEF I WANTED, NOT DE MAN!”</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="107"/>
            <div type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
               <head>DR. JEX'S PREDICAMENT</head>
               <p>IT was the funniest thing that I ever saw in my life. Cruikshank
would have gloried in it. I wish I had him here
to illustrate that scene with the spirited vigor that only his
dancing pencil gives.</p>
               <p>It was in Kentucky that it happened—that pleasant land
of blue-grass, and tobacco, and fine stock, and white-teethed
girls. Mabel, my sister, had married Dick Hucklestone, and
they had begun life in great contentment and a little three-roomed
house scarcely big enough to hold the bridal presents.
But they were happy, hearty, healthy. They had two cows,
ice-cream every day, a charming baby, and Uncle Brimmer.
Who shall say that their cup was not full? Indeed, they
thought it full before Uncle Brimmer added himself thereto
—a very ponderous rose-leaf. He was one of our old family
servants, who fondly believed that Miss Mabel and her young
husband would never be able to get on without him. He
walked all the way from Mississippi to Kentucky, with his
things tied up in a meal sack, and presented himself before
Mabel, announcing affably that he had come to “stay on.”</p>
               <p>“But I haven't any place for you, Uncle Brimmer,” said
Mabel, divided between hospitality and embarrassment.</p>
               <p>“Lor', honey, you kin jes tuck me aroun' <hi rend="italics">anywhar.</hi> I don't
take up no room.”</p>
               <pb n="108"/>
               <p>Mabel looked thoughtfully upon the big, brown, gray-
whiskered old negro, whose proportions were those of a Hercules,
and shook her head. “You are not a Tom Thumb, Uncle Brimmer.”</p>
               <p>“No, ma'am,” said he, submissively, “but I've got his <hi rend="italics">sperit.</hi>
Couldn't I sleep in de kitchen, honey?” he went on, with
insinuating sweetness.</p>
               <p>“No, indeed!” cried our young house-keeper. “I put my
foot down on anybody sleeping in the kitchen.”</p>
               <p>Aunt Patsey, the cook, stood by, balancing a pan of flour
on her head, one fat hand on her hip. I suspected her of a
personal interest in the matter, and indeed she afterward
acknowledged that she thought Uncle Brimmer's coming would
prove a “blessin' to her feet.” Those feet of hers had been
saved many steps through the service of her ten-year-old
daughter, Nancy Palmira Kate—called Nanky Pal for short.
But of late Nanky's services had been called into requisition
as a nurse, and Aunt Patsey, who was fat and scant o' breath,
thought she had too much to do; and so she viewed with
evident delight the stalwart proportions of our good-natured
giant from the South.</p>
               <p>“Dar's de lof', Miss Mabel,” she suggested.</p>
               <p>“It is too small, and is cluttered up with things already.”</p>
               <p>“Oh, sho, chile, afar ain't nothin' in dat lof' 'cep' de 'taters,
an' de peppers, an' de dried apples, an' some strings o' terbacker,
an' de broken plough, an' some odds an' ends o' de
chiller's, an Lucy Crittenden's pups. Lor', afar ain't nothin
ter speak of in de lof'.”</p>
               <p>“He can't get in at the window,” said Mabel, shifting her
ground.</p>
               <pb n="109"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>“COULDN'T I SLEEP IN DE KITCHEN?”</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb n="111"/>
               <p>“Lemme try,” said Uncle Brimmer.</p>
               <p>The kitchen was a small log-cabin, some distance from
the house—“in good hollerin' reach,” to quote Aunt Patsey.
Above it was a low room, or loft, crowded with the miscellaneous
articles enumerated. The only way of getting into it
was from the outside. A ladder against the side of the cabin
admitted one, through a little window, no larger, I am sure,
than that of a railway coach, into this storehouse of treasures.
Nanky Pal, who was as slim as a snake, was usually selected
to fetch and carry through the small aperture. But Uncle
Brimmer!</p>
               <p>“I'm pretty sho' I kin do it,” he said, squinting up one eye,
as he took off his coat and prepared to try.</p>
               <p>We stood in the door-way as he cautiously went up the
ladder; and after an exciting moment he pushed himself through
the window, and, turning, smiled triumphantly.</p>
               <p>This settled the matter. A cot bed was procured for Uncle
Brimmer, and he soon became the main-stay of the family.
Cheerfully avoiding all the work possible; indifferently as an
ostrich eating all he could find in cupboards or highways;
grimly playing hobgoblin for baby; gayly twanging his banjo
on moonlight nights—memory recalls thee, with a smile, Uncle
Brimmer! I can close my eyes now and recall him, big, shapeless,
indistinct in the semi-darkness, as he sat under the mulberry-tree,
singing:</p>
               <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <l part="N">“Wish I wuz in Tennessee,</l>
                  <l part="N">A-settin' in my cheer,</l>
                  <l part="N">Jug o' whiskey by my side,</l>
                  <l part="N">An' arms aroun' my dear!”</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="112"/>
               <p>This was his favorite. Who shall doubt that it expressed to
him all the poetry, romance, passion, of life?</p>
               <p>After a time Uncle Brimmer fell ill, and we sent for a
doctor.</p>
               <p>Dr. Trattles Jex was the medical man of our county. He
lived in Middleburn, seven miles away, and he came trotting
over on a great bay horse, with a pair of saddle-bags hanging
<figure>
                     <p>DR. JEX.</p>
                  </figure>
like Gilpin's bottles, one on either side. He looked as diminutive
as a monkey perched on the tall horse's back, and indeed
he was “a wee bit pawky body,” as was said of Tommy
Moore. But, bless me! he was as pompous and self-important
as though he had found the place to stand on, and could move
the world with his little lever. A red handkerchief carefully
pinned across his chest showed that he had lungs and a
mother. His boots were polished to the last degree. His
pink and beardless face betrayed his youth; and his voice—
<pb n="113"/>
ah, his voice!—what a treasure it would have been could he
have let it out to masqueraders! Whether it was just changing
from that of youth to that of a man, or whether, like reading
and writing, it “came by nature,” I can't tell. One instant
it was deep and bass, the next, squeaking and soprano. No
even tenor about that voice!</p>
               <p>He held out his hand, with, “GOOD-MORNING, <hi rend="italics">Mrs.
Hucklestone.</hi>
                  <hi rend="italics">I hope</hi> THE BABY HAS NOT HAD <hi rend="italics">an
attack?</hi>”</p>
               <p>I popped into the dining-room to giggle, but little well-bred
Mabel did not even smile.</p>
               <p>“Oh no!” she cried; “it is Uncle Brimmer.”</p>
               <p>The doctor offered to see him at once. Mabel got up to
lead the way. Up to this moment I warrant it had not struck
her as anything out-of-the-way that she must invite Dr. Jex to
climb a ladder and crawl through a window to get at his
patient. But as she looked at him, speckless, spotless, gloved,
scented, curled, then at the ladder leaning against the wall in
a disreputable, rickety sort of way, a sense of incongruity seemed
borne in on her soul. To add to her distress and my hilarity,
we saw that Uncle Brimmer had hung out of the window
some mysterious under-rigging that he wore. Long, red, and
ragged, it “flaunted in the breeze” as picturesquely as the
American flag on a Fourth of July.</p>
               <p>“I am afraid, doctor, it will be a little awkward,” faltered
Mabel; “Uncle Brimmer is up there;” and she waved her lily
hand.</p>
               <p>“An' you'll have ter climb de ladder,” put in Nanky Pal,
with a	disrespectful chuckle.</p>
               <pb n="114"/>
               <p>I thought the little doctor gasped; but he recovered himself
gallantly, and said:</p>
               <p>“AS A BOY I HAVE CLIMBED <hi rend="italics">trees, and</hi> THINK I
CAN ASCEND A l<hi rend="italics">adder as a man;</hi>” and he smiled
heroically.</p>
               <p>We watched him. He was encumbered by the saddle-bags,
but he managed very well, and had nearly reached the top,
when suddenly Uncle Brimmer's head and shoulders
protruded, giving him the look of a snail half out of its shell.</p>
               <p>“Here's my pulse, doctor,” he cried, blandly, extending his
bared arm. “ 'Tain't no place for you up here. An' here's
my tongue.” Then out went his tongue for Dr. Jex's
inspection.</p>
               <p>The doctor settled himself on a rung of the ladder, quite
willing to be met half-way. Professional inquiries began, when</p>
               <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <l part="N">“A deep sound struck like a rising knell.”</l>
               </lg>
               <p>“Good gracious!” exclaimed Mabel; “what is that?”</p>
               <p>Nanky Pal sprung up, with distended eyes, almost letting
the baby fall.</p>
               <p>Again,</p>
               <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <l part="N">“Nearer, clearer, deadlier than before.”</l>
               </lg>
               <p>“Sakes alive, Miss Mabel!” cried Nanky, “ole Mr. Simmons's
bull's done broke loose!”</p>
               <p>She was right. A moment more, and in rushed the splendid,
angry beast, bellowing, pawing the ground, shaking his
evil, lowered head as if the devil were contradicting him.</p>
               <p>Dr. Jex turned a scared face. My lord Bull caught sight
of the fluttering red rags, and charged the side of the house.
<pb n="115"/>
And I give you my word, the next instant the ladder was
knocked from under the doctor's feet, and he was clinging
frantically round the neck of Uncle Brimmer.</p>
               <p>Fearful moment!</p>
               <p>“Pull him in, Uncle Brimmer—pull him in!” shrieked
Mabel, dancing about.</p>
               <p>“I can't, honey—I can't,” gasped the choking giant; “I'm
<hi rend="italics">stuck.</hi>”</p>
               <p>“<hi rend="italics">Hold me</hi> UP!” cried the doctor. “SEND FOR <hi rend="italics">help!</hi>”</p>
               <p>Uncle Brimmer seized him by the arm-pits. The saddlebags
went clattering down, and about the head of Master Bull
a cloud of quinine, calomel, Dover's and divers other powders
and pills, broke in blinding confusion.</p>
               <p>“Aunt Patsey, go for Mr. Hucklestone <hi rend="italics">at once!</hi>” called
Mabel.</p>
               <p>Aunt Patsey looked cautiously out from the kitchen door.
“Yer don't ketch <hi rend="italics">me</hi> in de yard wid ole Simmons's bull,” she
said, with charming independence.</p>
               <p>“Then I shall send Nanky Pal.”</p>
               <p>“If Nanky Pal goes outen dat house I'll break every bone
in her body.”</p>
               <p>Then Mabel began to beg: “Aunt Patsey, let her go,
please. I'll give you a whole bagful of quilt pieces, and my
ruby rep polonaise that you begged me for yesterday.”</p>
               <p>Aunt Patsey's head came out a little farther. “An' what
else?”</p>
               <p>“And a ruffled pillow-sham,” said Mabel, almost in tears,
“and some white sugar, and I'll make you a hat—and that's
<hi rend="italics">all. Now.</hi>”</p>
               <pb n="116"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>“HOLD ME!” CRIED THE DOCTOR.</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>“I reckon cat's about as much as de chile is wuth,” said
the philosophic mother. “Let her go.”</p>
               <p>“Fly! fly!” cried Mabel.</p>
               <p>“I ain't skeered,” said Nanky. “I ain't dat sort. Mammy
<pb n="117"/>
ain't nuther. She wuz jes waitin' ter see how much you'd
give.”</p>
               <p>Nanky's bare legs scudded swiftly across the yard. The
bull took no notice of her. He was still stamping and bellowing
under that window. Uncle Brimmer and the doctor clung
together, and only a convulsive kick now and then testified to
the little man's agony.</p>
               <p>“Suppose Uncle Brimmer should let go?” I suggested, in
a hollow whisper.</p>
               <p>“Oh, hush!” cried Mabel. “The doctor's blood would be
on our heads.”</p>
               <p>“Or the bull's horns.”</p>
               <p>It was not far to the tobacco field, and in an incredibly
short time brother John came riding in, followed by half a
dozen stout negroes. With some delightful play that gave
one quite an idea of a Spanish bull-fight, his lordship was
captured, and our little doctor was assisted to the house.</p>
               <p>Gone was the glory of Dr. Trattles Jex. His coat was
torn, his knees grimy, his hands scratched, and he looked—
yes—as if he had been crying.</p>
               <p>“Can you ever forgive us?” said Mabel, piteously. She
hovered about him like a little mother. She made him drink
two glasses of wine; she mended his coat; she asked him if
he would not like to kiss the baby. And finally a wan smile
shone in the countenance of Dr. Jex. For me, I felt my face
purpling, and leaving him to Mabel, I fled with brother John
to the smoke-house, where we—roared.</p>
               <p>Uncle Brimmer got well, and went in to see the doctor.
He returned with a new cravat, a cane, and several smart
<pb n="118"/>
articles of attire, from which we inferred that, in those trying
moments when he supported the suspended doctor, that little
gentleman had offered many inducements for him to hold fast.
When questioned he responded chiefly with a cavernous and
mysterious smile, only saying:</p>
               <p>“Master Dr. Jex is a gentleman; starch in or starch out,
he's de gentleman straight.”</p>
               <p>And brother John, who is somewhat acquainted with slang,
said, with a great laugh, “Well, old man, you had a bully
chance to judge, so you must be right.”</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>REPAIRING DAMAGES.</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="119"/>
            <div type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
               <head>IN AUNT MELY'S CABIN.</head>
               <p>TWELVE o'clock and a starless night, the sky bending so
close to earth that one might fancy the very steam of the
world's passions condensed in the black clouds that rolled
heavily across it: no sound save the ceaseless, soft plashing of
the Mississippi waves. Suddenly a light wind rose: a piercing
shaft of moonlight struck through the clouds, falling on the black
letters over a beer-shop, and idealizing to purple and fine
linen some fluttering rags that hung from a dingy tenement-house.
The wind grew stronger; the clouds were blown into
wild shapes; the shaft of moonlight melted out into a broad
sheet of silver.</p>
               <p>A steep bluff overhung the river; sloping away from it
were the long, curving streets of a Southern city. A flight of
stone steps led from its highest point to a flat level, where new
workshops, ruins of burnt houses, and long cotton-sheds were
crowded together. It was a damp, dirty place. People called
it “Hell's Half-Acre,” and in the day it justified its name. But
the moon denies her gift of beauty to naught, and to-night this
most melancholy half-acre seemed to have a better right to be.
One noticed then twenty-four slim white pillars, Corinthian in
design, that fire had left standing from some stately public
building. The moonbeams broke into a thousand different
shapes in the little inlets where the river had pushed its way
<pb n="120"/>
in. The shapeless ruins were imposing in the half-light, and
heavy-scented flowers grew above them, mingling their odors
with the sweet, fresh smell of new timber at the planing-mill.
And the river—by daylight a vulgar, muddy stream—now
flowed in wide, mysterious grandeur, with distant gleams of
silver on its slow waves.</p>
               <p>Across the river, on the line of another State, was a little
town, so white and simple and still that it might have been
the home of moths and shadows. But as the moon's light
grew clearer a keen eye might have seen a man's form standing
at the water's edge, and a keen ear might have heard the
sound of a body falling into water. The river was narrow
at this point, and a man could easily swim across it, as this
one was doing. His body undulated under the waves like a
snake's. His head, barely visible above the water, was small,
and the wet hair clung closely about it like a cap. When he
had landed he stood for a moment shivering with cold and
casting quick, nervous glances around him, as if he had been
pursued. Then he walked irresolutely toward a cotton-shed,
and throwing himself on the ground, partly sheltered by a bale
of cotton, he fell asleep.</p>
               <p>The sun rose gloomily, and in its light the place that had
been almost poetic the night before showed all its squalid
ugliness. The street near the river, once a fine and fashionable
promenade, now seemed built of the very skeletons of
houses, so busily had decay been at work, and so little had
been done to stop its advance. The very flowers had lost
their purity, and hung heavy with little particles of cotton that
had blown upon them from the wagons continually passing,
<pb n="121"/>
and blackened in the coal-dust. It had caught in the delicate
lily-cups; it weighed down the roses; and in the broad foliage
of the arbor-vitae it had woven itself in and out until each
piece was like a fan. With the sun awoke noisy life. The
cotton-drays raced along Front Row, their black drivers standing
in them, hatless, shoeless, and ragged, urging on their
mules with discordant cries. The bleating of goats was heard
from the darkey settlement on the side of the cliff as queer
old aunties and uncles hobbled out to milk them. Down on
the flat the whir of machinery began; grimy men flung oaths
or rough jests at each other; flatboats appeared on the river;
and the air grew dense with smoke from the mills.</p>
               <p>Through all the man sleeping under the cotton-shed did
not stir, a deep exhaustion seemed to hold him hand and foot.
The sun found him out and dried his jeans clothing, warmed
his bare feet, and even tried to pierce through his cold body
to the dark, soggy earth on which it rested. It beamed on his
close hair until it blew from his face, light in color and curling
at the ends. The face was one common enough in a malarious
country—a yellow, lean, sharp face; besides this, it was a
young, weak, passionate face. The sunbeams were kind and
did not wake' him. The eyelids pressed close upon the eyes,
and the lashes lay motionless on the thin cheeks.</p>
               <p>After a time a negro passed near the cotton-shed—one of
the kind called “roustabouts” in that part of the country - 
people who live in a happy-go-lucky sort of way, dependent
from day to day on stray jobs or stray thefts, never losing flesh
or vivacity, never appearing otherwise than supremely content
with life and their lot. This one had his work for the day.
<pb n="122"/>
A bag was hung over his shoulder, and he was picking up the
loose cotton that had fallen from burst bales preparatory to
cleansing it for the gin. He saw the sleeping man, and became
instinct with the natural hostility that the negro seems
to have for the poor white.</p>
               <p>“Git up from dar, you lazy tramp!” he shouted, and, seeing
that the man did not stir, he picked up a bit of coal and threw
it with such precision as to hit the sleeper on his sunburnt neck.</p>
               <p>He started up and stared around him with a gleam of
ferocity in his eyes.</p>
               <p>The negro laughed loudly. “What gyardin did you come
outen?” he said. “You's enough to skeer de crows, you is.”</p>
               <p>The man took no notice of his gibes, but staggering, to his
feet walked slowly across the flat and up the stone steps.
Now and then he put his hand to his head in a confused way.
“I must git across the city,” he muttered: “there's good hiding
in some o' the slums 'round the bayou.”</p>
               <p>He turned up Promenade Street, walking with slow, dragging
steps. “Seems to me I'm powerful weak,” he muttered.
“Has it been longer'n a day sence I tuk my food?”</p>
               <p>“Chickee! chick! chick! chick!”</p>
               <p>He stopped at the sweet sound of a child's voice, and looking
over a broken gate saw a little blue-eyed girl feeding
chickens by the wood-pile in the yard.</p>
               <p>“Sissy, can you give me a glass of buttermilk?”</p>
               <p>“Mamma! mamma!” called the child, “here's a man wants
some buttermilk.”</p>
               <p>“He will have to wait for it,” answered a voice from the
house: “the churn won't be ready for half an hour.”</p>
               <pb n="123"/>
               <p>“Come in,” said the little maid, running to the gate and
holding it open. “You can wait a while, can't you? Here's a
seat on the wood-pile.”</p>
               <p>He followed her like one in a dream.</p>
               <p>She stood up before him, a straight, sweet shape, and
began to talk. “You don't look very nice,” said she, her eyes
wandering over his torn, soiled garments, with bits of coal and
dirt falling away from the side that had lain next to the earth;
“but I s'pose you were a soldier.”</p>
               <p>“No, little girl; I never wuz a soldier.”</p>
               <p>“I'm s'prised to hear that. My papa was a colonel, and
nearly all the men that come here and—and—ask for things,
you know, b'longed to some big general's army—Lee's or
Forrest's or Hood's. I can't remember all the names.”</p>
               <p>He said nothing, and little Miss Delicacy feared she had
hurt his feelings. “Do you like sugar-cakes?” she said,
soothingly.</p>
               <p>He nodded his head.</p>
               <p>“The trouble is”—she drew nearer and lowered her voice
confidentially—“there are so many boys about, and they are
<hi rend="italics">dreadful</hi> fellows for sugar-cakes. They hardly <hi rend="italics">ever</hi> leave any
till next day. But I'll see about it.”</p>
               <p>She disappeared behind the honeysuckle that hung over
the porch, but she did not come back. The sound of tempestuous
sobbing came from within, and it was plain she had
either been disappointed of the sugar-cakes or, as was more
likely, forbidden a social chat with a tramp.</p>
               <p>The man took no heed of her absence. He lifted his eyes
and looked across the river to Hopefield, the little town so
<pb n="124"/>
white and still. But to him it seemed to run with blood
and ring with sound. His teeth clinched together; his eyes
glowed in his set face like eyes in discolored marble. Close
by the river-bank was his home, a log-house, weather-boarded,
that he had built himself. He could see the zigzag line of the
fence and the hollyhocks growing by the window. He had
planted them there two years ago, when he married little Betty
Hill and brought her home. What those years had been to
him he and God knew. He was poor, but Betty had made
him love his daily work. He was ignorant, but Betty had
been his teacher. He was rough, but Betty was fine. That
for which men have</p>
               <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <l part="N">“Ransacked the ages, spoiled the climes,”</l>
               </lg>
               <p>had come to him pressed down and running over. And
now —</p>
               <p>Wrenching his mind from that horrible “now,” he threw
back his thoughts to the early days of his love and hers:
“She allays belonged ter me. I learnt her ter swim an' ter
fish an' ter row. We gethered hick'ry-nuts in th' same basket,
an' I marked every sweet-gum tree she wanted, so 't not a boy
in Hopefield dared ter tech one of 'em. I cut her name in my
arm; and once I took a stran' of her long black hair and
sewed it over my heart s deep that the blood run every time
I drawed the needle out. Little Betty! Little Betty! Wuz
ther' ever a time I didn't love her? I toted her in my arms
when she wuz a teenchy baby, an' I watched her year by year
growin' purtier, an' straighter 'n a saplin' in the woods. She
never growed very tall; on'y as high as my heart, she said.
<pb n="125"/>
She had sech a purty way of sayin' things!—nimble with her
tongue as she wuz with her feet in a reel.” His lips parted
with something like a smile.</p>
               <p>“Here is the buttermilk,” said the child's voice, “and the
sugar-cakes too; but I had to cry for them.”</p>
               <p>He started to his feet, and, taking the bowl, drank the milk
thirstily, a faint color coming under his brown skin. But he
never took his eyes from the Hopefield shore; and as he
drained the last drop he saw three men walking rapidly down
toward the river. His heart gave a wild leap: the bowl dropped
from his hands. “They're on my track,” he said, hoarsely.</p>
               <p>No use now to hurry across the city to hide in the slums:
it was too late for that plan. In his pressing need a sudden
thought came to him of an old black woman who lived near.
She had belonged to a minister's family in Hopefield. He
had known her all his life; she had made a pet of him, and
would befriend him now.</p>
               <p>He walked quickly out of the yard toward the hovel that
Aunt Mely called home. It was a chance whether he ever
reached it, for he stopped at the steepest height of the bluff,
and for one mad moment thought how easy it would be to
crush out fear, remorse, agony, life, in one short, sharp point of
time. But he drew back and walked on with long, quick steps.</p>
               <p>Aunt Mely's house was poised on the side of the bluff like
a rocking-stone. Back of it was a struggling garden, protected
from the goats by a queer sort of fence made of all the refuse
stuff Aunt Mely could find—broad planks and narrow planks,
old fence-rails, sticks of wood and brush-heaps. Of the house
itself you could not say that one part was worse than another.
<pb n="126"/>
It seemed to hang together by attenuated threads. Samson
in his days of bibs and long-gowns could have brought it
about his ears with a vigorous infantine kick. The chimney
was remarkable. It had been daubed with mud and stuck
with clay, and on the outside Aunt Mely had nailed a shining
sheet of tin.</p>
               <p>The old woman was bustling about in-doors when a shadow
came between her and the sun. She looked up and saw a
man's form in the door- way: “Lor' bless my soul, Phil Vickers!
is dat you? What's de matter wid you?”</p>
               <p>“I'm in great trouble, Aunt Mely. I want you to help me
—hide me.”</p>
               <p>“Hide you? Why, what hev you been a-doin'?”</p>
               <p>He pushed his way beside her into the room.</p>
               <p>She followed him and shut the door. “What have you
done, boy?” she repeated.</p>
               <p>“I've killed Tom Jack, if you must know.”</p>
               <p>“Killed Tom Jack! Phil Vickers, you God-forsaken creetur'!
what did you do dat for?”</p>
               <p>His eyes sparkled; he forgot his terror; his voice rose to
a shrill key and shook in speaking: “Aunt Mely, tell me this:
have I been a good husband to Betty Hill?”</p>
               <p>“Yes, you have, Phil: come what may, I'll always b'ar witness
to dat.”</p>
               <p>“I've loved her, Aunt Mely, and <hi rend="italics">you</hi> know it. She lay on
my heart day an' night. I thought she wuz a true wife to me.”</p>
               <p>“So she wuz, Phil—so she wuz. Many an' many's de time
she said ter me, ‘My Phil's de sweetest, kindest boy dat ever
lived.’ ”</p>
               <pb n="127"/>
               <p>He broke into a howl of anguish: “Now you hear what
that counts up ten I got home Monday night from a day's
huntin': I had a deer on my shoulder. It wuz the day befo'
Moddy-Gras, you know; we wuz comin' across next day to see
the sights. I had been whistlin' loud, but I stopped when I
got in hollerin' reach o' the house, and slipped to the winder
to see what Little Betty wuz doin'. An' thar, sho' as thar's a
livin' God, standin' by my wife, his arm round her waist, wuz a
man! Things swum befo' my eyes for a minnit; then the
pine-knots blazed up an' I saw Tom Jack's face. I watched
'em. They were talkin' an' laughin' quite frien'ly , Tom struttin'
about like a dancin'-jack. Then he comes up to her
again, pulls at her dress an' kisses her on the bare neck, she
a-laughin' an' a-strugglin' with him, as she'd done with me a
thousan' times. I lifted my rifle, thankin' God there wuz a
load in it, an' shot. I'd as lief ha' hit 'em both; but on'y Tom
Jack dropped, and Little Betty stood screamin' over him an'
wringin' her han's. I flung down my rifle an' run to the
woods. I wuz thar all that night an' yesterday, walkin', walkin',
walkin', till another night come; an' I swum the river befo'
sun-up this mornin'.”</p>
               <p>“God forgive you, Phil! God forgive you fo' yer sin!”</p>
               <p>“Sin, is it?—sin to shoot a man who wants to reap a crop
I've fenced in? Don't talk to me about sin, old Mely Mitchell!”</p>
               <p>“Thar! thar! poor boy! Don't look at me so wild! What
kin I do for you, honey?”</p>
               <p>“Whatever you do must be done soon,” he said, sullenly.
“I saw some men leave Hopefield as I started here: they must
be nearly across.”</p>
               <pb n="128"/>
               <p>“I ain't got a place on de yearth to hide you, Phil, 'thouten
you kin git in de chimley: they'll never think o' lookin' dar.
You kin keep in all day, and steal off when night comes. I
think you'd better take ter de woods ag'in.”</p>
               <p>“I won't do that—not unless I want ter go blind crazy.”</p>
               <p>“See 'f you kin crawl in de chimley. Dar ain't been no
fire in it for a month o' Sundays. It smokes so bad I can't
cook nothin'. You kin stan' up, an' I'll put a cheer in de
fireplace, and pile it up wid my ole clo'es, ter hide yer legs.”</p>
               <p>“Look out, Aunt Mely, an' see 'f they're comin'.”</p>
               <p>She opened .the door cautiously: “I see three men at de
landin', Phil, but dey ain't a-comin' dis way. Dey's struck
across Front Row.”</p>
               <p>“They're off my track. They'll look for me in the very
slums I meant to hide in.”</p>
               <p>“For all dat, dis ain't a safe place fo' you, Phil.”</p>
               <p>“Do you want to turn me out of your house?”</p>
               <p>“God forbid, you po' boy! Stay and git what comfort you
kin. Stretch yerself out on dat bed afar and try ter rest. I'll
watch out fo' you.”</p>
               <p>He threw himself down and tried to sleep, but in vain.
His blood began to burn and race in his veins; pain struck
at him with a thousand whips. He held his hands over his
mouth to keep himself from screaming aloud.</p>
               <p>Toward noon he heard, as from some far-off place, Aunt
Mely's voice: “Phil, honey, dey're comin' back.”</p>
               <p>He sprung up and thrust his head recklessly out of the
door.</p>
               <p>“Git back, Phil!” said the old woman, sharply. “I kin tell
<pb n="129"/>
you all afar is to tell. Dey's stoppin' now at a house on Promenade
Street. Dey's drawin' water at de well by de wood-pile,
an' a little gal is talkin' to dem.”</p>
               <p>“She gave me some buttermilk this mornin': she saw the
way I come. I'm a lost man!”</p>
               <p>“No, you ain't. You jes git right in de chimley, an' I'll
deal wid 'em if dey come r'arin' roun' dis house.”</p>
               <p>By the time he was well in the hiding-place the men had
turned toward the negro quarter. Aunt Mely sat down and
went to work quietly on a patchwork quilt, ready to receive
them with proper surprise and dignity. But when they came
the work fell from her hands, her skin turned ashen-gray, she
shook in every limb; for Tom Jack was the first man to burst
into the room—Tom Jack, strong in virile life, angry-eyed, a
long knife stuck in his belt.</p>
               <p>Aunt Mely was a shrewd old soul; she recovered herself
quickly, and said nothing. “Phil sartinly shot somebody,” she
thought, “an' I'll jes hol' my tongue till I see how things is
gwine ter turn out.”</p>
               <p>“Where is Phil Vickers?” said Tom, in a voice husky with
passion.</p>
               <p>“Phil Vickers? Why, I ain't seed de boy sence I went
over to his house 'bout a week back to git a settin' of eggs
Miss Betty 'd been savin' up for me.”</p>
               <p>“Now, come, Aunt Mely,” said one of the party,
good-humoredly, “you needn't lie. Little Sally Polk saw him come
right in yer do'. We left a p'liceman huntin' him in the city,
an' wuz on our way back to Hopefield when the child told us
whar he were.”</p>
               <pb n="130"/>
               <p>“O my soul! What's poor Phil done dat you're all a-huntin'
him like a pack o' houn's?”</p>
               <p>“Phil's had a little shootin' affair,” said the good-natured
man.</p>
               <p>“Who'd he shoot?”</p>
               <p>“Who'd he shoot?” cried Tom Jack. “The sweetest, brightest
creetur' the Lord ever made—my sister, Nancy Jack.”</p>
               <p>In the dreadful silence that followed a convulsive, gasping
sound was heard. The next moment Phil Vickers sprung out,
his hair and clothes covered with mould, like a spectre from
the grave. “Is this true, boys? Did I kill Nancy Jack?” he
said, in a harsh, hollow voice.</p>
               <p>Jack sprung at him, his knife flashing in the air. But he
was caught and held back by one of the men with him:
“Softly, Tom, softly! Let Phil have fair play.”</p>
               <p>“Fair play for a man who shot down my sister in cold blood?”</p>
               <p>“As God sees me, Tom, I thought it wuz you kissin' Little
Betty.”</p>
               <p>“That's an argyment, Tom,” said the third man, who had
a long, sad face, and who lingered over his words as if he were
patting them—“that's an argyment as'll go down with the
jury. It wuz night; you an' Nancy are alike in the face;
you've got no whiskers, you know, Tom. How wuz Phil to
know that it wuz Nancy a-showin' herself off to Little Betty,
dressed up in your clo'es for a Moddy-Gras frolic?”</p>
               <p>As he heard a curious change came over Phil. His knees
began to shake pitiably, his body to collapse. He held out his
<pb n="131"/>
hand as if trying to steady himself, and, grasping only air, fell
slowly to the floor, saying, in a stifled voice, “Let Tom kill
me: I ain't fit to live.”</p>
               <p>“The hangman will do it for me,” said Tom, with a snarl.</p>
               <p>“Is de po' gal dead?” said Aunt Mely.</p>
               <p>“No, she ain't dead—she ain't deed <hi rend="italics">yit</hi>, ” rejoined the sad-
faced man. “We couldn't git a doctor yisterday, de town wuz
in such a swivel. But Dr. Taylor he come over las' night, an'
is thar now. He ain't foun' de bullet. He says Nancy's in a
cosmotose state.”</p>
               <p>Now, while this talk was going on some one else was
crossing the river from Hopefield - a sturdy little woman with
black hair and eyes. She was seated in the exact centre of a
knife-bottomed boat that cut through the water fast as a bird
flies. With her single oar flashing into the water on either
side she made quick time across the Mississippi; and now she
came flying into Aunt Mely's cabin, a little vehement whirlwind
of a creature, with a voice as high and sweet as a
birdnote.</p>
               <p>“Oh! thank goodness! you are all here!” she cried, brokenly.
Then she caught Tom Jack's hand: “Oh, Tom, she is
saved! The doctor has found the bullet. He says she is all
right now—will need nothing but good nursing; an' that, you
know, she'll have. I won't leave her night nor day till she's
on her feet;” and Little Betty burst into tears, in which,
perhaps, all wanted to join.</p>
               <p>“How'd you come here, chile?” said Aunt Mely.</p>
               <p>“I wuz so anxious about Nancy that I couldn't think of
<pb n="132"/>
anything else till the doctor had spoke. Then my mind
mistrusted me about Tom. I asked where he wuz, an' they told
me he had taken his bowie-knife an' gone over to the city. I
wuz afeard he had got on Phil's track. I jumped in the canoe
and rushed over just blindly. But the first man I met on the
Flat said he'd seen some Hopefield men go into Aunt Mely's
cabin. So I came right here. Thank God for it! thank God
for it!”</p>
               <p>“It's a good thing for Phil that Nancy 'll git well,” remarked
the sad man, slowly tearing off a strip of tobacco from a
ragged roll; “the law can't do nothin' to him now, 'thouten it
shets him up a while for 'sault an' battery.”</p>
               <p>“His account with me ain't settled yet,” said Tom Jack,
ominously. “Look to yourself, Phil Vickers! Blood's got to pay
for blood!”</p>
               <p>“Oh, Tom! Tom!” cried Little Betty, the tears streaming
down her face, “forgive us. We didn't mean to do you any
harm. Phil would ha' died a thousand deaths befo' he'd ha'
harmed a hair of Nancy's head. Tom, no wife nor child nor
sister will ever pray for you and bless you as I will if you'll
just shake hands friendly and say, ‘Phil, I pardon you.’ Nancy
would do it; I know she would. Oh, what can I say to you?
I'll go on my knees to you, Tom.”</p>
               <p>She fell on her knees and lifted her warm, wet, beautiful
eyes to Tom's face.</p>
               <p>“Get up, child,” he said, hoarsely. “I'll let him go, an'
when Nancy's on her legs ag'in I'll shake hands.”</p>
               <p>He turned abruptly and left the house.</p>
               <pb n="133"/>
               <p>Phil's head fell on his breast: “You'd better have let him
kill me, Little Betty. I ain't fit to be the husband of such as
you.”</p>
               <p>But Little Betty drew the tired head to her tender heart
and looked defiantly round upon the others, as if throwing all
the splendor of her faithful love between Phil and any look of
contempt or blame.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="134"/>
            <div type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
               <head>THE CASE OF ELIZA BLEYLOCK.</head>
               <p>CAPTAIN JAMES PETERS, riding home from a raid
into the moonshine counties, stopped at Jared's store and
asked for a drink. A jug was taken from the shelf, and a
finger's-length of clear yellow whiskey poured out.</p>
               <p>“No moonshine in this sto', you see, captain,” remarked
Mr. Jared.</p>
               <p>“Humph!” and the captain's keen eyes glanced toward the
loungers in and about the store. “Reckon if I took a notion
I could unearth some moonshine, an' spot some moonshiners
not fur off.”</p>
               <p>“Captain, you mustn't be so suspicious.”</p>
               <p>“Suspicious? Reckon I shouldn't earn my pay 'f I wuzn't.
S'picion 's mighty good thing for a man-hunter. My game's
shy. But I've my eye on mo' than knows of me. Some folks
'll find thar b'ilers smashed when they dunno I'm aroun'.”</p>
               <p>Silence. Some of the young men shrugged their shoulders.
One drawled out at last that he “didn't know as anybody
keered three-jumps of a louse fur Jim Peters or his
threatenin's.”</p>
               <p>“Come, come,” said a cunning-looking old man; “don't
let's have no words. We're all peaceful folks, captain, in this
here settlement—powerful peaceful. Ter be sho', we don't like
<pb n="135"/>
nobody a-foolin' round our business. We come from Car'liny
more'n a hundred ye'rs ago, an' here we've lived peaceful an'
orderly ever sence—a-livin' an' a-dyin' an' a-marryin' an'
a-breedin'—”</p>
               <p>“An' a-learnin' th' use of th' shot-gun,” interposed Dick
Oscar, quietly.</p>
               <p>“I'm a Tennessee man myself,” said Captain Peters, “an'
I ruther think I know how t' use a shot-gun. An' I've got a
rifle—that's a sixteen-shooter.”</p>
               <p>There was a general movement of interest.</p>
               <p>“Let's have a look at it, captain.”</p>
               <p>“It don't go out o' my hand. But you can look much 's
you please. Ain't she a beauty, now?”</p>
               <p>They crowded around, patting and praising the gun as if
it were human. And there was a general murmur of assent
when old man Welch exclaimed, “Ain't it a pity, boys, ter see
sech a rifle as that thronged away on a damned Gov'ment
officer?”</p>
               <p>Captain Peters only laughed. He was very good-humored,
this mountain terror, except when, as they would say, his blood
was up. Then it was as safe to meet a starving tiger.</p>
               <p>“Seems to me 's if the captain has somethin' on his mind,”
remarked Mrs. Riggs that same evening.</p>
               <p>The Riggses lived at Bloomington, and the captain and his
family were paying them a visit, preparatory to settling in the
same place. Mrs. Riggs was a bustling young woman, “born
in quite another part of the State,” as she would tell you, with
an air; “no mopin' mountain blood in me.” She was the third
wife of her husband—a sanctimonious old chap, with his long
<pb n="136"/>
white beard, the ends of which he used to assist meditation,
as a cow chews its cud.</p>
               <p>“James Riggs,” his wife had said when he courted her,
“it's my opinion you <hi rend="italics">talked</hi> them two previous women to
death; but if you get me, mark one thing—you'll get your
match.” And he did.</p>
               <p>The Riggses were extremely sensible of the honor of having
Captain Peters in their house. Dom Pedro and Cetywayo
rolled into one could not have been watched with more solicitude.
Had not his name been in every paper in the Union,
and his portrait in a New York journal? That the eyes of the
nation were fixed upon him Peters himself did not doubt; and
it was asserted through the country that he was in close
correspondence with the President.</p>
               <p>“Jim's been a-broodin',” said Mrs. Peters—a moon-faced
woman with dull blue eyes—“ever sence he went inter this
business. I've wished time 'n' ag'in he'd stuck to blacksmithin',
for I've suffered a thousan' deaths with him off a-hangarin'<ref n="1" target="note1">*</ref>
over the mountains.”</p>
               <p>“He wuz called of the Lord,” said Mr. Riggs, “and his
hand must not be stayed. The inikity of man <hi rend="italics">shell</hi> be put
down in the land.”</p>
               <p>“Ye—es,” drawled the captain, “I'm a-goin' to bust up the
'stillin' business in Tennessee. But I'm plagued about them
Bleylock boys. I can't ketch 'em nohow.”</p>
               <p>A knock at the door, and a young fellow came in and shook
hands eagerly with the captain. His name was Maddox.</p>
               <note n="1" type="footnote" place="foot" anchored="true" target="ref1">*Wandering.</note>
               <pb n="137"/>
               <p>Captain Peters had picked him up in Nashville, and
employed him “on trial.”</p>
               <p>“I wuz jest a-speakin' of the Bleylocks,” he said. “I'm
pretty sure they've got a still somewhar. They look me in
the eye too powerful innocent to be all right. Now, I've got a
notion—” Maddox drew himself up, alert, watchful as a listening
sentinel. “What can't be done one way must be done another,”
said Captain Peters, slowly.</p>
               <p>“And rightly you speak,” said Mr. Riggs, as he spat out
his beard; “it's the Lord's work, an' be done it must, with
every wepping known to man.”</p>
               <p>“I knew it!—I knew it, captain!” cried Mrs. Riggs. “I
knew you had somethin' on your mind. You're a-schemin'
somethin' great. I see it in your eye.”</p>
               <p>It remained in the captain's eye, as far as Mrs. Riggs was
concerned, for the captain took Mr. Maddox out-of-doors, where
they talked in whispers, and Mrs. Riggs berated her lord for
having driven them away with his tongue.</p>
               <p>A few days later a peddler stopped at Bleylock's and asked
for a drink of water. Old Mother Bleylock sent Eliza to the
spring for a fresh bucketful; and the peddler, after refreshing
himself, opened his pack.</p>
               <p>“ 'Pears 's if we oughtn't ter trouble you,” she said, “ 'cause
we can't buy a pin's wuth.”</p>
               <p>“Jest for the pleasure, ma'am,” said the gallant peddler.</p>
               <p>The pack was opened, and three pairs of eyes grew big
with delight.</p>
               <p>“ 'F you'll wait till par comes I'll make him buy me that
collar,” said Janey, the younger of the Bleylock girls.</p>
               <pb n="138"/>
               <p>“P'raps Dick Oscar 'd buy you a present 'f he wuz here,
suggested Eliza.</p>
               <p>“If 'tain't makin' too free, I'd like to say I admire Dick
Oscar's taste,” said the peddler, with an admiring glance.</p>
               <p>Janey responded with, “Oh! you hush!” and a toss of her
head; and old Mother Bleylock said, “The boys most generully
always paid Janey a good deal 'f attention.”</p>
               <p>She possessed a bold prettiness, this mountain pink.
Brown-skinned, black-eyed, red-lipped, and a way of dropping
her head on her swelling neck, and looking mutiny from under
her heavy brows. Eliza was a thin slip of a girl, with a demure
but vacant look in her blue eyes, and a shy, nervous manner.</p>
               <p>“I'll tell you the truth, ma'am,” remarked the peddler to
the mother: “you could take these girls o' yours to Nashville,
an' people in th' streets would follow them for their good looks.
An' that's Heaven's own truth. All yo' family, these two?”</p>
               <p>“Lor! no; I've got three boys.”</p>
               <p>“All at home farmin', I s'pose?”</p>
               <p>“Yaas.”</p>
               <p>“Long road to take their crops to market.”</p>
               <p>“I ain't never heerd no complaint.”</p>
               <p>“Now, 'bout these goods o' mine,” said the peddler; “ 'f you
could put me up for a few days, we might make a trade. I'm
's tired 's a lame horse, and wouldn't want nothin' better'n to
rest right here.”</p>
               <p>“I'd like nothin' better'n to take you. But th' ain't no use
sayin' a word till par gits home. He ain't no hand fur
strangers.”</p>
               <pb n="139"/>
               <p>“Well, I won't be a stranger longer'n I can help,” said the
agreeable peddler. “My name's Pond—Marcus Pond - Nashville
boy; but a rollin' stone, you know. I've peddled books
an' sewin'-machines, an' no end of a lot of traps ginerally.
Fond o' travel, you see; but jest 's steady as old Time. Never
drink when I travel; promised my mother I wouldn't.”</p>
               <p>“ 'Tis a good thing,” said Mother Bleylock, with energy. “I
do despise to see a fuddled man. Whiskey ain't fit fur nothin'
but ter fatten hogs on.”</p>
               <p>Father Bleylock came home, and, beyond a stare and a
silent nod, took little notice of the peddler. He was a tall
man, thin, taciturn, and yellow, and with a neck so small that
his head presented the appearance of being stuck on with a
pin.</p>
               <p>He lighted his pipe, and after a soothing interval of smoking,
“Peddler 'd like to stop over a period,” said his wife.</p>
               <p>Puff, puff. “Don't see no objection.” Puff, puff.</p>
               <p>And a gentle hilarity agitated the bosoms that yearned
over the peddler's pack.</p>
               <p>Mr. Pond, as he had promised, soon ceased to be a stranger.
The old man discoursed on the grievances of taxes, and
the old woman, after the manner of mothers, talked about her
daughters.</p>
               <p>“My gals is eddicated,” she would say—“been over t'
Cookville months an' months a-schoolin'. But, lor! thar's some folks
you can't weed the badness out'n, an' Janey's a spitfire, she is.
Seems 's if Dick Oscar wants to have her, but he acts kinder
curious about it—blow hot, blow cold. Dunno. Now, Lizy is
different. Can't tell why, less'n 'tis that I went to camp-meetin'
<pb n="140"/>
an' perfessed a while befo' she wuz born. Somehow she's
always been delicater an' quieter like 'n any of my childern.”</p>
               <p>The Bleylock boys, easy, rollicking fellows, treated the
peddler very much as if he had been a harmless though
unnecessary cat about the house, and were surprised when Dick Oscar,
dropping in one evening, informed them that they were all a
pack of fools for “takin' in a stranger so free and easy.”</p>
               <p>“Why, I ain't paid no more attention to th' man 'n if he'd
a-been a preacher,” said Sam Bleylock; “seems 's if th' ain't no
harm t' him.”</p>
               <p>“He's a very God-fearin' man,” said Eliza, softly, “an' a
powerful reader o' the Bible.”</p>
               <p>“ 'F you'll take <hi rend="italics">my</hi> say so, you'll git quit of him,” said Dick
Oscar.</p>
               <p>“He's got such beautiful taste!” said Mother Bleylock.
“It's as good 's goin' to th' city to look at his things.”</p>
               <p>“I see he's been a-dressin' you up,” said Oscar, with a sneer
at the new ribbons the girls wore round their necks.</p>
               <p>Janey sprung up. Her face reddened. In an instant she
had torn off the ribbon and stamped her foot on it. “That's
how much I care for him an' his ribbins!” she cried.</p>
               <p>“Don't fly quite off the handle,” said Mr. Oscar, coolly.
Evidently he shared her mother's opinion that Miss Janey was
a spitfire.</p>
               <p>Poor Janey! She had hoped to please her lover by her
scorn of the peddler's gift, but she was coming to the conclusion
that he was a hard man to please. She was a passionate
young animal, and she had thrown herself into his arms with
a readiness that robbed herself of her graces. He liked to
<pb n="141"/>
sting and stroke her alternately, and was about as unsatisfactory
a lover as Janey could have found on the Cumberland.
But she liked him, saw with his eyes, thought with his
thoughts. Naturally she turned against the peddler, and from
this time set herself to watch him.</p>
               <p>That harmless young man in the mean time was doing
what he could. He wandered about the country selling such
little things as the people could buy, “pumping” the Bleylock
boys, and making love to the Bleylock girls. The pumping
process was rewarded with about as much success as would
attend fishing for a soul through the eye of a skeleton. In
the love-making there was more hope.</p>
               <p>Janey was accessible to flattery, and encouraged him with
little looks of fire. But there was something in her eyes he
did not trust, and he was a wary man, the peddler. Besides,
she slapped his face when he tried to kiss her. But he soon
grew to believe that Eliza—simple, unsuspicious, serious—
would be as clay in his hands.</p>
               <p>Chance favored Miss Janey. She was bathing, one warm
day, in the creek that ran out from the spring, when she saw
Eliza and the peddler coming, like Jack and Jill, to fetch a
pail of water. Being naked, Janey could not get away; but
she slid along to a cool inlet overhung with tree branches,
and so hidden, waited for them to do their errand. Of course
they stopped to talk.</p>
               <p>“That pink ribbon becomes your black hair mightily,” said
the peddler.</p>
               <p>Eliza blushed. “We're just country girls, you know, Mr.
Pond; we don't have many pretty things. Seems 's if the
<pb n="142"/>
boys don't have any money left after buyin' the sugar an flour an'
molasses an' things.”</p>
               <p>“Meat, I s'pose?” said the practical peddler.</p>
               <p>“No; we raise our own meat. Par has a powerful lot o' hogs.”</p>
               <p>“So!”</p>
               <p>“But I expect you don't take much interest in country life,
Mr. Pond?”</p>
               <p>“Why, my dear”—and Mr. Pond slipped his arm around
Eliza—“I'd like the best in the world to settle down in a
country just like this. A fellow gets tired trampin' around.
But I'd want two things to make me happy.”</p>
               <p>Eliza looked at him with happy confidence.</p>
               <p>“First, a little wife 'at wuz gentle in her ways, an' a good,
religious girl, an' one with black hair, to set off the pink ribbons
I'd buy for her, an' a fleet foot, and a red mouth.”</p>
               <p>Here Mr. Pond came to a full stop with a kiss.</p>
               <p>“And the other thing?” with a bright blush.</p>
               <p>The peddler grew practical again. “Well, it's nothin' more'n
some way to make a livin'. Now, say I married a sweet girl
up the Cumberland, and made a little crop. It's too far to git
it to market. I <hi rend="italics">might</hi> turn it into whiskey, but lately Gov'ment's
turned meddler, an' is a-breakin' stills right an' left
through the country.”</p>
               <p>“They do hide 'em sometimes,” said Eliza, in a half-whisper,
“so's a blood-hound could hardly scent 'em. An' a very good
business it is, an' the hogs live on the mash.”</p>
               <p>“Do you know of any such stills, my little darlin'?”</p>
               <p>But she drew back a little. “Ef I do know of any,” she
said, “I've promised not to tell of 'em.”</p>
               <pb n="143"/>
               <p>“Not to the man as is goin' to be your husband?”</p>
               <p>“Not to him until he <hi rend="italics">is</hi> my husband.” And blushing, but
resolute, Eliza filled her pail and started for the house.</p>
               <p>Under the water Janey clinched her hands. “Dick was
right,” she thought; “and I see his game. He's a spy, and
Eliza's a fool.”</p>
               <p>She knew that she had heard enough to justify her lover
in his suspicions, enough to put them all on their guard. A
passionate exultation fired her blood as she thought of the
service she should render Dick Oscar, his praise, the reward
of his rude kisses.</p>
               <p>But, alas for Janey! something had ruffled her sweetheart's
temper when next they met. Before she could approach the
subject of which she was full stinging words had passed
between them.</p>
               <p>“Dick,” said Janey, hoarsely, “d'ye mean that you're goin'
back from your word—that you ain't agoin' to marry me?”</p>
               <p>“Marry hell!” said Mr. Oscar. And he walked off.</p>
               <p/>
               <p>“I want to speak t' you,” said Janey that night to the
peddler. “Can you git up in th' morning befo' th' folks is
stirrin'?”</p>
               <p>“Of course I can, when it's to meet a gal like you.”</p>
               <p>Privately he wondered at her pallor and lurid eyes.</p>
               <p>Morning came. As the stars were drowsily getting out
of the sun's way Janey and the peddler met by the spring.</p>
               <p>“You needn't lie to me,” said she, harshly. “I've found
you out. You're up the Cumberland spyin' for wild-cat stills.
I'll take you to one.”</p>
               <pb n="144"/>
               <p>“But, my dear, is this a trap? I'm nothin' but a poor
harmless peddler.”</p>
               <p>“Come, then, my harmless peddler,” said the girl, with a
sneer, “an' I'll show you somethin' t' make your mouth water.”</p>
               <p>She struck through the woods, and he followed, alternately
blessing and wondering at his luck. What thread led her he
knew not. Fallen logs lay in the way, thickets opposed,
foliage dense as the massed green in Dewing's “Morning”
hid all signs of path, but on she went, easily, as if she were
illustrating the first line of prepositions in Lindley—above,
around, amidst, athwart obstacles of every kind. And finally,
girdled and guarded by trees and rocks, was the hidden still,
where the “dull, cold ear of”—corn was changed into the
flowing moonshine that maketh glad the heart of man.</p>
               <p>The peddler could hardly keep back a shout. He had
won his spurs. It was a much larger concern than he had
expected. Some hogs were rooting about the sodden earth.
The monotonous dripping of water mingled with the grunts
of these poetic animals.</p>
               <p>Janey leaned against a rock, breathing heavily. The peddler
thought he would about as soon touch a wild-cat as to speak to
her. Nevertheless he did.</p>
               <p>“B'long t' your folks?” he said.</p>
               <p>“ 'T b'longs to Dick Oscar, an' you know it!” said the girl,
fiercely. “Now I'm goin' back home.”</p>
               <p>“You don't know of any more such,” said the insatiate
peddler, “lyin' 'round loose up here?—pearls among swine,
so to speak.”</p>
               <p>“I've done enough. An', look here, keep your tongue
<pb n="145"/>
                  <figure>
                     <p>“THE PEDDLER COULD HARDLY KEEP BACK A SHOUT.”</p>
                  </figure>
between yo' teeth. Tell that <hi rend="italics">I</hi> fetched you here, an' you won't
see many more sun-ups with them spyin' eyes.”</p>
               <p>Mr. Pond was a tolerable woodsman, and he led Captain
Peters and his scouts to the mountain-still without trouble.
They were all there—the Bleylock boys, the father, and young
<pb n="146"/>
Oscar. They were hard at work, and, surprised, were handcuffed
without the firing of a gun.</p>
               <p>Who so crestfallen as the toiling, moiling moonshiners?
Who so jubilant as the long-whiskered captain? He would
have sung a paean had he known how. As it was, he chewed
a great deal of tobacco, and unbuttoned his flannel shirt for
expansion.</p>
               <p>The prisoners were halted at the Bleylock cabin for baggage
and good-byes. They were to be taken to the penitentiary,
and would need a change of socks.</p>
               <p>Mrs. Bleylock and Eliza wept and moaned their fate;
but Janey was still, brown lids veiling the dull fire of her eyes.</p>
               <p>“Janey, my girl,” said Oscar, drawing her apart, “I spoke
up rough to you t' other day. But don't you mind it. 'Twarn't
nuthin' but jealousy.”</p>
               <p>Her eyes softened. Mountain pinks, as well as some fine
ladies, consider jealousy as a tribute to their charms.</p>
               <p>“Perhaps I'll never come back,” said he.</p>
               <p>She seized him by the arm.</p>
               <p>“Dick, what can they do t' you?”</p>
               <p>“Dunno. Most likely I'll kill somebody tryin' to git away,
and be strung.”</p>
               <p>Janey burst into tears.</p>
               <p>“Shouldn't wonder 'f you married one o' the Jareds,” he
said, piling on the gloom.</p>
               <p>“Dick Oscar, I promised to marry <hi rend="italics">you</hi>, an' <hi rend="italics">I</hi> don't go back
from my word.”</p>
               <p>“No, an' I don't!” cried Dick. “There ain't as pretty a
<pb n="147"/>
shaped girl as you on the Cumberland; an' if ever I do git
back—”</p>
               <p>He whispered the rest in Janey's ear, and she clung to
him, blushing a deep, deep rose.</p>
               <p/>
               <p>“ 'S jest one thing I want to know,” said old Bleylock, as
they tramped to Nashville: “how 'd you find us?”</p>
               <p>The captain laughed.</p>
               <p>“Been entertainin' a peddler, haven't you? Which one o'
your gals 'd he make up to?”</p>
               <p>Father and brothers swore. Dick Oscar nodded to his
discernment, with human triumph.</p>
               <p>A few days later a young girl walked into Nashville who
had never been in a city before. She asked but one question—
the way to the Governor's house. That accessible mansion was
readily found; doors were swinging open; and, announced by a
sleepy darkey, Janey Bleylock stood in the Governor's presence.</p>
               <p>With a fine and courteous manner that gentleman listened,
struck by her figure, her full voice, and passionate eyes. He
promised to use his influence with the President to procure a
pardon for Dick Oscar, and Janey was allowed to go to the
prison with the cheering news.</p>
               <p>The mountain girl was heard of in high circles. Hearts
beat warmly in lovely Southern bosoms, and they made a
heroine of Janey.</p>
               <p>“Why don't you marry here?” said a beautiful enthusiast,
who had called to see Janey, and kissed her, “because she
knew so well how to love.” “Marry here, and I'll give you a
wedding dress.”</p>
               <pb n="148"/>
               <p>“So we will,” said Dick Oscar, when he was out of prison.</p>
               <p>And Janey went home a wife, as if the stars had been
diamonds, and strung like a larkspur chain for her neck—
father, brothers, husband, sheltering her in their love.</p>
               <p>Mrs. Bleylock and Eliza ran to meet them. Eliza thought
perhaps some one else would come with them. Had not her
lover left her with a kiss and a promise to come back with a
gold ring?</p>
               <p>The pink ribbon was round her neck. Her lips were
parted in a happy, vacant smile.</p>
               <p>The old chap whose head looked as if it were stuck on
with a pin was in advance. He thrust out his arm as Eliza
drew near. “Don't you speak to me!”</p>
               <p>“Pappy!”</p>
               <p>“Damn your tattlin' tongue! Keep away from my hands!”</p>
               <p>The smile had gone; the vacant look spread over the face
that turned helplessly to her brothers.</p>
               <p>“You ought to be whipped like a nigger!” said Sam
Bleylock. “What you tell that peddler 'bout Oscar's still
for? Might 'a known he wuz foolin' you.”</p>
               <p>“I didn't tell where the still wuz.”</p>
               <p>“Hoh! you lie too.” And her father, passing by, struck
her with the back of his hand.</p>
               <p>“Shame on you, pappy!” and Janey ran to her sister, over
whose lips blood was pouring.</p>
               <p>Her husband drew Janey away. “Don's touch her,” he
said, with a look of disgust; “she ain't fit.”</p>
               <p>A wild, terrified look swept over Janey's face. Should she
grasp at the wind blowing in the tree-tops above her? She
<pb n="149"/>
caught Dick Oscar's arm, holding it fiercely. Here was something
to clasp, to cling to. Her soul shrivelled in her ardent
body.</p>
               <p>Afterward Eliza Bleylock seemed to wither away. She
repeated her denial of having been a traitor, but no one ever
believed her. She worked hard, and was used roughly. She
had never been strong. Sometimes she stole away and nursed
<figure>
                     <p>“SHE LEANED HER HEAD AGAINST A TREE.”</p>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="150"/>
Janey's baby, that seemed to love her; but never when Dick
Oscar was at home.</p>
               <p>One day, sitting by the spring alone, too weak since a long
while to work, she leaned her head against a tree, and, with 
one moan, too faint to startle the singing birds, she died.</p>
               <p>Her mother and Janey dressed her cleanly, and tied about
her neck a pink ribbon that they found in her Bible. And
she was buried, with very little said about it, in the valley.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="151"/>
            <div type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
               <head>THE BRAN DANCE AT THE APPLE
		SETTLEMENT.</head>
               <p>“THEY'S mostly Apples in that settle<hi rend="italics">ment</hi>,” said Mr. Jack
Officer. “When they has a blow - out they kind o'
jines together, and makes the feathers fly. Lucky thing for
preachers 'f they take a camp-meetin' in han'. They'll have
the mo'ners lively 'f they have to press every waggin an' old
mule in the Cumberland to git 'em thar. They pretty much
rule things round here. 'F one of 'em takes a fancy to a
good-lookin' girl, the other boys keep away—they are shooters,
them Apples. Thar's a powerful lot of 'em. Old Grandpa
Apple—him that started the settle<hi rend="italics">ment</hi>—is a-livin' yet He
come over from Carliny some sixty years back, in a canopied
waggin, with all he had, includin' his gret-uncle, ready to light
out fur Jordan, an' a yeller dog—female, that's mothered the
best breed o' pups on the mountain. He had two blooded
cows, an' a stavin' young woman for a wife; an' calves an'
children came's fast's he could house 'em—faster too, I reckin,
for they had to tent it one hot summer. The boys they
growed up, an' the married aroun' the country, an' somehow
they've had luck—big, smart, han'some families. An' their childern
is a-marryin' an' child-bearin'. So, you see, old Grandpa
Apple he sees the fourth generation. An' I guess the Lord
<pb n="152"/>
ain't any pleaseder in surveyin' the earth he has made than
that old man in a-countin' Apple noses.</p>
               <p>“They're goin' to have a bran dance to-morrer over in the
settle<hi rend="italics">ment</hi>. Ever seen a bran dance? 'T's a powerful nice
entertainment. Better stop over an' go 'long with me.”</p>
               <p>We “stopped over.” Starting the next morning by earliest
cock-crow, we reached the Apple Settlement, so exhilarated—
ah! delicious air of the Cumberland!—that we were ready to
cut pigeon wings in a bran dance until the bran flew about
our ears as dry as the dust of a powdered mummy.</p>
               <p>The scene was as animated as one of Hogarth's pictures.
Horses, mules, ox-wagons, spring-carts, were huddled at the
gate. People were moving about under the trees with the
fantastic gravity that hides inward joy. Half a dozen slim
young fellows, in blue calico shirts, opening to show their sunburnt
throats, were masters of ceremonies. They shook our
hands with serious cordiality, and nodded silently to Mr. Officer.
They do not say much, these mountain people. How
should they? They might be early-language makers, for the
few words they know. Jack Officer was garrulous. But, as
he said of himself, he was “born with the gab.” Besides, he
read the Bible and a weekly paper.</p>
               <p>Grandpa Apple was sitting under a tree in the yard.</p>
               <p>“Looks like a peeled Apple, <hi rend="italics">he</hi> does,” said Mr. Officer,
facetiously.</p>
               <p>This startling simile was not inappropriate, the old man
was so white and clean. His head was bare, and shone like
the snow. A long white beard dropped from his chin, and
white overhanging eyebrows almost hid his eyes. His face
<pb n="153"/>
was white and wrinkled as a yeasty tub of beer. His trousers
and shirt were of white linsey, and he was fanning himself
with a white turkey-tail fan. He would have served gloriously,
backed up in a Christmas window, as Santa Claus, or the Old
Year.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>GRANDPA APPLE.</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>In the heart of a lovely grove Grandpa Apple had built his
log-cabin. It was so comfortable-looking, so entirely the right
sort of house to be set among those trees! The logs were
sawed in two, and were worn to a rich polish; the spaces
between were new chinked with white mortar. There were
<pb n="154"/>
many rooms connected by little porches wide as foot-paths.
Doors and windows were opened wide. The floors were bare,
and freshly scrubbed. There were beds in every room, four
red posters guarding feather-beds of forty-goose power.
Woodcuts from newspapers and fashion magazines were gummed
on the walls. Althea boughs were thrust into the cavernous
depths of the wide fireplaces, and in one room there was a
wonderful screen made of hundreds of little pictures.</p>
               <p>The kitchen was the place to melt your soul. A mass of
coals that would have frightened Daniel glowed in the fireplace.
A black pot hung from a crane. Half a dozen ovens
were ranged on the hearth, coals under and above them.
From time to time the oven lids were lifted with the burnt
end of a broom-handle, revealing six little pigs in various
stages of brownness. The deities of this place were somewhat
wizened Apples, so to speak. They danced once; now
they cooked. So passes the glory of mountain pinks. They
looked warm, and a little anxious. But now and then they
would plunge their heads into a basin of cool water, and come
up, like Duffy after the third round, confident and smiling.</p>
               <p>The women were nearly all assembled in the room with
the screen. They sat against the walls solemnly. They were
dressed in clean, bright calicoes, cut as low as the collar-bone.
Some—vain, dressy creatures—wore broad, flat, crocheted
collars, and bows shaped like flying birds. The girls were supple
and straight, with ankles not offensive to the eye of man;
but among the matrons were some queer figures, whose lacks
or redundancies were concealed by hoops and set off with
trails.</p>
               <pb n="155"/>
               <p>“Looks 's if them sort ought to perch in the trees,” said
Mr. Officer, watching a green calico dragged across the floor.</p>
               <p>The young men glowered in through the windows, and
poked each other in the sides, making a noise between tongue
and cheek not unlike a prolonged cluck to a horse.</p>
               <p>Mr. Officer held a violin under his chin. “Take your
partners!” he called, with a piercing scrape of the bow across the
strings.</p>
               <p>“My fust fiddled,” remarked Mrs. Officer, “but not with the
skill'dness of Mr. Officer.”</p>
               <p>The young men came in and led out the girls; one mountain
maid—and a pretty one—lingered.</p>
               <p>“You needn't ask me,” she said, coquettishly. “I've promised
to dance the first dance with Mr. Tom Jared.”</p>
               <p>“Should like to know why he don't come,” said young Jack
Apple; “ 'pears 's if he ain't in a hurry.”</p>
               <p>At this instant a little black bullet head was thrust inside
the door, and an African voice called, with a subdued chuckle,</p>
               <p>“Mars' Tom say he done gin out de notion.”</p>
               <p>Sensation. Up jumped the offended fair, and rushed after
the messenger, who ran from the slap to come.</p>
               <p>“She's as mad as forty thousand wet hens,” said Mrs. Officer,
mildly.</p>
               <p>And we thought she had a right to be.</p>
               <p>From the grove sounded the inspiring strain of “Billy in
the Low Grounds.” We found the dancers in a rustic arbor,
roofed with green boughs intertwined with hickory withes.
Floor there was none save the smooth earth covered three
inches deep with wheat-bran. Slightly dampened, it was pleasant
<pb n="156"/>
                  <figure>
                     <p>“MARS' TOM SAY HE DONE GIN OUT DE NOTION.”</p>
                  </figure>
to dance on; but Heaven preserve them when they danced
it dry!</p>
               <p>Men on one side, women on the other, stiff as a line of
bayonets. It was a reel they were to dance. Jack Officer sat
on an inverted barrel at one end of the arbor.</p>
               <p>Down the middle danced the leading pair, and, separating
<pb n="157"/>
with an air of being braced for duty, began their advances at
opposite ends of the line. It was rather heavy. Here was
their stamping ground, and they came down flat-footed.
Suddenly a screech created a pleasant confusion.</p>
               <p>“He trod on my foot a-purpose, he did!” cried a woman
with elfish black hair, shaking her fist at a young fellow.</p>
               <p>Another woman, wife or sweetheart, responded, with a
provoking drawl,</p>
               <p>“What made yer come t' a party bar'-footed?”</p>
               <p>“P'r'aps I'd have as good shoes as you, Jane Oscar, 'f my
man wuz in th' ground-hog whiskey business.”</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>THE BRAN DANCE.</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb n="158"/>
               <p>“Come, come!” interposed a peaceful Apple. “Speaking o'
ground-hog, who'll have a drink?”</p>
               <p>A blue water-bucket, in which a tin dipper floated, was
brought forward.</p>
               <p>All took Titanic gulps. There was a smacking of lips
such as would have done credit to a tournament of lovers.</p>
               <p>“Ah-h! That's the true Cumberland punch!” cried the
refreshed fiddler.</p>
               <p>We tasted the Cumberland punch. It was not made on
the one, two, three principle, but was even more simple. It
was sugarless, lemonless, waterless. It was smoky, strong, and
brought tears to the eyes. In short, it was white whiskey
mixed with white whiskey.</p>
               <p>“An' very strengthenin' to the legs it is,” said Jack Apple,
pressing its offer.</p>
               <p>The dancing began again with vigor, with fire and fury.
The music sped in tripping notes, and Mr. Officer added hi
cracked but cheerful voice:</p>
               <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <l part="N">“Oh! whar did you come from? —</l>
                  <l part="N">Knock a nigger down —</l>
                  <l part="N">Oh! whar did you come from,</l>
                  <l part="N">Jerry <hi rend="italics">M</hi>iah Brown?”</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The bran dried under their warm feet and blew up in little
swirls. The mountain boys jumped until their heads knocked
against the boughs above, and green leaves whirled through
the flying dust. Rills of laughter bubbled forth, checked by
sudden coughs. Girls' loosened hair caught around the wet
necks of their partners.</p>
               <pb n="159"/>
               <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <l part="N">“Don't you weep no more, Sister Mary;</l>
                  <l part="N">Don't you weep no more, Brother John,”</l>
               </lg>
               <p>sang Mr. Officer, kicking his feet against the barrel;</p>
               <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <l part="N">“For Satan is dead, an' the word is said</l>
                  <l part="N">For to save you a heavenly crown.</l>
                  <l part="N">Yes, it is ”- thump, thump -</l>
                  <l part="N">“Yes, it is ” - thump, thump -</l>
                  <l part="N">“For to save you a <hi rend="italics">heavy</hi>-anly crown.”</l>
               </lg>
               <p>“The devil!” suddenly exclaimed one of the Bleylock boys.</p>
               <p>The dancing stopped; Jack Officer leaped from the barrel.</p>
               <p>“Look yonder!” said young Bleylock, pointing up to the
forest roof of the arbor.</p>
               <p>There darted a sunbeam, here fluttered a dogwood blossom,
and between flower and ray the evil head of a snake
wriggled socially.</p>
               <p>“Clear out!” cried Mr. Officer, gesticulating wildly. In two
minutes the place was cleared. The bran settled slowly. His
snakeship was monarch, but there was naught to survey.</p>
               <p>Jack Apple stepped in, however, an open clasp-knife in one
hand. He poured some whiskey on the ground, and stooping,
rubbed his other hand in the wet earth until it was gummy
and black. Whether there was some mysterious significance
in this rite, or he did it to secure a firmer grip, we did not
know. But he seized the snake just back of the head, and
before it could hiss for wonder one snake of the world had
been cut in two, and could not come again.</p>
               <p>Grandpa Apple had surveyed the scene with interest and
pride.</p>
               <pb n="160"/>
               <p>“Purty well done, Jack—putty well,” he said. “ 'T comes
natural to the Apples to hate snakes. D' I ever tell you o'
my scrimmage with the snakes on Council Rock?”</p>
               <p>“Reckon 't 'll b'ar tellin' over agin,” said Jack Officer's wife.</p>
               <p>“ 'Twuz when I fust settled in Tennessee,” said Grandpa
							Apple; “ an'
<figure>
                     <p>“JACK APPLE STEPPED IN, AN OPEN CLASP-<lb/>KNIFE IN ONE HAND.”</p>
                  </figure>
							I built my
							house on a
							rock, like the
man in Scripture
							you know.
							We moved in
							befo' it wuz
							finished, an'
					the roof wuz but partly shingled.
					'Twuz coolish, snappish
					weather, an' I made rousin' big
					fires, an' warmed the old rock
					up. An' one mornin' me an' my
					wife an' the baby (Jack's
					grandpa) wuz in bed, an' I heerd a
					soft, ugly sound—hiss-s-s-s-s!
					The mornin' wuz dark, but I
peered with young eyes at the floor, an' it seemed to be a-risin'
in curls an' waves—put me in mind o' Cany Fork when
the wind is of a moderate gustiness. I raised on my elbow,
an' I squinted up my eyes for a closer look, an' I said,
‘Lord o' creation!’—not that I'm a swarin' man; but them
wuz snakes! an' that sight wuz enough to make a man throw
<pb n="161"/>
rocks at his grandmother. What a lot of 'em, little an' big!
—'s many's there are Apples here to-day. Maybe 'twuz kind
o' prophetic. Well, I woke Nancy, an' told her to roll up
head, ears, an' baby (Jack's grandpa) in the blankets; an' I
crawled up the bed-post an' out through that blessed hole in
the roof. Fortunate I had a neighbor with a family o' boys,
an' we got on boots, an' with rifles an' whips we went in for
the biggest snake-fight ever seen this side o' Jordan. You see,
thar nests wuz under the rock, an' my fires had made it warm
for 'em, an' they had come a-corkscrewin' out o' thar winter
quarters. Tell you we slayed an' we slew! The old woman
she stayed kivered up, ekally afeard, she said, o' men an'
snakes, we got so bloody an' fierce to kill. I do s'pose we
killed a million o' them rattlers—they wuz all rattlers.”</p>
               <p>“Oh! oho! Mr. Apple,” said Jack Officer; “them figgers
is too high. 'F you killed one thousand a day, 'twould take
you a matter o' twenty years to git shet of a million.”</p>
               <p>“Now, look at that!” said the old man, admiringly; and,
“Mr. Officer's a powerful smart man—powerful,” said Jack's
wife.</p>
               <p>It was now noon, and dinner was served in the grove.
The table was made of pine boards stretched across chair
backs. It was crowded with savory dishes, and as for the
dear little pigs, never were pigs so good since the first that
it took the burning of a hut to roast.</p>
               <p>After dinner the dance began again, but we were tired and
spent with laughter. We sought a far-off tree, and, gazed upon
admiringly by three small Apples, slept until the bran dance
was over.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="162"/>
            <div type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
               <head>LAME JERRY.</head>
               <p>WITH her baby at her breast, Jane Oscar strolled through
the woods one summer morning. There were memories
in this young woman's life that sometimes violently agitated
her heart, and at such times nothing pleased her more than to
plunge into wild depths of the forest, and forget in physical
fatigue the pain it angered her to feel. As she stepped on,
fleet of foot, with down-dropped eyes, and arms tight as steel
around her child, she was startled by a weakly-uttered curse,
loosed apparently, like a poisonous odor, from the ground.
Pressing on, flung among a heap of weeds beside a fallen
tree, she saw a coiled, misshapen figure. An ugly, contorted
face lay, with closed eyes, in a piercing sun-ray. It had, probably,
been the sun-ray that he had cursed.</p>
               <p>“Lame Jerry!”</p>
               <p>“Jane!—is that Jane Oscar?”</p>
               <p>“Yes. What's the matter?”</p>
               <p>“They've done for me, I'm afeard, Jane.”</p>
               <p>“Who? what? in pity's name.”</p>
               <p>“Them wild-cat devils who helped t' run Welch's still.”</p>
               <p>“You told on 'em to Peters?” in a loud, frightened whisper.</p>
               <p>“Yes. d -- n them! And they've killed me for it.”</p>
               <p>“Mebbe not, Jerry. I'll go for Dick, an' we'll do all we kin 
for you.”</p>
               <pb n="163"/>
               <p>Then, with a woman's impulse, she took off her cotton
dress waist and hung it on a bush in a way to shield Lame
Jerry's eyes from the sun; and hiding her neck and her bare
breast with her hair and the soft baby form, she hurried
home.</p>
               <p>“It wuz wrong in the boys—all wrong,” said Dick Oscar,
when Jane had told him how she had found Lame Jerry half
dead in the woods.</p>
               <p>“Yes, it <hi rend="italics">wuz</hi> wrong,” said Jane, hotly, “an' cruel, too, to
treat a man so, just for bein' on the side o' the law.”</p>
               <p>“Yes; they ought to 'a killed him outright,” said Mr. Oscar,
thoughtfully.</p>
               <p>“Dick! you don't mean it?”</p>
               <p>“Come, come, my girl, you've got a soft spot in yo' heart
fur sneaks, on account o' yo' sister; but you can't expect <hi rend="italics">me</hi> to
stomach 'em.”</p>
               <p>“No, no,” said Jane, in a dull, low tone; “but you'll be
kind to Jerry, won't you?”</p>
               <p>“Lord! yes, Why not? But if he gits up agin, poor old
devil! I guess he'll wish we'd 'a left him whar we found him.”</p>
               <p>“That ain't our look-out.”</p>
               <p>They brought him to their cabin, and nursed him, rudely,
but with skill enough to bring him through the fever that set
in from his inflamed wounds.</p>
               <p>In his raving he called continually for his daughter.</p>
               <p>“Cordy! Cordy! Cordy!” repeated in tones that rang, or
moaned, or prayed; but no woman bent over him save brown-eyed
Jane Oscar, and faithfully she tended him, while the baby
screamed from its cradle in fright at the strange, rough voice.</p>
               <pb n="164"/>
               <p>A conscious day came, and he called to Jane, “Does Cordy
know?”</p>
               <p>He looked so pitiful lying there, a stunted, humpbacked
figure, his eyes big in his gaunt face, his hair white—an old
man hated by the mountain people among whom he lived,
shaken by nameless fears for the one thing that he loved.</p>
               <p>“I ain't been able to git word ter Cordy,” said Jane Oscar.</p>
               <p>“D'ye know how she's got on, all alone there, the poor
child? She wuz always one to be frightened at shadows and
noises.”</p>
               <p>Jane said nothing.</p>
               <p>“Why don't you speak, Jane Oscar?”</p>
               <p>“You're mighty weak, Jerry. I don't want you to have no set-
back.”</p>
               <p>“An' what could you tell me, woman, to give me a set-
back?”</p>
               <p>Jane put her lips together, and, taking up her baby, gave
it the breast.</p>
               <p>“Might 's well tell him, Janey,” said Dick Oscar; “it's got
to come.”</p>
               <p>“Tell him yourself, then.”</p>
               <p>Lame Jerry's eyes glared at the two—the stolid beings who
were hiding some awful secret from him—one smoking a cob
pipe, the other suckling her child, removed remote from his
terrible suffering as heaven from hell.</p>
               <p>“Whar's my daughter?”</p>
               <p>“Well, old man,” said Dick Oscar, “she's gone with
Discoe.”</p>
               <p>“Are they married?”</p>
               <pb n="165"/>
               <p>“Not as I's heerd tell.”</p>
               <p>“Oh God! God! God!”</p>
               <p>“Come, Jerry, don't take it so hard. He'll treat her kind.”</p>
               <p>“<hi rend="italics">Treat her kind!</hi> I hope he'll kill her! Oh, my lost girl!
my little lost Cordy!”</p>
               <p>“I'm powerful sorry for you, Jerry,” said Jane, shifting her
baby comfortably from one arm to the other.</p>
               <p>“Keep yo' sorrow till it's asked for.”</p>
               <p>“You know he may marry her,” said Dick, putting a fresh
coal in his pipe, “if she's pleasant to him; he's a nice man,
Discoe is.”</p>
               <p>“A d -- d whiskey-drinking devil!”</p>
               <p>“He's got his faults, but they're the faults of a <hi rend="italics">man</hi>,” said
Mr. Oscar, impartially; “and he ain't a tattlin' sneak.”</p>
               <p>Lame Jerry turned his face to the wall and groaned.</p>
               <p>From that time he seemed to get well with a sort of fury.
He rarely spoke, never smiled, and Jane could only guess at
the thoughts that fixed on his rugged features the expression
of a demon. He said little to her about having saved his
life, but on leaving he flung into the baby's lap a purse of
money.</p>
               <p>“What's that?” cried Dick Oscar. He snatched the child
up, and the purse fell to the floor. He kicked it toward Lame
Jerry. “We don't want none of the money you wuz bought
with,” said the stern husband of Janey Bleylock.</p>
               <p>Lame Jerry did not go back to his now hateful home, but
lived on the mountain as simply as a wild beast, hiding from
men, indifferent to all things save the set purpose of his life.
It was known to but few that he had survived the
<pb n="166"/>
moonshiners' attempt to kill him. Jane and Dick Oscar were
silent people, and news travelled slowly in that mountain
country.</p>
               <p>Lame Jerry lay in wait for Discoe, and saw him continually
as he lounged about his occupations—hunting, fishing, hoeing
his little patch of ground, riding down the mountain to join
the boys in a frolic. But he never shadowed Cordy's lover as
far as his cabin door. He would not see his child until —</p>
               <p>The day came at last. Discoe was cleaning his gun in the
woods, unarmed, inert, unsuspicious. Behind him, huge and
misshapen, the hunchback crawled and coiled and sprung.
There was little resistance—the surprise was too complete
—and Lame Jerry's arm was nerved by hate and madness.
When Discoe was dead the murderer dragged his body to
Caney Fork, and weighting it with rocks, saw it sink beneath
the hiding waves. Then he went to his daughter.</p>
               <p>“Cordy!”</p>
               <p>At the sound of his voice, and at sight of him, the girl
fell, screaming. She fully believed her father dead, and being
slow of wit, now conceived that his ghost stood in her
doorway.</p>
               <p>“Don't you know your father, Cordy?”</p>
               <p>“You are his spirit.”</p>
               <p>“No, I am flesh, my girl. Come to me.”</p>
               <p>“You were killed by Welch's boys.”</p>
               <p>“I wuz hurt, but I got well.”</p>
               <p>Still, incredulity and fear were in the girl's big wandering
blue eyes. “If you ain't a ghost,” said she, timidly, “taste my
soup on the fire.”</p>
               <pb n="167"/>
               <p>“No, my girl. I won't taste Discoe's soup. But look here.”</p>
               <p>He threw himself on the high, soft feather-bed, and rising,
pointed to the impress of his form. She came forward, her
hands outstretched, like one who is blind. He seized them,
and gazed into her face. Yes, it was the same white, fragile
Cordy, not altered by a line or a trace of thought. The same
wide, simple blue eyes; the same weak, red baby mouth; the
light hair falling in a smooth plait; the skin clear and colorless.
But was his gaze distracted that he fancied a change
in the slim girl's figure?</p>
               <p>“Cordy! Cordy!” He clasped her in his arms, and she
wept. But before he kissed her he wiped her face fiercely,
as though rubbing off a stain. “And so, my girl,” he said,
gently, after they had talked a long while, “you didn't think
you wuz doin' anything wrong to take up with Discoe—and
no preacher to make it honest?”</p>
               <p>She twisted her fingers nervously. “I didn't know what
to do. They said you wuz dead. An' Discoe said he'd like
to have me. An' he's a nice, well-made man. An' I wuz so
dull with fright an' grief that I didn't much care. But I care
now. An' he's goin' to marry me, pappy, when—when the
baby comes.”</p>
               <p>“He's a black-hearted devil.”</p>
               <p>“No, pappy, no. You don't know him 's I do. He's been
powerful good to me.”</p>
               <p>Lame Jerry sat long in Discoe's cabin, affecting not to see
Cordy's restless glances down the mountain path.</p>
               <p>“I'll go now,” he said, “ 'nless you like t' have me stop with
you to-night, Cordy.”</p>
               <pb n="168"/>
               <p>“Better not, pappy. Discoe mightn't like it. But I'll tell
him about you when he comes home, an' to-morrer you come
t' see him.”</p>
               <p>Her father came with the morrow, to find Cordy but slightly
annoyed at Discoe's non-appearance. “I reckon he's off
somewhere with the boys,” she said; “I ain't no call to
fret.”</p>
               <p>Days passed; weeks dragged along. Lame Jerry spent all
his time now in Discoe's cabin, but Cordy rarely spoke to him.
All her soul was absorbed in watching and waiting. Her hearing
grew to be so finely attuned that she heard all strange
sounds of nature that hide from dull ears; but never the
sound for which she waited.</p>
               <p>“Cordy,” said her father one day, “it's lonely here.”</p>
               <p>“Not for me, pappy. I have to keep things ready for
Discoe.”</p>
               <p>“He won't come, girl.”</p>
               <p>Cordy smiled—that dim, vacant smile that Jerry was learning
to dread.</p>
               <p>“Come with me, honey; let us go away.”</p>
               <p>“I must wait here, pappy.”</p>
               <p>“You don't feel as if you could give him up, my girl, for
me as loves you so much, much more?”</p>
               <p>And Cordy answered, very simply, “How can I give him
up, pappy?—he's my man, you know.”</p>
               <p>Again he said to her, “You didn't know I had money,
Cordy, in the bank at Nashville?”</p>
               <p>“No, pappy.”</p>
               <p>“I've always kept you different from others,” said the old
<pb n="169"/>
man. “I meant to leave the mountains with you when there
wuz money enough for us to be free. But I had to hurry.
You remember the day you wuz fifteen?”</p>
               <p>“Yes, pappy,” she said, vacantly.</p>
               <p>“You had been strange an' ailin' a long time, and that day
you fell down in a fit. I knowed then I must hurry an' git
you to the city, whar a doctor could cure you. That wasn't
more'n a year ago. You're only a child now, Cordy.”</p>
               <p>“Yes, pappy.”</p>
               <p>“It wuz slow work makin' money, so I engaged as a spy to
Peters; he paid well, or Government paid through him. It
wuz for you, Cordy—for you.”</p>
               <p>“ 'Twuzn't right, pappy. Discoe didn't think it wuz right.”</p>
               <p>“Honey, have you had any of them fits since you came
here to live with Discoe?”</p>
               <p>“One, pappy. Sometimes I think that's why he left me.”</p>
               <p>“Then you ought to hate him. Give up the thoughts of
him, child, an' come with me to Nashville. It'll be pleasant.
We'll have a pretty little house, not a rough log-cabin. An'
I'll hire a woman to do all the work. You sha'n't soil your
little hands, my girl; and I'll buy you ribbons and such gowns
as city girls wear—blue and pink. An' I'll get a buggy an'
take you drivin' every day like a lady. Won't you come, my
girl?”</p>
               <p>“No, pappy; I have to stay here. My man will be back soon,
an' he'll want Cordy.”</p>
               <p>And to every attack or entreaty Cordy returned the same
unmoved answer. Once he threatened her. But at his tone
of force and rough authority she fell in the dreadful convulsions
<pb n="170"/>
that maddened him and shook her reason. After that
he was always gentle with her.</p>
               <p>One day a travelling preacher stopped at the cabin and
asked to stay all night. When Cordy learned who he was an
unwonted excitement took possession of her.</p>
               <p>She called her father apart.</p>
               <p>“Discoe said he'd marry me the first time a preacher come
this way,” she whispered, her light eyes shining. “P'r'aps he
has sent this one.”</p>
               <p>“No, no, my girl; don't think it.”</p>
               <p>“But I will think it,” she said, shrilly, and springing toward
the stranger. “Mister, did my man send you? and will he
come after you soon?”</p>
               <p>The stranger stared.</p>
               <p>“Don't mind her,” said Lame Jerry, roughly. “Her man
left her, and she ain't been right in her wits since.”</p>
               <p>Looking from one to the other, Cordy burst into a low
laugh.</p>
               <p>“I see; Discoe wants to surprise me. But never mind;
I'll be ready.”</p>
               <p>As the sun went down she dressed herself in a white dress,
and braided her smooth, thick hair. Then, with a smile, she
sat watching by the window. Ah! it was a sight for God to
pity! The young, unrested head, the eagerness of the sharpened
face, and, defined against the rough walls, the most pathetic
shape of one soon to become a mother, with Shame
and Despair for her furious handmaidens.</p>
               <p>After this her father hoped no more. A little later, in a
<pb n="171"/>
driving storm, he plunged down the mountain to find Jane
Oscar and bring her to his child. At the wild midnight
hour a babe was laid on Cordy's piteous young breast—both
breathed faintly until the rising of the sun, when their souls
went out together. And Lame Jerry was left to live with his
money—and his memories.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="172"/>
            <div type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
               <head>JACK AND THE MOUNTAIN PINK.</head>
               <p>YOUNG SELDEN was bored. Who was not bored among
the men? It was the tense summer of '78. A forlorn
band of refugees from the plague crowded a Nashville hotel.
There was nothing for the men to do but to read the fever
bulletins, play billiards in an insensate sort of way, and keep
out of the way of the women crying over the papers.</p>
               <p>Young Selden felt that another month of this sort of thing,
would leave him melancholy mad. So he jammed some things
into a light bag and started off for a tramp over Cumberland
Mountain.</p>
               <p>“I envy you,” said a decrepit old gentleman, with whom he
was shaking hands in good-bye. “I was brought up in the
mountain country fifty years ago. Gay young buck I was! Go
in, my boy, and make love to a mountain pink! Ah, those
jolly, barefooted, melting girls! No corsets, no back hair, no
bangs, by Heaven!”</p>
               <p>It was the afternoon of a hot September day. Young
Selden had started that morning from Bloomington Springs
in the direction of the Window Cliff—a ridge of rocks from
which he had been told a very fine view could be obtained.
The road grew rougher and wilder, seeming to lose itself in
hills, stumps, and fields, and was as hard to trace out as a
<pb n="173"/>
                  <hi rend="italics">Bazar</hi> pattern. He finally struck a foot-path leading to a
log-cabin, where a very brown woman sat peacefully smoking in
the door-way.</p>
               <p>“Good-day,” he said, taking off his hat.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>“‘GOOD-DAY,’ HE SAID, TAKING OFF HIS HAT.”</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>The brown woman nodded in a friendly manner—the little
short, meaning nod of the mountains, that serves, so to speak,
as the pro-word of these silent folk. Young Selden inquired
the way to Window Cliff.</p>
               <p>“You carn't git thar 's the crow flies,” she drawled, slowly;
“but I reckin my daughter k'n g'long with yer.”</p>
               <p>“Aha!” thought Selden—“a mountain pink!”</p>
               <pb n="174"/>
               <p>“Take a cheer,” said the mother, rising and going within.
He seated himself on the steps, and made friends with a dog
or two.</p>
               <p>A young girl soon appeared, tying on a sun-bonnet. She
greeted him with a nod, the reproduction of her mother's, and
drawled, in the same tone, “Reckin you couldn't git tu Winder
Clift 'thout somebody to show you the way.”</p>
               <p>“And you will be my guide?”</p>
               <p>“ 'F co'se.”</p>
               <p>They started off, young Selden talking airily. He soon felt,
however, that he shouldn't make love to <hi rend="italics">this</hi> mountain pink.
To begin with, there was no pink about her. She was brown,
like her mother.</p>
               <p>“Coffee!” thought Selden, with a grim remembrance of a
black, muddy liquid he had drunk a few nights before at a
log-cabin, over which the very babies smacked their lips.</p>
               <p>Her eyes had the melancholy of a cow's, without the
ruminative expression that gives sufficient intellectuality to a cow's
sad gaze. To put it tersely, they looked stupid. Her mouth
curled down a little at each corner. Her hair was not visible
under her pea-green sun-bonnet. Her dress of whitish linsey
was skimpy in its cut, and she wriggled in it as if it were a
loose skin she was trying to get out of.</p>
               <p>She was not a talker. She looked at Selden with big eyes,
and listened impassively. He elicited from her that her name
was Sincerity Hicks; that her mother was the widder Hicks,
and there were no others in the family; that she had never
been to school, but could read, only she had no books.</p>
               <p>“Should you like some?”</p>
               <pb n="175"/>
               <p>“Dunno. 'Pears 's if thar's too much to do t' fool over
books.”</p>
               <p>Perhaps because he had talked so much young Selden
began to get out of breath. They had crossed a field, climbed
a fence, and were descending a great hill, breaking a path as
they walked. He panted, and could hardly keep up with
Sincerity, though she seemed not to walk fast. But she got over
the ground with a light-footed agility that aroused his envy.
It looked easy, but, since he could not emulate her, he concluded
that long practice had trained her walk to its perfection.
He noticed, too, that she walked “parrot-footed,” placing each
new track in the impression of the other. Imitating this,
awkwardly enough, he got on better.</p>
               <p>Reaching the clear level at the bottom of the hill, he saw
at a glance that he had penetrated to a wild and virginal heart
of beauty. Like a rough water-fall melting into a silver-flowing
river, the vexatious and shaggy hill sloped to a dreaming
valley. Streams ran about, quietly as thoughts, over pale
rocks. Calacanthus bushes, speckled with their ugly little red
blooms, filled the air with a fragrance like that of crushed
strawberries. Upspringing from this low level of prettiness
rose the glory of the valley—the lordly, the magnificent birch-
trees. Their topmost boughs brushed against the cliffs that
shut in the valley on the opposite side. How fine these cliffs
were! They rose up almost perpendicularly, and, freed halfway
of their height from the thick growth of underbrush, stood
out in bare, bold picturesqueness. Window Cliffs! Aha! these
were the windows. Two wide spaces, square and clean-blown,
framing always a picture—now a bit of hard blue sky; other
<pb n="176"/>
times pink flushes of sunrise, or the voluptuous moon and
peeping eyes of stars.</p>
               <p>“Want ter go t' the top?” inquired Sincerity.</p>
               <p>“I—dunno,” rejoined Selden, lazily. Truth was, he did not
wish to move. He liked the vast shadows, the cool deeps, the
singing tones of the valley. Then he was sure he had a blister
on his heel. Still, to come so far—“How long a walk is it?”</p>
               <p>“Oh, jest a little piece—'bout a quarter.”</p>
               <p>“Up and away, then!” cried young Selden.</p>
               <p>A long “quarter” he found that walk. They crossed the
valley, climbed a fence, and dropped into a corn-field to be
hobbled over. Up and down those hideous little furrows—it
was as sickening as tossing on a chopping sea. Selden stopped
to rest. Sincerity, not a feather the worse, looked him over
with mild patience.</p>
               <p>“Lemme tote yo' haversack,” she said.</p>
               <p>“No, no,” said the young man, with an honest blush. But
he was reminded of a flask of brandy in his knapsack, of which
he took a grateful swig.</p>
               <p>“Now,” said his guide, as, the corn-field crossed, they
emerged into forest—“now we begins to climb the mountain.”</p>
               <p>Selden groaned. He had thought himself nearly on a
level with the Window Cliff. To this day that climb is an
excruciating memory to young Selden. He thought of</p>
               <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <l part="N">“Johnny Schnapps,</l>
                  <l part="N">Who bust his shtraps,”</l>
               </lg>
               <p>and wondered if the disaster was not suffered in going up a
mountain. He felt himself melting away with heat. He knew
<pb n="177"/>
that his face was blazing like a Christmas pudding, and dripping
like a roast on a spit. He resigned the attempt to keep
up with Sincerity. When they started on this excruciating
tramp the droop of her pea-green sun-bonnet had seemed to
him abject; now he knew that it expressed only contempt—
contempt for the weakling and the stranger.</p>
               <p>But one gets to the top of most things by trying hard
enough, and they gained at last the rough crags that commanded
the valley.</p>
               <p>Ah! the fair, grand State! There was a spot for a blind
man to receive sight! The young man drew a long breath as
he gazed over the bewitching expanse. All so fresh, so
unbreathed-on, the only hints of human life the little log-cabins
perched about, harmonious as birds' nests amid their
surroundings.</p>
               <p>Sincerity Hicks stood fanning herself with the green
sun-bonnet. There was something pretty about her, now that this
disfigurement was removed. But a mountain pink—what a
pretty implication in the name!—no.</p>
               <p>“So this is Window Cliff?” he said. “And is there any
particular name for that ledge yonder?”</p>
               <p>“ 'Tis called Devil's Chimney, 'nd the cut between is Long
Hungry Gap.”</p>
               <p>“Long Hungry Gap?—where have I heard that famished
name? Oh yes, some of Peters's scouts. You know Peters?”</p>
               <p>“Yaas, I've heerd tell o' Jim Peters.”</p>
               <p>Sincerity's drawl was not quickened, but Selden was
surprised to see a light leap into her eyes as suddenly as a witch
through a key-hole.</p>
               <pb n="178"/>
               <p>“These fellows had a room next to mine at the Bloomington
Hotel,” Selden went on, “and the walls are like paper; so I heard
all they said.”</p>
               <p>“And what d' they say?”</p>
               <p>“Well, that the captain was up the country on a moonshine
raid; but that they were on the track of something
better—had heard of a ‘powerful big still’ up in Long Hungry
Gap—and would mash it up as soon as the captain got back.”</p>
               <p>“D' they say when Peters wuz expected?”</p>
               <p>“The next day.”</p>
               <p>Sincerity tied on her bonnet.</p>
               <p>“Guess you kin find the way back,” she remarked.</p>
               <p>“Hello! what does this mean?”</p>
               <p>“I've got somethin' t' attend to across the mounting.”</p>
               <p>“I'll go with you.”</p>
               <p>Sincerity stopped and turned a serious face. “Likely 's
not you'll git hurt.”</p>
               <p>“Oho! I'm <hi rend="italics">in</hi>, if there's any chance of a scrimmage. Go
ahead.”</p>
               <p>She did go ahead. If the path had been vexatious before,
now it was revengeful and aggressive. In fact, there was no
path. But Sincerity, like love, found out a way. Suddenly,
like a comic mask popped on a friend's face, something sinister
and strange burst upon them through the familiar woods.
Or, rather, they burst upon it—a wild-cat still, securely
sheltered under an innocent combination of rocks, ferns, and
magnolia-trees.</p>
               <p>Four or five wild-looking fellows sprang up, their hands on
their rifles.</p>
               <pb n="179"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>“ ‘NONE O' YO' SHOOTIN',’ SAID SINCERITY.”</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>“None o' yo' shootin',” said Sincerity Hicks; “he's a friend.”</p>
               <p>“Sho' he ain't a spy? 'Cause if that's the case, mister,
you'll stay in these woods face down.”</p>
               <p>“My impetuous moonshiner, I don't call myself the friend
of you law-breakers? but I'm no spy. I brought the news to
the faithful Sincerity of Captain Peters being on your track.”</p>
               <p>Hurried questions were asked and answered. Several
resolute voices suggested to fight it out, but all seemed to await
the decision of an old man they called Jack, who leaned
<pb n="180"/>
against a tub, with a touching expression of meekness under
unmerited ill-luck.</p>
               <p>“No, boys,” he said; “we ain't strong enough. But we'll
run off what we can. Save the copper—we'll never git another
so big an' satisfactory—an' the mash tun, an' as many
of the tubs 's you can git off.”</p>
               <p>It was a transformation scene. Things seemed to fly to
pieces all at once, like a bomb-shell. The great copper still
was hoisted on the shoulders of two or three men; the worm,
the mash tun, the coolers, were taken down with celerity, and
the unlucky moonshiners made off through the woods.</p>
               <p>“Reckin th' rest 'll have ter go,” said Jack, pensively; “but
tell you what, Sincerity Hicks, seems 's if I couldn't b'ar to
have 'em git th' old sow an' her pigs.”</p>
               <p>“Run 'em off.”</p>
               <p>“They're too young, honey. Come 'ere.”</p>
               <p>He led to a mimosa-tree behind a rock; and under its
sensitive shade reposed, like Father Nile, a portly porcine mother,
overrun with little, pink, blind pigs.</p>
               <p>“Ain't you got a spar' tub?” asked the girl.</p>
               <p>His face lighted. “I catches,” he said, gently.</p>
               <p>He brought an empty whiskey puncheon, and covered the
bottom with straw. Then he lifted the pink pigs into it, assisted
by Sincerity and the elegant Selden.</p>
               <p>The mother squealed. “Stuff her mouth,” ordered the old
man.</p>
               <p>Sincerity thrust an ear of corn into the open jaws.</p>
               <p>“Now,” said Jack, “I'll run briefly through the woods,
a-toting this, an' the old sow she'll follow—”</p>
               <pb n="181"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>“NO, YOU DON'T, JACK BODDY!”</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>“No, you don't, Jack Boddy!” said a quiet voice. “ Smell o'
that.”</p>
               <p>The ugly end of a rifle protruded itself. A Tennessee
giant leaned against the rock. Peters? Of course it was
Peters. What other man had that easy swagger, three feet
of black beard, and as wide a grin in saying checkmate?</p>
               <pb n="182"/>
               <p>Jack Boddy smiled innocently.</p>
               <p>“Why, captain, you see me jest attendin' to a litter o' pigs
o' mine.”</p>
               <p>“Yes, I see. An' my men is attendin to some pigs o
yourn. Walk out, old 'coon.”</p>
               <p>Peters's scouts were destroying all that was left of the
mountain still.</p>
               <p>“Whar's the others?” asked one of the men.</p>
               <p>“I run this here still all by myself,” said Jack, with an air
of ingenuous pride.</p>
               <p>“What a lie!” said the captain. “Have you cut his copper
boiler, boys?”</p>
               <p>“ 'Tain't here.”</p>
               <p>“Whar's your copper, Jack?”</p>
               <p>“Gone to heaven,” said Jack, rolling his eyes.</p>
               <p>“You can't make anything out o' Jack Boddy,” said a
scout, grinning.</p>
               <p>“Well, I've got you, anyhow,” cried the captain.</p>
               <p>“An' the oldest one in the business, Jim.”</p>
               <p>“An' I'll ketch the rest in time. Come on, boys. We'll
stop at the widder Hicks's to-night. Can your mother put us
up, Sissy?”</p>
               <p>“Dunno,” said Sincerity.</p>
               <p>“Mighty know-nothin' all of a sudden.” And turning to
Selden: “You're a stranger, I see, mister. On the cirkit?”</p>
               <p>“Not at all; only a traveller. Climbed the Window Cliff,
and stumbled over here.”</p>
               <p>“ 'F you'd been in these parts a year or so ago,” said an old
man, relieving his mouth of the white whiskers he was chewing
<pb n="183"/>
“you'd 'a seen a sight o' stills. They were thick as weevils
in flour. But a man of might arose in the land, and he
cleared 'em out.”</p>
               <p>“Peters, I suppose?”</p>
               <p>“Yessir—James Cook Peters, whose name ought to be
Gideon, the Sword of the Lord; formerly an ignorant blacksmith
of Tipper County, but advanced, by the grace of God
an' the app'intment of gov'ment, to bust wild-cat stills, an'
flood the earth with hot whiskey a-steamin' from the vats.”</p>
               <p>“Any—er—murderin' involved in the blacksmithin' trade?”
inquired Jack Boddy, with a casual air of interest.</p>
               <p>Captain Peters turned an angry red, but said nothing.</p>
               <p>“Becaze,” continued the artless old man, “it's a pretty
bloody business you've took up now. How many men have
you killed? Five, I b'lieve, with your own hand, an' twenty-one
with yer men.”</p>
               <p>“It wuz a fair fight,” said the captain. “I killed 'em honorable,
an' wuz acquitted by the laws o' my country.”</p>
               <p>“And though their numbers should be seventy times
seven,” said the white-haired satellite of the captain, “and
the land run with blood, this thing has got to be put a stop
to.</p>
               <p>“Look a-here, James Riggs,” said Jack, “this here moonshinin'
is jest a wriggle-worm. Don't you know howsoever
many pieces you chop 'em into, a fresh head 'll grow,
an' a new worm swim away? Tell you, you cant stop moonshinin'
's long's there's an honest man in Old Hickory's State.”</p>
               <p>“The Lord commanded, and the sun stood still,” said
James Riggs; “ 'twon't be no harder job 'n that.”</p>
               <pb n="184"/>
               <p>As they talked they were descending the mountain. The
noble Jack, alas! was handcuffed and guarded between two
men. From time to time he scratched his head against the
end of a rifle that was nearer his ear than some men would
have liked. Evidently, though open to reproach, Mr. Boddy
was a knight without fear.</p>
               <p>The widow Hicks manifested no surprise at the coming
of her guests. They found her with her hands plunged into
a great tray of meal and water—enough to make hoe-cake for
a regiment.</p>
               <p>“Hurry up with supper, old woman,” said Captain Peters.
“I'm dead tired. I rid all last night, an' ain't slept for three
nights runnin'.”</p>
               <p>At supper he could hardly keep his eyes open.</p>
               <p>“I'll turn in right off,” he said.</p>
               <p>There were some preliminaries to be gone through with—
not of prayers or undressing, however. The captain eyed his
prisoner thoughtfully, and remarked, “B'lieve they call you
Slippery Jack?”</p>
               <p>“ 'I am kind of hard to hold,” said Mr. Boddy, with a modest
twinkle.</p>
               <p>“So!”</p>
               <p>Another moment, and Jack was tightly bound by a stout
rope around the captain's own body. “I reckon you don't git
away to-night.”</p>
               <p>“Dunno!” said Jack.</p>
               <p>The cabin had two rooms. In one the widow, Sincerity,
and Mr. James Riggs went to bed. Mr. Boddy and the captain
occupied the one bed in the other. A third of it was offered
<pb n="185"/>
young Selden, but he preferred a blanket and the floor. The
scouts were divided, and guarded doors and windows.</p>
               <p>Young Selden could not sleep. The wild novelty of the
situation excited him, and his aching limbs made him toss
uneasily. A little fire smouldered on the hearth, and big, shapeless
shadows clutched at each other in the corners. Plenty of
sounds broke the silence. The captain, happy in having made
a Siamese twin of Slippery Jack, snored as if he were choking
to death. The guards talked and jested roughly. A whippoor-will's
three wild notes sounded just above the roof. He
wondered if Jack was asleep. No; there was a slight alert
movement of his body, and young Selden caught the gleam of
a wild blue eye under a shaggy eyebrow. With perceptions
sharpened, intensified, Selden waited for he knew not what.
Mr. Boddy's eye rolled upward—and what! a wilder, brighter
eye, a star, shone with answering ray through a crevice in the
roof. The crevice widened; other stars stole in sight. Selden
felt as if his senses were leaving him. Now the crevice was
obscured; and now something shining, glimmering, and cold
as the light of eye or star, protruded itself cautiously as peeping
mouse through the hole in the roof. It was the point of
an open knife.</p>
               <p>Selden almost sprang to his feet. Was he to witness
murder? But somehow he trusted Jack Boddy—and he
waited.</p>
               <p>The knife was affixed to a knotted rope. It soon dangled
within reach of Mr. Boddy's hand. And the sly moonshiner,
with a silent grin at the sleeping captain, cut the ropes that
bound them together. Then hand over hand, lightly as a
<pb n="186"/>
sailor, he climbed the rope, slipped through the opening, and
was gone,</p>
               <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <l part="N">“Over the hills, and far away.”</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Young Selden wanted to shout. But he contented himself
with a quiet chuckle, and went to sleep.</p>
               <p>He was awakened in the morning by blue-blaze swearing.
The captain was foaming at the mouth, James Riggs was
wiping his eyes with a spotted handkerchief, and the scouts
were swearing by all that was blessed or damned that they
had not closed their eyes.</p>
               <p>“How is it with you, stranger?” said Captain Peters. “Did
you see or hear anything?”</p>
               <p>“Oh no. I slept straight through,” said young Selden,
with that cheerful readiness to lie that comes to great souls.</p>
               <p>“Well, the devil must 'a helped him.”</p>
               <p>“Lor, boys,” said the widow Hicks, with a slight twitch at
the corners of her mouth, “you know Jack Boddy is a powerful
cunnin' man—slippery as an eel.”</p>
               <p>“Jest let me get these hands on him once more—jes' <hi rend="italics">once</hi>
more!”</p>
               <p>“S'pose you'd kill him, wouldn't you?” said the widow,
sweetly. “Lor, now, I s'pose you don't make no more of
killin' a man 'n I do of wringin' a chicken's neck?”</p>
               <p>“Don't excite him,” implored James Riggs; “he's powerful
plagued over this misfortune.”</p>
               <p>“Come to breakfast,” said the widow. “I won't make no
laughin'-stawk of him 'f I can help it.”</p>
               <p>“Damnation!” said the captain.</p>
               <p>As for Sincerity Hicks, she looked as stolid as a wooden
<pb n="187"/>
Indian. Selden pressed some money in her hand at parting,
and whispered, “My dear girl, I was delighted; you climb like
a cat.”</p>
               <p>“Guess this 'll be good for some blue beads,” she said, without
moving a muscle; “I've been a-wantin' some a right smart
while.”</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>“A MOUNTAIN PINK!”</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Young Selden shook with silent laughter as he strode
away.</p>
               <p>“A mountain pink!” he murmured. “Oh no, a bean stalk
—a Cumberland bean stalk.”</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>