<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:fo="urn:oasis:names:tc:opendocument:xmlns:xsl-fo-compatible:1.0" 
     xmlns:style="urn:oasis:names:tc:opendocument:xmlns:style:1.0" 
     xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
     xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
     xmlns:w="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/wordprocessingml/2006/main"
     xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main" 
     xmlns:r="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/officeDocument/2006/relationships" 
     xmlns:p="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/presentationml/2006/main">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TEI Simple: summary</title>
        <author>Sebastian Rahtz</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>September 2014</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>University of Oxford</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Freely available for use and derivative works under a Creative Commons Attribution
	      license.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>born digital</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
	<head>TEI Simple</head>
	<list>
	  <item>Joint project between TEI Consortium, Mellon Foundation, Northeastern University, University of Nebraska-Lincoln, and the University of Oxford</item>
	  <item>TEI Simple aims to define
a new highly-constrained and prescriptive subset of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI)
Guidelines suited to the representation of early modern and modern books, and a formally-defined set of processing rules which permit modern web applications to easily present and analyze the encoded texts</item>
 <item>Project investigators are Martin Mueller (NW), Brian Pytlik Zillig (UNL), Sebastian Rahtz (Ox).</item>
 <item>Project team includes Magdalena Turska (DiXiT project, Oxford), James Cummings (Oxford), Lou Burnard (Oxford)</item>
 <item>Project runs from September 2014 to July 2015</item>
	</list>
      </div>

      <div>
	<head>Objectives</head>
	<list rend="ordered">
	  <item>The highly constrained and prescriptive element subset of TEI Simple</item>
	  <item>The processing model</item>
	  <item>Formal mapping of the TEI elements used by Simple to the CIDOC CRM</item>
	  <item>TEI-Performance Indicators</item>
	  <item>Integration of TEI Simple into the TEI infrastructure </item>
	</list>
      </div>

      <div>
	<head>The Simple schema: guidelines</head>
	<list>
	  <item><q>Simple</q> does not have to mean <q>Small</q></item>
	  <item>The schema is based on analysis of existing usage</item>
	  <item>Our biggest enemy is ambiguity for the encoder</item>
	  <item>The target is encoding of the <gi>text</gi>; the <gi>teiHeader</gi> must simply conform to <ident>tei_all</ident></item>
	</list>
      </div>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
