<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TEI Simple: towards an amenable TEI</title>
        <author>Sebastian Rahtz, Martin Mueller, Brian Pytlik Zillig</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2014-04-21</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>unknown</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>ab initio</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
          <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change n="5" when="2014-05-21" who="Sebastian Rahtz">towards Mellon</change>
      <change n="4" when="2013-12-20" who="Sebastian Rahtz">comments from Lou Burnard</change>
      <change n="3" when="2013-12-08" who="Sebastian Rahtz">rename project, and incorporate comments
        from TEI Board/Council</change>
      <change n="2" when="2013-12-01" who="Sebastian Rahtz">comments from MM and KH</change>
      <change n="1" when="2013-11-27" who="Sebastian Rahtz">initial version</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head><anchor xml:id="SECTION_1001"/>Summary</head>
        <p>TEI Simple aims to define a new <hi rend="italic">highly-constrained</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">prescriptive</hi> subset of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) Guidelines
          suited to the representation of early modern and modern books, a formally-defined set of
          processing rules which permit modern web applications to easily present and analyze the
          encoded texts, mapping to other ontologies, and processes to describe the encoding status
          and richness of a TEI digital text.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head><anchor xml:id="SECTION_1002"/>Background</head>
        <p>The Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) has developed over 20 years into a key technology in
          text-centric humanities disciplines, with an extremely wide range of applications, from
          diplomatic editions to dictionaries, from prosopography to speech transcription and
          linguistic analysis. It has been able to achieve its range of use by adopting a <hi
            rend="italic">descriptive</hi> rather than <hi rend="italic">prescriptive </hi> approach
          , by recommending <hi rend="italic">customization</hi> to suit particular projects, and by
          eschewing any attempt to dictate how the digital texts should be rendered or exchanged.
          However, this flexibility has come at the cost of relatively limited success in
          interoperability. In our view there is a distinct set of uses (primarily in the area of
          digitized ‘European’-style books) that would benefit from a <hi rend="italic"
            >prescriptive</hi> recipe for digital text; this will sit alongside other
          domain-specific, constrained TEI customizations, such as the very successful <hi
            rend="italic">Epidoc</hi> in the epigraphic community. TEI-Simple may become a prototype
          for a new family of constrained customizations. For instance, a TEI Simple MS for
          manuscript based work could be built on top of the ENRICH project, drawing on many of the
          lessons and some of the code for TEI Simple. </p>
        <p>The TEI has long maintained an introductory subset (TEI Lite), and a constrained
          customization for use in outsourcing production to commercial vendors (TEI Tite), but both
          of these permit enormous variation, and have nothing to say about processing. The present
          project can be viewed in some ways as a revision of TEI Lite, re-examining the basis of
          the choices therein, focusing it for a more specific area, and adding a "cradle to grave"
          processing model that associates the TEI Simple schema with explicit and standardized
          options for displaying and querying texts. This means being able to specify what a
          programmer should do with particular TEI elements when they are encountered, allowing
          programmers to build stylesheets that work for everybody and to query a corpus of
          documents reliably.</p>
        <p>This proposal, TEI Simple, will focus on interoperability, machine generation, and
          low-cost integration. The TEI architecture facilitates customizations of many kinds; TEI
          Simple aims to produce a complete 'out of the box' customization which meets the needs of
          the many users for whom the task of creating a customization is daunting or seems
          irrelevant. TEI Simple in no way intends to constrain the expressive liberty of encoders
          who do not think that it is either possible or desirable to follow this path. It does,
          however, promise to make life easier for those who think there is some virtue in
          travelling that path as far as it will take you, which for quite a few projects will be
          far enough. Some users will never feel the need to move beyond it, others will outgrow it,
          and when they do they will have learned enough to do so.</p>
        <p>‘Comparability and interoperability with other resources’ are an increasingly important
          topic on various Digital Humanities agendas. Echoes of it are found in a recent ‘work set
          construction’ Mellon grant to the Hathi Trust Research Centre. Under the heading
          ‘Wissenschaftliche Sammlungen’ it is a major part of an ambitious DARIAH project anchored
          at the SUB Göttingen. Progress towards it may be slow, tedious, and partial, but
          ‘simplicity, interoperability, broad use and reuse’, and ‘comparability and
          interoperability with other resources’ are important goals to keep in mind for many
          purposes. For a lot of current and future users of the TEI the really important benefits
          come from the simple stuff, and beyond some level of complexity they begin to feel some
          sympathy with Andrew Prescott's not very kind phrase about ‘angels dancing on angle
            brackets.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">In “Consumers, creators or
            commentators? Problems of audience and mission in the digital humanities “; Arts and
            Humanities in Higher Education published online 1 December 2011,
            http://ahh.sagepub.com/content/early/2011/11/30/1474022211428215</note></p>
        <p>A major driver for this project is the texts created by phase 1 of the EEBO-TCP project,
          which will be placed in the public domain on 1 January 2015. Another 45,000 texts will
          join over the following five years, creating by 2020 an archive of 70,000 consistently
          encoded books published in England from 1475 to 1700, including works of literature,
          philosophy, politics, religion, geography, science and all other areas of human endeavor.
          When we compare the query potential of the EEBO TCP texts in their current and quite
          simple encoding with flat file versions of those text, it is clear that the difference in
          query potential is very high, especially if you add to that coarse encoding simple forms
          of linguistic annotation or named entity tagging that can be added in a largely
          algorithmic fashion. During 2012 and 2013 extensive work has been undertaken at
          Northwestern, Michigan and Oxford to enrich these texts and bring them into line with the
          current TEI Guidelines (where necessary working with the TEI to modify the Guidelines).
          TEI Simple will use this corpus as a point of departure and will provide its users with a
          friendlier environment for manipulating EEBO texts in various projects. But TEI Simple
          should not be understood as an EEBO specific project. We believe that, given the
          extraordinary degree of internal diversity in the EEBO source files, a project that starts
          from them can, with appropriate modifications, accommodate a wide range of printed texts
          differing in language, genre, or time and place of origin. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head><anchor xml:id="SECTION_1003"/>Summary of objectives</head>
        <p>TEI Simple has the following high-level objectives:</p>
        <list type="ordered">
          <item>Definition of a new <hi rend="italic">highly constrained</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
              >prescriptive</hi> subset of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) Guidelines suited to
            the representation of early modern and modern books. .</item>
          <item>Creation of a notation (as an extension to TEI's ODD metalanguage) for specifying
            processing rules for TEI encoded texts,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">The paper
              on “Documenter des “attentes applicatives” (processing expectations)” by Frédéric
              Glorieux and Vincent Jolivet at TEI Members Meeting 2013
              (http://digilab2.let.uniroma1.it/teiconf2013/program/papers/abstracts-paper/ ) also
              addresses this area.</note> referencing web standards such as XPath, CSS and XSL
            FO.</item>
          <item>Reference implementations of processing rules defined for this TEI subset.</item>
          <item>Formal mapping of the TEI elements used by Simple to the CIDOC CRM, allowing for
            full interoperability with the Europeana Data Model, in order to facilitate the
            participation of projects in open data repositories.</item>
          <item>Definition and implementation of machine-readable descriptions of the encoding
            status and richness of TEI texts, providing a “TEI Performance Indicators” indicating to
            a user what they can expect to use the text for.</item>
        </list>
        <p>The overall aim is to lower the access barriers to working with TEI-encoded texts in various web
          environments. Programmers familiar with a particular web environment, whether Django,
          Drupal, eXist, Ruby on Rails, or others will be able to integrate TEI Simple-based
          projects into their environment with moderate effort and with no more than their usual
          tools and skills.</p>
        <p>The project will adhere to the following principles:</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>As little overlap as possible, and as much compatibility as possible, with existing
            repository projects</item>
          <item>At least as prescriptive as level 3 of the <hi rend="italic">Best Practices for TEI
              in Libraries</hi></item>
          <item>Encompassing I18N principles at all times</item>
          <item>Useable implementations of all features</item>
        </list>
        <p>Outcomes from TEI Simple, consisting of a documented definition in ODD of the TEI subset,
          a set of processing rules, and extensions to the TEI ODD language to record processing
          expectations, will be fully integrated into the TEI infrastructure with ongoing
          maintenance by the TEI Technical Council.</p>
        <p>TEI Simple is intended to be <hi rend="italic">complementary</hi> to community projects
          like the TAPAS project, and to the established work of TextGrid, the German Text Archive
          (the DTA ‘base format’, which shares many of the goals of TEI Simple) and other national
          projects.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
	<head>Objective 1: constrained subset of the TEI</head>
	<p>The project  will specify a subset of the TEI sufficient to encompass, at a minimum, the current practices of the TCP's EEBO, ECCO,
            and Evans collections plus those of other major European initiatives such as Text Grid
            or the DTA in Germany, and the Consortium Cahier in France. This subset will include mandatory vocabularies for <att>type</att> attributes, 
	    and more constrained content models for some elements, aiming to reduce the number of ways an encoder can record the semantics of the digital text.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
	<head>Objective 2: definition of a TEI processing model</head>
	<p>The project will develop a notation by which a TEI profile
	can express how documents which meet that profile can be
	published or made accessible. TEI elements are generally
	<emph>descriptive</emph> of the interpreted semantics of the
	source text (<q>this is a title</q>, <q>this is a
	quotation</q>), where the interpretation is often based on a
	human interpretation of layout. The <att>rend</att> attribute
	is sometimes, but not necessarily, used to describe that
	layout. The resulting encoded text is very amenable to
	analysis, but for the common case of re-presenting the text on
	the web, there TEI semantic model is incomplete.</p>

        <p>The processing model notation will allow each element to be
        assigned to a category, according to a taxonomy whose first
        draft is in Table <ptr target="#pitax"/>. This allows a
        processor to know whether to handle the element or not, and
        broadly speaking how to display or otherwise process it.  The
        notation will probably use XPath, as the constraint language
        Schematron does, refine a simple element name. The model
        instructions will be embedded in the TEI ODD customization, and
	a workflow will be specified for how implementations should access that information.</p>

        <table xml:id="pitax">
          <head>A preliminary processing categorisation</head>
          <row role="label">
            <cell>Category</cell>
            <cell>Meaning</cell>
            <cell>Example</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>metadata header</cell>
            <cell>fileDesc</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>2</cell>
            <cell>section heading</cell>
            <cell>head[parent::div]</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>3</cell>
            <cell>title of object (figure, table etc)</cell>
            <cell>head[not(parent::div)]</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>structural division</cell>
            <cell>div</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>5</cell>
            <cell>uncategorized block level object</cell>
            <cell>quotation</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>semantic block level object</cell>
            <cell>person</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>uncategorized inline object</cell>
            <cell>hi</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>semantic inline object</cell>
            <cell>persName</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>list</cell>
            <cell>list</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>10</cell>
            <cell>list item</cell>
            <cell>item</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>11</cell>
            <cell>table</cell>
            <cell>table</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>12</cell>
            <cell>cell</cell>
            <cell>cell</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>13</cell>
            <cell>row</cell>
            <cell>row</cell>
          </row>
          <row><cell>14</cell><cell>out of line note</cell><cell>note</cell></row>
          <row>
            <cell>15</cell>
            <cell>figure</cell>
            <cell>figure</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>16</cell>
            <cell>pointer</cell>
            <cell>ptr</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>17</cell>
            <cell>Janus element (alternate children)</cell>
            <cell>choice</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>18</cell>
            <cell>modern commentary element</cell>
            <cell>desc</cell>
          </row>
        </table>

      </div>
      <div>
	<head>Objective 3: development of the processing model for Simple</head>
        <p>Using the processing model notation, the categories are
        mapped to a presentation format for a given project, using
        HTML and CSS concepts where possible; for example, if we know that a certain construct maps to a <emph>janus</emph> presentation, the 
	project will dictate whether this is to be presented using colours, pop-ups or notes. We will develop
        these rules for TEI Simple, and the DiXiT project (<ptr
        target="http://dixit.uni-koeln.de/home.html?&amp;L=1"/>) will
        experiment with the same notation in the field of digital
        scholarly editions.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
	<head>Objective 4: Reference implementations of processing rules</head>
	<p>To implement the presentation of a text using its processing model, a normalized set of property values will be created for each
        element, where the base model is combined with any information from <emph>rend</emph>, <emph>rendition</emph> and
        <emph>style</emph> attributes, and the <gi>rendition</gi> element, 
        to produce a map to  names and allowed values for HTML and  CSS. This  allows a processor to work
        out how to present that element in the current context in a web page or ePub document.</p>
        <p>Although our primary target is the web, processors will also be create a variety of other outputs without having to maintain specific rule
          sets for TEI Simple, by translating the high-level presentation notation into, eg, TeX, Word or OpenOffice. The implementation of this will 
	  build on the existing  "TEI to XXX" stylesheets
          (<ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets"/>) maintained for the TEI Consortium.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
	<head>Objective 5: mapping of Simple to RDF</head>
	<p>Although simple presentation in web pages is an important
	aim of Simple, it is also important that the structural and
	semantic markup is able to be represented in the open data
	interchange format of RDF.  Several investigations and proofs
	of concept have demonstrated a close relationship between much
	of the TEI and the CIDOC CRM ontology. The TEI ODD already has
	a notation (the <gi>equiv</gi> element) for expressing the
	relationship between TEI and RDF, and this will be used
	(possibly with proposed extensions to the ODD language) to
	secure map all the elements of Simple to the CRM and
	FRBRoo. The implementation of this will follow that of the
	processing model, and be embedded in the same transformation
	toolset.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
	<head>Objective 6: definition of machine-readable text profile</head>
	<p>Although SImple is designed to be very constrained, it will
	still allow for many choices by the encoder. Do they choose,
	for example, to explicitly identify names of people and
	places? Will they mark where spelling has been normalized?
	Will all the words be marked with part of speech information
	for linguistic analysis? This will affect the <emph>query
	potential</emph> of a corpus of texts, and cannot be done
	simply by analysing the markup<note place="foot">The absence
	of <gi>persName</gi> markup may be because the encoderhas
	decided not to distinguish them, or because there are no
	names.</note> The TEI already has extensive provision in the
	metadata header for describing the encoding decisions which
	have been made, but this is largely targetted at storing
	human-readable notes, and is thus not machine readable. This
	objective is to develop and implement an extra level of
	notation aimed at automatically profiling a text.</p>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Programme of work and budget</head>
        <p>We propose a total budget of $100,000, divided into labour costs ($36,000), travel and
          meeting costs ($59,000), and a contingency fund ($5000). </p>

        <p>The work will be undertaken in three ways: <list type="ordered">
            <item>Contributed time and expertise by members of the advisory panel, and other members
              of the TEI community, in consultation events.</item>
            <item>Technical development sprints during which the core programming tasks will be
              completed, in some cases as a group activity at the same location.</item>
            <item>Outputs commissioned at an agreed cost from partner organisations or individuals,
              under supervision of one of the PIs.</item>
          </list> The aim is to ensure that payments from the project are tied to explicit
          deliverables.</p>

        <table>
          <head>Project tasks</head>
          <row n="1">
            <cell/>
            <cell>Task</cell>
            <cell>Activity</cell>
            <cell>Method</cell>
            <cell>Participants (leader in bold)</cell>
            <cell>Date</cell>
          </row>
          <row n="2">
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>Management</cell>
            <cell>Overseeing the progress of the project</cell>
            <cell>Two face to face meetings of the PIs and advisory group; monthly video-conference
              management meetings</cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Rahtz</hi>, Mueller, Pytlig Zillig</cell>
          </row>
          <row n="3">
            <cell>2</cell>
            <cell>Simple subset of TEI</cell>
            <cell>Definition of the prescriptive subset of the TEI, expressed as an ODD
              customization</cell>
            <cell>Workshop sprint (3 days)</cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Mueller</hi>, Burnard, Cummings, Geyken, Glorieux, Burnard, Pytlig
              Zillig, Rahtz</cell>
          </row>
          <row n="4">
            <cell>3</cell>
            <cell>Model notation</cell>
            <cell>Extension to the TEI ODD language to support processing expectations</cell>
            <cell>Workshop (3 days)</cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Rahtz</hi>, Cummings, Glorieux, Jolivet, Turska</cell>
          </row>
          <row n="5">
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>Model for Simple</cell>
            <cell>Definition of processing expectations for TEI Simple, using the model
              notation</cell>
            <cell>Workshop sprint</cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Rahtz</hi>, Cummings, Jolivet, Pytlig Zillig, Turska</cell>
          </row>
          <row n="6">
            <cell>5</cell>
            <cell>Model Implementation </cell>
            <cell>Implementation of processing expectations, as a rewrite of the TEI XSLT
              stylesheets</cell>
            <cell>Workshop sprint (5 days)</cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Pytlig Zillig</hi>, Rahtz, Turska</cell>
          </row>
          <row n="7">
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>Documentation</cell>
            <cell>Maintainable open access documentation for TEI Simple</cell>
            <cell>Continuous refinement</cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Mueller</hi>, contractor TBD</cell>
          </row>
          <row n="8">
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>Mapping to RDF</cell>
            <cell>Mapping TEI Simple to other ontologies, eg CIDOC CRM, expressing the mapping using
              the TEI ODD language</cell>
            <cell>Continuous refinement</cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Rahtz</hi>, contractor TBD</cell>
          </row>
          <row n="9">
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>Profile markup</cell>
            <cell>Development of a markup system for recording the formal profile of a text</cell>
            <cell>Workshop sprint (3 days)</cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Pytlig Zillig</hi>, Geyken, Glorieux, Mueller, Turska</cell>
          </row>
          <row n="10">
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>Profile implementation</cell>
            <cell>Implementation of profile reporting</cell>
            <cell>Continuous refinement</cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Pytlig Zillig</hi>, Geyken, contractor TBD</cell>
          </row>
          <row n="11">
            <cell>10</cell>
            <cell>Integration into TEI</cell>
            <cell>Integration of TEI Simple into the Guidelines and other TEI Consortium
              infrastructure</cell>
            <cell><hi rend="bold">Cummings</hi>, Burnard, Rahtz</cell>
          </row>
          <row n="12">
            <cell>11</cell>
            <cell>User validation</cell>
            <cell>Explanation and demonstration of TEI Simple to check that user requirements are
              being met </cell>
            <cell>Open workshop at midpoint of project (2 days, local expenses only)</cell>
          </row>
        </table>

        <p>The following people will work on TEI Simple over the course of the project lifetime: <table>
            <row role="label">
              <cell>Name</cell>
              <cell>Institution</cell>
              <cell>Project role</cell>
              <cell>Expertise</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Sebastian Rahtz</cell>
              <cell>University of Oxford</cell>
              <cell>PI</cell>
              <cell>TEI processing, ODD language</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Martin Mueller</cell>
              <cell>University of Nebrasks</cell>
              <cell>PI</cell>
              <cell>Re-useable digital text, analysis</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Brian Pytlik Zillig</cell>
              <cell>Northwestern University</cell>
              <cell>PI</cell>
              <cell>Normalizing text corpora</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Lou Burnard</cell>
              <cell>independent consultant</cell>
              <cell>contractor</cell>
              <cell>TEI design and semantics</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>James Cummings</cell>
              <cell>University of Oxford</cell>
              <cell>contractor</cell>
              <cell>TEI re-use and processing</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Frédéric Glorieux</cell>
              <cell>Université Paris-Sorbonne</cell>
              <cell>TEI processing</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Vincent Jolivet</cell>
              <cell>Université Paris-Sorbonne</cell>
              <cell/>
              <cell>TEI processing</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Alexander Geyken</cell>
              <cell>Deutsches Textarchiv (DTA)</cell>
              <cell>Normalizing text corpora</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Magdalena Turska</cell>
              <cell>University of Oxford</cell>
              <cell>Developer</cell>
              <cell>TEI processing</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        </p>

        <p>Costs are calculated on the following basis <list type="ordered">
            <item>The time of Pytlig Zillig, Mueller, Geyken, Glorieux and Jolivet will be
              contributed by their organizations</item>
            <item>Expert advisors and technical contractors will be paid, to a maximum of $350 a day
              FTE</item>
            <item>Travel and living expenses will be paid for all attendees at workshops and
              development sprints</item>
            <item>Local expenses only will be paid for the open workshop</item>
            <item>Commissioned outputs managed by one of the PIs are allocated a number of days
              technical assistance which they can use to pay individuals or organisations</item>
          </list>
        </p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head><anchor xml:id="SECTION_1005"/>Collaboration, management, timing</head>
        <p>TEI Simple is a cross-Atlantic collaboration between (at least) the following
          partners:</p>
        <list type="ordered">
          <item>Northwestern University, Chicago: Professor Martin Mueller</item>
          <item>The University of Oxford: Sebastian Rahtz</item>
          <item>The Text Encoding Initiative Consortium: Elena Pierazzo (Chair)</item>
          <item>The University of Nebraska: Brian Pytlik Zillig</item>
          <item>Université Paris-Sorbonne: Frédéric Glorieux</item>
          <item>The Deutsches Textarchiv (DTA): Alexander Geyken</item>
          <item>TextGrid</item>
        </list>
        <p>TEI Simple will commence work on 1st August 2014, and aim to complete the first stage of
          work in time for the TEI Annual Meeting in late October 2014. The launch at the Annual
          Meeting will be followed by eight more months of development and revision before final
          sign-off on July 1st 2015.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Curricula vitae</head>
        <div>
          <head>Sebastian Rahtz</head>
          <p>Sebastian Rahtz is Director (Research) of Academic IT in the University of Oxford IT
            Services, and leads for the department on research support, open source support,
            research data management, open data, and information strategy. He is a member of IT
            Services Senior Management team, and represents IT Services on a variety of university
            committees.</p>
          <p>On the research side, Sebastian is technical director for
          the data store of the CLAROS project
          (http://www.clarosnet.org/), based in the Oxford e-Research
          Centre, and directs its work on geolocation models and data.
          He maintains the input of the Lexicon of Greek Personal Names
          project at Oxford to CLAROS and to the SNAP:DRGN project, and
          assists the Lexicon of Greek Personal Names in its
          typesetting and sustainability activities. He provides
          extensive editorial and development work to the Text
          Encoding Initiative (TEI) Consortium
          (http://www.tei-c.org/), for which he has served on its
          Technical Council since 2001.</p>
          <p>Sebastian has led a number of successful funding bids in
          the last decade: the OSS Watch (http://www.oss-watch.ac.uk),
          open source advisory service, which he directed from
          2003-2007; the OXCRI project (2006) to implement XCRI to
          describe Oxford courses; and,
          the Erewhon project (http://erewhon.oucs.ox.ac.uk/)
          (2008-2010) to investigate mobile access and geolocation of
          university resources. He was co-leader of Oxford
          participation in the EU-funded ENRICH project on manuscript
          encoding (http://enrich.manuscriptorium.com/). Sebastian has
          taught on the Digital Humanities at Oxford Summer School
          since 2008, is a regular speaker at digital humanities and
          text encoding conference, and teaches TEI workshops.</p>
          <p>Sebastian has authored and maintains a wide portfolio of open source software in the
            area of TEI and TeX typesetting. </p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Martin Mueller</head>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Brian Pytlik Zillig</head>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Lou Burnard</head>
          <p>Formerly assistant director at Oxford University Computing Services, Lou Burnard is one
            of the original editors of the TEI Guidelines and has been closely involved with the TEI
            throughout its evolution. He is an Oxford graduate with a Masters degree in English
            Language and Literature who has worked at the frontier between computing and the
            humanities since the 1970s, when he founded the Oxford Text Archive. During the nineties
            and noughties he was responsible for many other key developments in what we now call the
            digital humanities, notably the British National Corpus, and the UK's Arts and
            Humanities Data Service. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>James Cummings</head>
<p>James Cummings is the Senior Digital Research Specialist for the IT
Services of the University of Oxford. He helps academics from the
Humanities and Social Sc§qiences plan research projects with digital
aspects, and is the department's liaison for Digital Humanities at
Oxford activities. James is Director of the annual week-long Digital
Humanities at Oxford Summer School. James often acts as a liaison
between developers and researchers, sometimes taking on principal
investigator or project management aspects of digital humanities
projects. He still does some active coding and development on
workpackages related to XML, markup, schemas and digital editions. He
is the Oxford principal investigator for the Marie Curie ITN 'DiXiT'
on digital scholarly editions.</p>
<p>Since 2005 he has been an elected member to the Text Encoding
Initiative Consortium's Technical Council and is now its Chair. This
technical council develops new features and fixes bugs in the TEI
Guidelines for encoding digital text, and undertakes other activities
related to supporting this standard. James has a great deal of
experience in teaching digital publishing concepts and XML-related
technologies.</p>
<p>James completed a PhD in medieval drama from the University of
Leeds, an MA in Medieval Studies from the University of Leeds, and a
BA in Medieval Studies from the University of Toronto. His PhD
investigates the archival survival of information concerning the
performance of drama in medieval culture. It involved a significant
amount of archival transcription.</p>
<p>In addition to the archival survival of information about early
performance, the relationship of medieval manuscripts to their digital
surrogates is one of his interests. From 2009-2012 he was the elected
director of the executive board of the Digital Medievalist
project. </p>
<p>In addition to the work on TEI-Simple, James plans to use it as a
starting point for a schema targetting scholarly digital editions of
medieval manuscripts.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Magdalena Turska</head>
          <list type="gloss">
            <label>April 2014</label>
            <item>Researcher for the Digital Scholarly Editions IT Services, University of Oxford.
              Fellow of the Marie Curie DiXiT (Digital Scholarly Editions Initial Training Network)
              project responsible for requirements and development of a modular publication
              architecture targeting multiple media</item>
            <label>2007-2014</label>
            <item>Laboratory for Editing Sources, Faculty „Artes Liberales”, University of Warsaw.
              Co-author of “Corpus of Ioannes Dantiscus’ Texts and Correspondence”
              (dantiscus.al.uw.edu.pl) responsible for TEI/XML encoding policies, design and
              implementation of software for on-line and printed scholarly editions of renaissance
              correspondence and other manuscript sources encoded with TEI/XML </item>
            <label>1999 – 2014</label>
            <item> Faculty „Artes Liberales”, University of Warsaw, Poland. Lecturer (computer
              workshops for students &amp; staff) and academic research IT support</item>
            <label>2003 – 2014</label>
            <item>InviMed – developer (PHP), Poland. Software system for patients’ medical records
              for InviMed fertility clinics nationwide</item>
          </list>
        </div>



      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
